<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sober ansvvere to an angry pamphlet, or, Animadversions, by way of reply, to Robert Barclays late book (entituled, Truth cleared of calumnies) in answere to A dialogue between a Quaker and a stable Christian by VVilliam Mitchell.</title>
            <author>Mitchell, William, 17th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1671</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 224 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 75 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89189</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2294</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R43708</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">42475119</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 42475119</idno>
            <idno type="VID">151253</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89189)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 151253)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2252:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sober ansvvere to an angry pamphlet, or, Animadversions, by way of reply, to Robert Barclays late book (entituled, Truth cleared of calumnies) in answere to A dialogue between a Quaker and a stable Christian by VVilliam Mitchell.</title>
                  <author>Mitchell, William, 17th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 133 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Forbes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Aberdene :</pubPlace>
                  <date>An. 1671.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. [15]</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained, tightly bound, and with print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Newberry Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Barclay, Robert, 1648-1690. --  Truth cleared of calumnies.</term>
               <term>Mitchell, William, 17th cent. --  Dialogue between a Quaker and a stable Christian.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Doctrines.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:151253:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SOBER ANSVVERE, TO AN ANGRY PAMPHLET: OR, ANIMADVERSIONS, By way of Reply, to <hi>Robert Barclays</hi> late Book (entituled, <hi>Truth cleared of Calumnies</hi>) in anſwere to <hi>a Dialogue between a Quaker and a Stable CHRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STIAN.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By VVILLIAM MITCHELL.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.24.</bibl>
               <p>For there ſhall ariſe falſe Chriſts, and falſe Prophets, and ſhall ſhew great ſignes and wonders: inſomuch that (if it were poſſible) they ſhal deceive the very Elect,</p>
               <bibl>2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.17.</bibl>
               <p>Ye therefore, Beloved, ſeeing ye know theſe things before, beware leſt ye alſo being led away with the errour of the wicked, fall from your own ſtedfaſtneſs.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Aberdene, Printed by <hi>Iohn Forbes,</hi> An. 1671</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:151253:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:151253:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>An Epiſtle to ROBERT BARCLAY, VVhich may ſerve for an Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition to the Quakers in and about ABERDENE.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I have conſidered the Preface prefixed to your book, wherein you give an account of the riſe of <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keriſme</hi> in this place (under the notion of the LORDS raiſing up the witneſſes of this day) and the oppoſition it met with. And <hi>First,</hi> It is alledged that your ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed witneſſes (and yet real enough in bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing teſtimony againſt the truth) were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached as <hi>demented diſtracted and bodily poſſeſſed.</hi> Sir, did you ever hear any ſpeak (in this place) thus of Quakers? Or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb facs="tcp:151253:3"/>
are you not too apt to take things upon truſt; without weighing what truth or falſhood may be in a report? Yet it is not to be thought ſtrange, though Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers had been charged with all this: when as men of Faith, Credit, and eminent Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, (in our neighbour Nation) have teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied of <hi>their extraordinary quaking, going naked in the ſtreets,</hi> (even the women of them) and ſome pretending to a power of raiſing <hi>the Dead:</hi> and for this end taking <hi>them</hi> out of their Graves, calling <hi>them</hi> by name to ariſe and walk; but their inef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual attempts of this kind, made them to returne covered with confuſion and ſhame, and yet as much hardened in their deluſions as ever! See <hi>Sam Clarks Mir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, pag.</hi> 259. 262. 263. 267. See the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Phariſee,</hi> publiſhed by the Miniſters of <hi>New-Castle pag</hi> 41. 48. ſee <hi>Pagits Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiography pag.</hi> 250. 257.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly</hi> You ſay they were called no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing better then <hi>Iohn of Leyden, and his Complices.</hi> Sir, I hope you are not ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant that <hi>Iohn of Leyden, and thoſe that followed him,</hi> were much led by revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb facs="tcp:151253:3"/>
and delivered their Doctrines, as being moved of GOD; and that with as much confidence as any of <hi>you</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend unto: And at firſt they ſpake againſt <hi>bearing Armes</hi> and would not ſuffer a man to weare a <hi>Ring,</hi> nor a woman a <hi>Silken Gowne:</hi> they made a great ſhew of Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and their ordinary communication was about Mortification. But what their after carriage was, we are ſufficiently in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by thoſe that have written of their principles; and of their practiſes, ſee <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gits Hereſiography, pag.</hi> 13.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> You ſpeake of ſome <hi>ſerious and ſober profeſſours in and about Aberdene, who (in the year</hi> 1663.) <hi>began to find the Savour of that Life, in the teſtimony of that ſo much reproached people, which ſome yeares before had ſtirred in others.</hi> Sir, that people whom you call ſo <hi>much reproached,</hi> have with very much bitterneſs reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed others: and caſt as much obloquie u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the beſt perſons that have differed from them as ever a generation of men did: Are not their opprobrious termes ſo far from any good ſavour, that they rather
<pb facs="tcp:151253:4"/>
ſavour of a Spirit of rancour, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wray a root of bitterneſs to be within?</p>
            <p>And let not Quakers think to ſhelter themſelves under the practiſe of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, who were wont to ſpeake of Phariſees, and other open enemies of the Goſpel: as being a viperous Generation, children of Hell and of the Devil; now let us ſearch the records of Scripture, and (as I ſuppoſe) it will not be found that Chriſt and his Apoſtles carried thus: to thoſe that profeſſed ſubjection to the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, and owned Chriſt to be the <hi>Meſsiah,</hi> ſhewing earneſtneſs of deſire, that Souls might be ſaved: being willing to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny courſe for promoting and furthering this great and glorious deſigne.</p>
            <p>And Sir, becauſe you ſpeak of Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours who had found that ſavour of life in the teſtimony of Quakers, which before had ſtirred in others: It is probable you will not take it well, to ſay, that <hi>thoſe others</hi> were <hi>Ignatius Loyola</hi> and <hi>his followers;</hi> and yet in very deed, the Quakers carriage is very like unto theirs: which <hi>Doctor Stil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingfleet</hi> (in his late book <hi>of the Idolatry of
<pb facs="tcp:151253:4"/>
the Church of Rome</hi>) notably demonſtrats; there he tels of a <hi>Sect</hi> in <hi>Spaine</hi> called <hi>Alum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brado s,</hi> or the <hi>Illuminati:</hi> this Sect under a pretence of mental prayer, divine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation, and union with GOD, they deſpyſed Sacraments and Religious exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes. Of this <hi>Sect Ignatius Loyola,</hi> the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Ieſuits, was vehemently ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to be. Thoſe of his own order who have write his life <hi>(Maffeius, Orlandinus)</hi> ſay; Firſt, that it was his cuſtome not to give men any <hi>titles of reſpect,</hi> but to call them by their <hi>common names,</hi> and reſolved he would not break this cuſtome: becauſe to do it; proceeded from too great fear of men. Secondly, He preacht in an <hi>Enthu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiastical manner,</hi> going up and down the ſtreets: preaching to all perſons, and to all ſorts of men; and being examined, confeſſed he was unlearned. Thirdly, When afterwards he was committed to priſon, he preacht to people with great zeale, and they gloried much in <hi>his ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings:</hi> and the reſt of the priſoners making their eſcape by the negligence of the keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, <hi>Ignatius</hi> and <hi>his adherents</hi> would not
<pb facs="tcp:151253:5"/>
ſtirr. Fourthly, Being to forme a ſocie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty, he had for that purpoſe uſed himſelf to all the Arts of inſinuation imaginable<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> obliging men with expreſſions of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt kindneſs, bearing all affronts with won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful diſſimulation. Fifthly, Having gotten perſons to be of his mind, <hi>he</hi> uſed all means to prevent any difference hape<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning among them. Sixthly, They preach in the ſtreets and market places; and in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vited people to hear <hi>him:</hi> and no doub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> (ſaith my Learned Authour) he converted many from the uſe of <hi>laces and ribbands</hi> And ſaith he, <hi>I know not whether any of the in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nocent &amp; religious order of the Ieſuits had any hand of forming this new Society among us (as hath been frequently ſuggested) but if one may gueſs the father by the childs likneſs,</hi> Ignatius Loyola <hi>the Founder of the Ieſuits, was at leaſt the Grand-Father of the Quakers.</hi> See theſe things at length, in the above mentioned Treatiſe, <hi>pag.</hi> 305. 313. 314. 315. 316. 317. 320. 321. 324. 325.</p>
            <p>Moreover <hi>Sir,</hi> If you would have others to ſavour and reliſh life in your teſtimony, ye muſt ſtudy more <hi>ſelf-denyal,</hi> and ſhew
<pb facs="tcp:151253:5"/>
forth <hi>first, leſs pride,</hi> be not too big in your own conceit, conſider <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> 65.5. Even be content with Burying places, that bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then your ſelves do lye in; and do not ſeperat from us as <hi>children of Heth:</hi> this is intolerable ſaucineſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Shew forth <hi>leſs paſsion and anger,</hi> the Scripture ſaith the Man of GOD muſt be gentle and meek, 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.25. reviling doth better become <hi>Shimei's</hi> then <hi>Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly;</hi> Shew forth <hi>leſs cenſoriouſneſs,</hi> do not ſay that men (who can manifeſt their ſpiritual deſcent from Chriſt upon as ſure grounds, if not ſurer grounds, then any Quaker) are ſmothering and reſiſting the Light, becauſe (forſooth) they will not dance after your pipe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Shew forth <hi>leſs folly:</hi> It would be your wiſdom to be well acquainted with your own hearts, and not to pretend ſo much to the knowledge of other mens hearts; when as it may be, ye know not their names.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly;</hi> Shew forth <hi>leſs contrariety</hi> in your doctrines to the good and holy word
<pb facs="tcp:151253:6"/>
of GOD. Set not your ſelves againſt the ordinances of Chriſt, and Iuſtification by his imputed Righteouſneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> Shew forth <hi>leſs ignorance,</hi> as to the nature of true Converſion: <hi>crying out againſt formes, and wearing of ribbands, ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thou and thee, and keeping on the hatt, condemning all that are not of your gang, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ye were never well till now,</hi> (which is a great part of the Religion of many of your Proſelytes) will never prove you nor them to be true Converts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seventhly,</hi> Shew forth <hi>leſs endeavours</hi> for promoting the Popiſh intereſt, if ye were under their hire, ye could not advance their intereſt more, then by decrying our Miniſtry and Churches: when once ye have perſwaded people to the belief of this, then they are fit matter for Prieſts to work upon: and they cannot but thank you, for doing their work to their hands. Sir, if you liſten not to my advice, yet I have followed my Light in tendering it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you.</p>
            <p>Sir, in the cloſe of your preface, you fall foule upon the <hi>Authour</hi> of the Dialogue
<pb facs="tcp:151253:6"/>
as having deceitfully miſrepreſented the Quakers, which is a crime he is not ſenſible of: for his deſigne in the Dialogue, was not to tell the world all the Scriptures which the Quakers abuſe; but onely to give a true information of the groſſeſt of their opinions, (and briefly to anſwere ſome of their arguments, and to lay down Scripture grounds for inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the ignorant, and confirming the weak in the truth) which He was in ſome capacity to do, having exchanged ſeveral papers with Quakers: and would have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in replying to their papers; but that he was told, it would prove no better, then (according to the proverb) <hi>lis Ptolemaica,</hi> that is, a long and conſtant ſtrief: Quakers (as he heard) being like ſome froward and ſcolding women, who will be ſure to have the laſt word: and indeed after this, he is reſolved to let <hi>Mr. Barclay</hi> have it.</p>
            <p>Some are of opinion that Quakers are of their nature, who are beſt appeaſed by ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect; and ſooneſt quieted by ſilence: and yet a total neglect of them (though they be contemptible in the eyes of many) may
<pb facs="tcp:151253:7"/>
make them formidable.</p>
            <p>Sir, It is altogether unneceſſary to be at paines in ripping up your <hi>wild compariſons,</hi> it were eaſie to be ſharp in <hi>reflections;</hi> but <hi>theſe things</hi> can neither commend to GOD, nor good men: and therefore deſiring you, and your brethren would allow ſome time for reading this my Anſwer: (which was in readineſs diverſe moneths ago; but a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient opportunity was wanting to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh it till now) I take my leave, <hi>wiſhing the LORD the great and Mighty GOD to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend his Power and Mercy for your recovery: and that he would reclaime you according to the working whereby he is able to ſubdue all to himſelf. Philipp.</hi> 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 21.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>W. M.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:151253:7"/>
            <head>The Epiſtle to the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IF a perſon who (really) affects retirement, hath ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventured thus to appear in publick (when hereby he brings himſelf under the laſh of the cenſures of many, which otherwiſe he might eſcape) his plea is, that Truth (even the leaſt graine of truth) is ſo choice, and precious: that it calls to the denyal of theſe things which would ſtand in the way, and hinder an under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking of the defence of it.</p>
            <p>If it be ſaid, that an abler hand had been meeter for a work of this importance: the Authours apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy is, that what is done, needs be no impediment to others; but rather a provocation of them to appeare for the interest of truth which is ſo much trampled upon: in the meane time let none find fault with the Authour for doing that, which in other caſes paſſeth for good ſervice: when a houſe is on fire, he that brings water to quench it, though (it may be) he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute but a little help; yet he is not blamed but en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged. Now the flame of errour has more danger in it, then a flame of fire: and therefore an endeavour to quench it, cannot be juſtly cenſured.</p>
            <p>In caſe the Author be twitted with this, that he has
<pb facs="tcp:151253:8"/>
done nothing, but what was done before: his anſwere is, that if the adverſaries of truth, have been at paine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to pluck out of the dunghill of Hereſie old errours, and to ſend them abroad in a new dreſs: then the authour ſhould not be quarrelled with; for making uſe of theſe weapons, by which heretofore good old truths have been defended: And he further ſaith, that Popery from the mouth of a Quaker will be ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed downe by ſome (as glorious diſcoveries) who yet would not liſten to a Popiſh Prieſt ſpeaking the ſame things? And therefore the Authour thinks that it may be good ſervice to well meaning people, to take off the Quakers arguments, by the ſame anſweres which PROESTANTS have uſed againſt Papiſts: that ſo it may appear, that Quakers and Papiſts are ſailing in one boat, though their faces look ſeveral wayes; but not willing to detaine the Reader any longer, from peruſing the following Treatiſe: which that it may be bleſſed for reducing the miſlead, and eſtabliſhing thoſe that yet ſtand, is, and ſhal be the earneſt deſire of him, who is</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy Servant for Chriſts ſake. <hi>William Mitchell.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:151253:8"/>
            <head>GOOD READER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Be pleaſed to do Me that favour, as to correct with thy pen theſe following miſtakes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Page <hi>16.</hi> line <hi>20</hi> read <hi>incolis.</hi> p. <hi>27.</hi> l. <hi>15.</hi> r. <hi>have not alwayes many.</hi> p. <hi>52.</hi> l. <hi>4.</hi> r. <hi>which is ſaid to be more.</hi> p. <hi>53.</hi> l. <hi>1.</hi> r. <hi>cauſa infirma.</hi> Epiſt. p. <hi>1</hi> l. <hi>1.</hi> r. <hi>reproach,</hi> for <hi>reroach.</hi> p. <hi>16.</hi> l. <hi>20.</hi> r. <hi>its rightly tranſlated,</hi> p. <hi>54.</hi> l. <hi>17.</hi> r. <hi>Now in that he ſaith</hi> p. <hi>94.</hi> l. <hi>23.</hi> r. <hi>repeale.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Reader, there are diverſe othter literal eſcapes, but ſeeing they do not obſcure the ſenſe, its expected thou wilt in charity cover them: If any thing in the book ſeeme dark, I deſire thou wouldſt look into the <hi>Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue,</hi> to which the book hath reference: and by that means, thou mayeſt get ſome clearneſs.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:151253:9"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:151253:9"/>
            <head>Some ANIMADVERTIONS, By way of Reply, to a Book ENTITVLED, TRUTH CLEARED OF CALUMNIES.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>I. HEAD. Wherein the Lawfulneſs of Salutations is juſtified.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT. I.</hi> Concerning Salutations by Geſtures.</head>
                  <head type="sub">THE <hi>AUTHOUR.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>HAving (after the Quaker-rate) ſaluted me with Reproaches, then page</hi> 10. 11. <hi>he tell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth us that Quakers dearly owne Salutations, warranted by the Scriptures, ſuch as Chriſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, and the Saints practiſed, but the ſaluta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that are amongst us, he calleth corrupt and I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrous; and inſtanceth in bowing the Body, and uncovering the head: The reaſon alleadged to prove
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:151253:10"/>
this to be Idolatry, is, becauſe theſe things are the ſignification of our worſhip to GOD, and what is Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious worſhip but that which is given to GOD? Anſwer,</hi> It is true, Religious Worſhip is given to GOD, and its that which is peculiar to GOD, and due to him alone, and giveing to the Creature, what is thus pecular to GOD? Is Idolatry, but bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the body and uncovering of the head is not of this nature. And therefore, <hi>worſhip</hi> is to be diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed, it is either <hi>Civil</hi> or <hi>Sacred,</hi> (this diſtinc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is founded on Scripture, of Civil-worſhip we read, <hi>Luke</hi> 14.10 <hi>Then ſhalt thou have worſhip in the preſence of them that ſit at meat with thee:</hi> We read of Sacred Religious worſhip; <hi>Matth.</hi> 4.10. <hi>Thou ſhalt worſhip the Lord thy God, and him on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhalt thou ſerve.) Civil worſhip</hi> proceedeth from a reverencing of men, for their Stations, Relations, or ſome notable Qualifications, and this kind of <hi>worſhip,</hi> hath been given and received by the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieſt of Saints, (neither is it any where forbidden in Scripture) and ſo <hi>Joſeph</hi> upon his approach to his Father <hi>Jacob, he bowed himſelf with his face to the ground, Geneſis</hi> 48.12. <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Lot bowed themſelves to the Angels,</hi> (ſuppoſing them to be men) <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 18.3. and 19.2. compared with <hi>Heb.</hi> 13 2. and the Angels accepted this worſhip without any reproof of them for it; yea, <hi>Abraham bowed himſelf twice before the people of the land, Gen.</hi> 23.7.12. and though every practiſe of <hi>Abraham</hi> is not to be ſo lowed, yet theſe practiſes which are not
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:151253:10"/>
condemned in Scripture, neither by repehenſion or prohibitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, why ſhould we be blaimed for an imitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Saints in them? Seeing we mantain <hi>Sacred, Religious worſhip</hi> to be due, onely to GOD, and his glory muſt not be given to another as the Papiſts give to their Images, of which one of themſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ffirms, that it is the conſtant opinion of their Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, <hi>that the Image is to be honoured and worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped with the ſame honour and worſhip which is given to him, whoſe Image it is.</hi> None can ſay, <hi>(unleſs they will be peeviſh and perverſe)</hi> that we bow to men, to worſhip GOD, in and by them. It is known that the Papiſts ſpeak of two kinds of Religious wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, <hi>namely, abſolute, which they give to GOD, or the Saints, and relative, which they give to their I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages,</hi> and therefore Papiſts have no advantage, as to their Idolatrous worſhipping of Images, from our allowable practiſe of bowing to men, thereby to teſtify a meer Civil reſpect to them.</p>
                  <p>The Gentle-man diſputeth againſt bowing of the body as Idolatry, but he ſeemeth to juſtify <hi>Moſes</hi> his doing <hi>Obeyſance</hi> to his Father in law; And yet what is <hi>obeyſance,</hi> but civil reverence by bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the body, in token of that regard which we owe to ſome perſon of note?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. II. Concerning Salutations by Words.</head>
                  <p>And as Salutations by <hi>Geſtures</hi> are warranted by
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:151253:11"/>
the Scriptures, ſo likewiſe are Salutations by <hi>words, Ruth</hi> 2. 4. <hi>And behold Boas came from Bethlehem, and ſaid unto the Reapers the Lord be with you, and they anſwered him the Lord bleſs thee.</hi> And that command of Chriſts, (<hi>Matth.</hi> 10.5. <hi>when ye come into an houſe ſalute it;</hi> Its explained by the Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt <hi>Luke, chapter</hi> 10. <hi>verſe</hi> 5. <hi>And into whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver houſe ye enter, first ſay, peace be to this houſe.</hi> Now its known that the Jews in their ordinary Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutations and Greetings, when they wiſhed all hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs unto one another, they expreſſed it thus, <hi>Peace be to You:</hi> And from this, I inferre that bowing of the body, and expreſſing our affections by words, comprehending deſires and good wiſhes, (<hi>though perſons be not friends, but foes, Matth.</hi> 5.47.) is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to Scripture, and the practiſe of renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Saints. As for taking of the Hatt, ſeeing it is not manifeſt from Scripture, that the Saints did wear Hatts, (the word ſo rendred <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.21. is varied on the margine <hi>Turbants,</hi> which were Head-garments peculiar to thoſe Eaſtern Countries) it is no wonder that we do not read of their putting them Off, and yet this being one harmleſs way, whereby we expreſs outward honour to thoſe to whom it is due, why ſhould it be quarrelled againſt? We muſt not think it enough to give Superiours <hi>inward ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,</hi> the Scripture alſo calleth for <hi>outward honour, Levit.</hi> 19.32. <hi>Thou ſhalt riſe up before the hoary head, and honour the face of the old man.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:151253:11"/>
                  <head>SECT. III. Containing an Anſwer to the Quakers Objection.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He ſaith, Its ſtrange that we ſhould ſay (conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering our principles) the kingdom of God conſiſteth not in words, for what is our Preaching, and the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture it ſelf, and the very Goſpell according to us, but a company of words. Anſwer.</hi> Truely by the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures we meane nothing elſe, but that Heavenly Doctrine, thoſe divine inſtructions, or revelation of the mind and will of God, which the Lord exci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and moved Holy men of old, to ſpeake and write for the good of his Church and People, and <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>(or the Goſpel)</hi> according to us, is the doctrine of Chriſt, (the good newes and joyful ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of Salvation by him to poor ſinners) contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the <hi>Scriptures;</hi> And the Preaching of <hi>this Gospell</hi> hath been found the Power of God to the ſalvation of many a Soul, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.16. Now if <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> be for another Goſpel, then they may juſtly be reputed ſubverters of the Chriſtian Religion, and enemies to the Croſs of Chriſt, and therefore liable to that curſe which is threatned <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.8. And likewiſe know, that we uſe to diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the <hi>ſubject matter</hi> of the Scripture, <hi>or the doctrine</hi> which it contains, <hi>and the words or writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings</hi> containing, or expreſſing this Doctrine, the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:151253:12"/>
one is as the Blood, the other as the Veins in which it runneth.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>II. HEAD. Wherein is warranted our way of ſpeaking, in Oppoſition to the Quakers Thou and Thee.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 12. <hi>He findeth fault with me for ſaying, that to whom the ſingular number is agreeable, the plural may be applyed without making a lie, and ſaith the proofes alleadged, evince nothing in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Anſwer.</hi> Though that place <hi>Luke</hi> 22.31. be not underſtood of one, <hi>Excluſively</hi> of others, yet Chriſt there directeth his ſpeach onlie to one, <hi>(viz. Peter)</hi> and he ſaith not (after the Quakers way) Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan hath deſired to have <hi>Thee</hi> and <hi>You,</hi> that he might ſift <hi>Thee</hi> and <hi>You,</hi> but behold Satan hath deſired to have <hi>you,</hi> and to ſift <hi>you</hi> as wheat. It is plaine that the third Epiſtle of <hi>John,</hi> is directed to a ſingle Perſon, verſe 1. <hi>The Elder unto the well beloved Gaius whom I love in the Truth,</hi> and yet verſe 12. the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Ye</hi> know that <hi>our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port</hi> is true. <hi>Job.</hi> 18.2. there <hi>Bildad</hi> ſpeaking to <hi>Job,</hi> ſaith, how long will it be ere <hi>you</hi> make an end of words? I am of that minde, that if our Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors had tranſlated <hi>Attah,</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, not according to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:151253:12"/>
the rigour of <hi>construction,</hi> but as uſe hath made the <hi>propriety</hi> of our Language, that then the Quakers would have kept their old tone, and ſaid <hi>you</hi> inſtead of <hi>thou.</hi> But if men will needs make a contentious buſle about <hi>words,</hi> then let them read and ponder 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.4. <hi>he is proud, knowing nothing, but dot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about queſtions and ſtrifes of words, whereof com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth envy, ſtrife, railings, evil ſurmiſings.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>III. HEAD. Shewing that the Quakers depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture from us, is not to be juſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified by our departing from Papiſts.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>He confeſſeth that when they walked with us, the Lord begat a meaſure of honeſty and integrity in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe of them, turning the bent of their hearts towards him. Anſwer.</hi> By what meanes was this honeſtie and integritie of heart wrought in them? Was it not in the uſe <hi>of theſe very Ordinances</hi> which now they cry down, their conſciences cannot but force ſome of them to an acknowledgement of this? Now when the Lord firſt wrought this integrity in them; what was it that he countenanced for begetting of it? It could not be any <hi>antecedaneous</hi> meaſure of integritie, for they had not integrity before it was wrought, and therefore doubtleſs GOD hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaird
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:151253:13"/>
to his own appointments, bleſſing and mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them effectual.</p>
               <p>May not ſome of the Quakers remember that (even in their walke with us) by ſuch a <hi>Sermon,</hi> and the opening of ſuch a <hi>Scripture,</hi> the bent of their hearts, was drawn <hi>Heaven-wards and GOD wards?</hi> Which though they ſhould refuſe, yet there are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny living Witneſſeſs who have found this effect of <hi>Preaching,</hi> and do remember it, to their unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able comfort.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He addeth page</hi> 13. <hi>That the Lord viſited ſome while they lived among Papists, and at times refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them. Anſ.</hi> The queſtion is whether theſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons were viſited in a way of <hi>converſion,</hi> by Popiſh inventions and traditions? Among Papiſts them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the Scriptures are to be found, and God hath bleſſed to ſome (in times of Popery) the reading of the Scriptures, for their Reformation, and illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation in the knowledge of the truth. When <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> betooke himſelf to the <hi>Auguſtine Monks Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> there he met with a copy of the Latine Bible, which he read with great attention and admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and thereafter ſpent his time in ſearching the Prophetical and Apoſtolical writtings, ſeeking thence to informe himſelf in the knowledge of Gods minde and will. It is known that in the darkeſt times of Poperie, the Lord wanted not his <hi>witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> who ſtood up in defence of the truth, whom the Papiſts (when they could get their hands on them) cruelly butchered and murthered, and the labour of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:151253:13"/>
theſe ſervants of God was nor in vaine, but atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with great ſucceſs.</p>
               <p>Now it remaineth for <hi>him</hi> to prove that ſuch as were converted among Papiſts, were converted by Popery, that is by their invented corruptions. And yet if the primeſt of Quakers were ever ſavingly wrought upon (as I cannot but think, thus it is with ſome of them) the work was begun by the Lords bleſſing, and countenancing theſe ſelf-ſame ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which they reject as our <hi>Traditions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He thinketh it meet to paſs by that objection (cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling it weak) from Solomons ſacrificing at Gibeon. Anſwer.</hi> No wonder if it be <hi>weak,</hi> coming from a feeble perſon, and yet an Apoſtle among the <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers,</hi> namely, <hi>P. L.</hi> in a Letter of his (which no doubt he will juſtify as the <hi>immediat endytment</hi> of the Spirit of <hi>God</hi>) to the People of <hi>ABERDENE.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>IV. HEAD. Concerning the Light, and their Union with CHRIST, that have Saving Grace and Light in them.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>He quarrels at me for calling the Light in us, our Light. Anſ.</hi> Though it be <hi>Efficiently</hi> and <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginally</hi> the Light of Chriſt, yet is it nor <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectively</hi> ours: Is it diſingenuity, to ſay, that we
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:151253:14"/>
are the perſons in whom this Light is?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He ſaith page</hi> 14. 15. <hi>That ſometimes the being of Christ in men, ſignifieth the exiſtence of Chriſt in them to prepare for union with him and that Chriſt muſt needs be in men, before thy have union with Chriſt. Anſ.</hi> We grant that Chriſt may be and is in men in reſpect of his <hi>general preſence,</hi> and as to <hi>common operations</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they be in Union with him; But it is incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent for <hi>him</hi> to prove, that Chrſt is in men as to <hi>ſaving grace and light,</hi> (which is the Quakers prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple) and that men who are thus ſavingly inligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tened are without Union to Chriſt.</p>
               <p>As for thoſe ſpoken of <hi>John</hi> 1.5.10. (the other Scriptures ſhal afterwards be examined) in that they knew not Chriſt, this ſheweth that <hi>ſaving grace</hi> was not their priviledge: The Scripture abundantly teſtifyeth, that perſons truely gracious and ſavingly inlightened, are in a ſtate of union with Chriſt; and therefore Chriſt is ſaid to be <hi>in them, Rom.</hi> 8.10. <hi>to dwel in them,</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.16. and they are ſaid to <hi>abide in Chriſt.</hi> 1. <hi>John</hi> 4.16. and to <hi>dwell in Him, Joh.</hi> 6.56. All which expreſſions clearly import an Union between Chriſt and thoſe that have <hi>ſaving Grace</hi> and <hi>Light</hi> in them.</p>
               <p>He ſubjoyneth if it be thought ſtrange that Chriſt <hi>ſhould be in the Heathen, and they not know him. Was it not as ſtrange, that he ſhould be among the Jews who had the Letter that did bear a teſtimony of him, and they not know him? Anſwere.</hi> It is not ſo much for men to have the Scriptures among them, and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:151253:14"/>
miracles wrought before them, as to have <hi>Saving Light and Grace</hi> in them, though ſome that enjoyed the former, did ſadly miſtake Chriſt, yet ſuch as had Chriſt in them, by his <hi>ſaving Light,</hi> they cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dially owned Chriſt, and had the Myſteries of his Incarnation, Paſſion, and Reſurrection revealed to them; ſee <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.14. <hi>Act.</hi> 1 3.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 16. <hi>He ſaith Chriſt doth reveal himſelf in ſome meaſure unto all, in whom he beares witneſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst iniquity. Anſwere.</hi> If it be a Revelation of Chriſt to perſons in that they have a <hi>testimony</hi> in them againſt ſin, then we muſt yeeld that the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mericans</hi> have Chriſt revealed to them: Yea more, the very <hi>Devils</hi> have this Revelation of Chriſt, for they have that in them, which witneſſeth againſt <hi>iniquity and ſin:</hi> And therefore notwithſtanding all the Quakers pleadings for Heathens (as having ſav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Light in them) he doth them but ſmal favour, in putting them in the ſame caſe with <hi>Devils.</hi>
               </p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. I. The Danger of Aſſerting Saving and Sufficient Light to be in all.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He calleth it difingenuity for ſaying, that the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of all mens having ſufficient Light in them ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to put Chriſtians in the ſame condition with Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans. Anſ.</hi> This Doctrine of Saving ſufficient Light
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:151253:15"/>
in all, naturally tends to it, for if Pagans have ſav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Light,</hi> their ſtate ſhould be as ſafe as the ſtate of of Real Chriſtians. Where <hi>ſaving illumination</hi> is, there is alſo ſaving Faith, there being a concatina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion between theſe Graces of the Spirit. That Scripture, <hi>while ye have the Light, believe in the Light,</hi> is underſtood of the Perſon of Chriſt, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 8.12. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 12.46. which the Jews then had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, and not of <hi>ſubjective inherent light,</hi> wrought in the ſoul by Chriſt, for this being a crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thing is not to be believed in. If the Pagans light be ſufficient, then there is no Spiritual benefit (let the Quaker call it as he will, whether the raiſing of the ſeed in them, or refreſhing of them, the ſeed being raiſed) neceſſary to Salvation, that accrues to Chriſtians by the <hi>Scriptures and the Goſpel,</hi> but Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans may have the ſame by their <hi>light,</hi> elſe their Light is not ſufficient. Now is not the tendency of this opinion to make the <hi>Goſpel a vaine and needleſs thing,</hi> and mens labour in Preaching the Goſpel, wholly unneceſſary? Yea, it tends to make men im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piouſly proud, as if they needed not to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holden to GOD for <hi>more light;</hi> And therefore if any of the Quakers judgdement, had been over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearing <hi>David,</hi> when be prayed, <hi>Open mine eyes, that I may underſtand the wonderful things of the law, give me understanding that I may keep thy precepts.</hi> They might have been bold to correct <hi>David,</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing look to the <hi>Light within</hi> thee, (thats ſufficient) what needeſt thou pray for more?</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:151253:15"/>Whereas he ſaith, <hi>page</hi> 17. <hi>That men are ſaid to be brutiſh in their knowledge and to have no under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, becauſe they turn their backs upon the light, and will not follow it. Anſwere.</hi> This is but <hi>petitio principis,</hi> a begging of the queſtion, (which yet muſt not be given upon alms, without ſolid proof) taking it for granted, that perſons who are bruitiſh in their knowledge, having no underſtanding, yet have ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Light in them which they refuſe to follow. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Quaker ſpeake of mens being in darkneſs, becauſe of their oppoſition to the Light; It would concerne <hi>him</hi> firſt to prove, that the wicked who in Scripture, are called <hi>darkneſs,</hi> have ſaving Grace and Light in them. Can dead men have this ſav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Light? And is not every man by Nature Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually dead? <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.1. To aſſert that perſons Spiritually dead, have ſaving grace and light in them, looks like a contradiction, for then they ſhould be ſpiritually <hi>dead,</hi> and not ſpiritually <hi>dead:</hi> And though according to Scripture they be children of <hi>darkneſs,</hi> yet according to Quakers they ſhould be children of <hi>light;</hi> for to be a child of <hi>light,</hi> is as much as to be one in whom there is <hi>ſaving grace and light,</hi> ſufficient to guide him to pleaſe GOD, <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.8.</p>
                  <p>If it may well be ſuppoſed (as he ſaith) <hi>that the light in ſome is darkneſs,</hi> then the Quaker would do well in exhorting his Diſciples, to bid them take heed of <hi>their light,</hi> (and not <hi>to it.</hi>) This was <hi>Chriſts</hi> way of exhortation, <hi>Luke</hi> 11.35. And as I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:151253:16"/>
that phraſe, take heed to the light of GOD within (which is ſo common among Quakers) is not to be found in all the <hi>Scripture.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Neither can <hi>ſaving light,</hi> which is from Chriſt in any ſenſe be called <hi>darkneſs,</hi> as the Quaker inſinuat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, calling it <hi>darkneſs to them that reject it, in that it giveth them not comfort and joy, &amp;c.</hi> VVe owne that a diſconſolate ſtate wherein men walk without comfort, is called <hi>darkneſs,</hi> but this name is no where given to Chriſts <hi>ſaving light,</hi> which he ſetteh up in the ſoul; and though <hi>comfort and joy,</hi> be the reſult of the ſouls aſſurance and confidence of being in a ſtate of <hi>light;</hi> yet this <hi>joy and comfort</hi> is not the proper effect of that <hi>light</hi> (which proceedeth from Chriſt) but of that Lord who gave the light, who is therefore ſtiled <hi>the God of all Comfort,</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.4.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He denyeth, that having of ſaving light and grace preſuppoſes Converſion, which he illuſtrateth by the ſimilitude of a wound and plaister, the being healed of a wound preſuppoſes the plaiſter, but the applicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the plaiſter preſuppoſeth not the being healed. Anſ.</hi> What is this to the purpoſe? For when a man has <hi>ſaving light &amp; grace,</hi> he is in part healed, cured of the dominion and reigning power of ſin: And ths ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth an application of healing grace, which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed into the ſoul, by the converting and ſanctify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Power of the Spirit of GOD, and to make a difference between having of ſaving Grace, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in a ſtate of Grace, is but the <hi>figment</hi> of the Quakers own braine. Its true, the wicked do not
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:151253:16"/>
ſtand in grace; For how can they ſtand in that which they have not?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He addeth page</hi> 18. <hi>That there may be a ſufficient light in men, who may be ſaid after a certaine manner not to have the Spirit; as wicked perſons have not the Spirit, bringing forth the fruits thereof in them, to wit, love, meekneſs, goodneſs, faith, &amp;c. Anſwere.</hi> Can that perſon be ſaid to have <hi>ſufficient light,</hi> who is deſtitute of <hi>goodneſs,</hi> and wants <hi>faith</hi> which units to Chriſt, in whom the Chriſtians ſtrength and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency lyes? <hi>Philp.</hi> 4.13. And without whom we can do nothing, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 15.5.</p>
                  <p>Beſids having the ſpirit, implyes the ſouls <hi>receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ſpirit,</hi> and this phraſe notes the implanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Graces of the ſpirit</hi> in the ſoul, at its Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion and Regeneration. VVhere the ſpirit of the LORD is, there is <hi>liberty,</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.17. this ſpirit is a ſpirit of <hi>faith,</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.13. and though the ſpirit reprove and convince the wicked, and by his motions call upon them, and ſtrive with them, yet it will not follow, that they have <hi>ſufficient light,</hi> or <hi>ſaving light;</hi> for men may have <hi>reproofes, ſtriv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, convictions,</hi> that are far from <hi>ſaving grace:</hi> And unleſs the Quaker can make out that the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit calls upon <hi>every</hi> man, and ſtrives with <hi>every</hi> man, in order to his converſion, then he cannot conclude that all have the Spirit, <hi>(even according to his own notion of mens having the Spirit)</hi> and if all have not the ſpirit, then all have not <hi>ſufficient light,</hi> as for that place <hi>Ioh.</hi> 16.8. it reſts for <hi>him</hi> to prove that
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:151253:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the word <hi>world</hi> (which is <hi>homonymous</hi>) is there ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for <hi>all and every one</hi> throughout the world.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. II. The neceſſity of the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Chriſts out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Crucifixion.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He telleth us, page</hi> 19. 20. <hi>That the Apoſtle,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.2. <hi>Speaketh not of Chriſt as crucified out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, but of him, as he was inwardly crucified in the Corinthians, as the word imports, being rightly tranſlated out of the Greek, I determined no to know any thing</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. i. e. <hi>in you. Anſwere.</hi> Here he hath no ground to except againſt our <hi>Tranſlation,</hi> the words being ſolidly and ſoundly enough <hi>tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated,</hi> for by an ordinary <hi>Enallage,</hi> which particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly is called <hi>Protheſeon Parallaga</hi> (which is the putting of one prepoſition for another) <hi>in,</hi> is rende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>among,</hi> and this is conſonant to the <hi>Hebrew</hi> and <hi>Greek,</hi> ſee <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 34.30. ye have made me to ſtink, <hi>Bejoſhev haaretz, in incoll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s ter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ae,</hi> and yet its tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated <hi>among</hi> the inhabitants of the Earth. Then <hi>Acts</hi> 6.8. <hi>Stephen</hi> did great wonders and miracles, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>in populo,</hi> and yet who juſtly quarrel, if it be ſaid that the wonders and miracles were wrought <hi>among</hi> the people. Then <hi>Luke</hi> 1.28. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Benedicta tu in mulieribus,</hi>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:151253:17"/>
but yet it muſt be rendered (for making it good ſenſe) bleſſed art thou <hi>inter mulieres, among women,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.6. we ſpeak wiſdom <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>in perfectis, in the perfect,</hi> and yet the skilfulleſt Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lators render it, <hi>inter perfectos, among the perfect; Paul</hi> in delivering his meſſage was not in them, though they wanted not inward fruits of that Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel which he Preacht to and <hi>among</hi> them.</p>
                  <p>That it may appear how corruptly the Quaker would be tranſlating the words, it muſt be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that the doctrine of Quakers is, <hi>That Chriſt was crucified in the Corinthians, in the time of their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief, and at that time Christ was crucified in them in his ſuffering ſeed; that ſeed of Light and Truth, ſuffered in them under the burden of their tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</hi> Now remark, that the knowledge of Chriſt mentioned, 1. <hi>Corinth.</hi> 2.2. was that which <hi>Paul rejoyced in,</hi> hence he ſaith, <hi>God forbid that I ſhould glory ſave in the Croſs of Chriſt;</hi> now it would not have been the Apoſtles <hi>joy,</hi> but his <hi>grief,</hi> to know that the Light of Chriſt was born down in them by their tranſgreſſion: And therefore I muſt ſay it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, that text ſpeaks of <hi>Chriſt outwardly crucified,</hi> and the obediential, heart affecting knowledge of Chriſt <hi>thus crucified,</hi> is the maine thing that all who profeſs Chriſtianity, ſhould aime to attaine unto. And as it is a calumny to inſinuate, that that which we plead for, is a bare naming of Chriſts Death and Paſſion, ſo it is a groſs abuſe of that Scripture, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.16. to inferre from it, any thing againſt
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:151253:18"/>
the knowledge of Chriſts <hi>outward Crucifixion.</hi> For the thing which the Apoſtle there condemns, is earthly and carnal thoughts of Chriſt, as if Chriſt as King of Iſrael, ſhould begin an earthly and tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Kingdom, in this manner (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>from henceforth know we him no more,</hi> or we know him no more as a man living amongſt us.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He addeth page</hi> 21. <hi>That the Blood of Christ knowne and felt within for Chriſt as he is within, is not without his Blood, which he giveth to them, who know not diſtinctly, the outward ſhedding of the Blood, as it was many hundred yeares ago. Anſwere.</hi> It is hard to take up what the Quaker means by <hi>Christs Blood within, he</hi> calls it <hi>ſpiritual, even the pure Blood of the Vine.</hi> But ſeeing <hi>he</hi> ſpeaketh of it, as diſtinct from the <hi>outward ſhedding of Christs Blood;</hi> it would ſeeme that either <hi>he</hi> inclines to juſtify that which hath been charged upon ſome of <hi>his</hi> brethren, for ſaying, that they are not <hi>ſuch fools, as to hope to be ſaved, by that JESUS, who was cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified at Jeruſalem above ſixteen hundred years ago:</hi> Or that which hath been charged upon others of <hi>them,</hi> who affirme, <hi>that CHRIST as man dwels in them.</hi> A doctrine that tends to overthrow the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcention of Chriſt to Heaven, there to continue till the Reſtitution of all things, <hi>Act.</hi> 3.21. If the Quaker deſigne nothing by the Blood of Chriſt felt within, but the <hi>inward working of the Spirit,</hi> helping men believingly to apply <hi>Chriſts Blood which was ſhed at Jeruſalem,</hi> (beſides this, there is no other
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:151253:18"/>
                     <hi>heart cleanſing</hi> and <hi>conſcience purging Blood,</hi> and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very cleanſing Grace in the Soul, is the fruit of <hi>this Blood.</hi>) Then it is <hi>his</hi> work to prove that they are wholly ignorant of <hi>this Blood,</hi> (that is, know no ſuch thing as <hi>Chriſts Paſſion and Suffering</hi>) who yet are helped to a believing application of it, which if <hi>he</hi> do, then true Faith ſhal be a blind Faith, contrary to <hi>Eſa.</hi> 53.11. by his knowledge ſhal my righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous ſervant juſtify many.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. III. The tendency of the Quakers Principle, to introduce Paganiſme.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He ſaith, as for thy deceitful inſinuation to render us odious, that if our principles were generally owned, theſe Nations would be overſpread in an Age or two with as palpable darkneſs, as the Heathens at this day are; ſeeing it hath no juſt ground, we returne it upon thee, as falſe and malicious, &amp;c. Anſwere. Bona verba quaeſo, ſoft words and hard arguments</hi> would become you better. If it be the Quakers principle, that the light within <hi>is a ſufficient teacher, and that taking heed to this, there needs no more,</hi> then it is no deceit to affirme that this tends to introduce <hi>Paganiſme,</hi> and that the general owning of it would make theſe <hi>Nations</hi> in a ſhort time as the <hi>Heathen
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:151253:19"/>
Nations</hi> at this day are. Now that this is their prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, our Quakers cannot deny, but by denying the writtings of their <hi>infallible friends,</hi> who in their Printed books call upon people to ceaſe from their <hi>outſide lights,</hi> and to returne to the <hi>light of Chriſt in them,</hi> ſaying, that they who look out at <hi>teachers without them,</hi> are ſtrangers to that Covenant, by which all come to know the Lord, and need not that one teach another. I am credibly informed (by a Reverend Perſon whom I may truſt) that upon oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of his viſiting a dying friend (in <hi>Aberdene</hi>) there was at that time in the houſe two Quakers, and both of them preſſed ſo much upon the dying man, to take heed to <hi>the light within,</hi> (making this the chief and onely matter of their diſcourſe) that my informer found fault with them, that they ſpake ſo much of taking heed <hi>to the light,</hi> and nothing of believing in Chriſt: Whereupon on of their fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſaid, that if he took heed to the light there needed no more <hi>words, neither book without, nor teacher without:</hi> which in effect is, that the light within is ſo ſufficient a teacher, that there needs no other to teach but that, neither the teaching of the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> nor the <hi>Miniſtry of men;</hi> and laying this Teaching aſide, what a woful plight ſhould theſe Nations (in an Age or two) be in? There is no doubt but diſmal darkneſs would overſpread them. It is like, that now the Quakers do ſee, how much this <hi>principle</hi> contradicts their own practiſe (and muſt of neceſſity tend to make them odious) for
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:151253:19"/>
they have teachers, and teaching among themſelves. And therefore its added, <hi>page</hi> 22. <hi>that the light muſt not only be taken heed unto, but believed, obeyed, and walked in, which who do, it will lead them to uſe the Scriptures, and lead them to the aſſemblies of Gods people, and to hear and receive the Miniſtry of thoſe whom God ſends.</hi> But ſome of the Quakers in <hi>England,</hi> to keep their principle from claſhing with their practiſe, have been heard ſay, that <hi>their teaching</hi> is but to take people off from <hi>other teachers,</hi> that they may be brought to minde the <hi>light in them alone;</hi> and then they will ceaſe teachings. Now when all Teaching ceaſeth, except the inward teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which the <hi>Indians</hi> have, how quickly ſhal we be like them, among whom the Name of CHRIST is not in rememberance.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. IV. The Light GIVER muſt not be confounded with the Light given.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He addeth page</hi> 22. <hi>That they do not confound the Light Giver with the Light, or enlightening given. Anſ.</hi> Ye do plainly confound them, for do ye not call <hi>that light Jeſus Christ,</hi> wherewith all men are enlightened? And yet <hi>this light</hi> is but a ray or beame proceeding from Chriſt, and therefore
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:151253:20"/>
he is ſaid to be that True Light, which enlighteneth every man: clearly importing a difference between the <hi>light</hi> in all men, and <hi>Chriſt</hi> the Donator of this light. It is acknowledged that where the light, or enlightening from Chriſt is, there is <hi>Chriſt himſelf,</hi> namely, according to the nature of the light: which light in the wicked is <hi>common,</hi> but in the Godly is <hi>ſaving,</hi> and ſo Chriſt is in the one, as to a <hi>common,</hi> but in the other, in reſpect of a <hi>ſaving operation of light.</hi> Now when <hi>he</hi> ſaith that Chriſt is in all men, if <hi>his</hi> meaning be that as <hi>God, he is in all men,</hi> then we do not control <hi>him,</hi> for thus Chriſt is every where. If <hi>his</hi> meaning be that <hi>as man, he is in all men,</hi> then the Scripture controls <hi>him,</hi> which holdeth forth his Man-hood, muſt continue in Heaven, <hi>untill the time of the reſtitution of all things.</hi> If <hi>his</hi> meaning be that Chriſt is in all men <hi>to enlighten them that they may believe,</hi> then <hi>his</hi> proof is not ſufficient, which is <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.9. compared with 7. for this ſeventh verſe, ſpeaketh expreſly of <hi>Iohn the Baptiſt,</hi> the fore-run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Chriſt, as is evident by looking back to the preceeding verſe, <hi>There was a man ſent from God, whoſe name was John, the ſame came for a witneſs to bear witneſs of the light, that all men through him might believe.</hi> Here the Evangeliſt holdeth forth <hi>Iohns</hi> calling and the end of it, which was to bear <hi>teſtimony</hi> concerning Chriſt. This was the ſpecial ſcop of <hi>Iohns Miniſtry,</hi> to point out Chriſt in his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies and uſefulneſs to loſt men, and to whom the offer of Chriſt comes <hi>(in the Miniſtry of the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:151253:20"/>
word)</hi> they are called upon to <hi>believe in Chriſt,</hi> none being excluded.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. V. There is a Conſiſtency between Mans Lapſed State, and the Remainders of the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MAGE of GOD in him.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He asketh, how it is conſiſtent (to affirme that ſome remainders of knowledge, and principles of good remaine in man after the ruins of Gods Image in him) with what we ſay, to wit, that there is no good thing at all in men unconverted, and that man fell wholly from God, as to all things that are good. Anſ.</hi> Who of us do ſay ſo, without adding any limitation? And yet there is no inconſiſtency between theſe things (even as ſet down by you) if rightly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, for though men unconverted have not any <hi>ſaving good,</hi> yet it followeth not, <hi>ergo,</hi> they are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute of all good. The unconverted have precious Souls in them, which are of great excellency and worth; and there ſtill remains in them ſome <hi>ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude</hi> of GOD, their Souls being Spiritual and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal. It is true man by the fall was bereaved of <hi>ſaving graces,</hi> in ſo much that <hi>true holineſs, and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:151253:21"/>
ſaving knowlegde</hi> he hath not; yet he is not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuded of all knowledge: In him there are <hi>certaine notions</hi> concerning good and evil, which though they cannot direct to <hi>Salvation</hi> and <hi>Eternal happineſs;</hi> yet if we live not up to them, they ſerve to leave us unexcuſable.</p>
                  <p>Now it may be demanded, whether it be incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent to ſay, that a City is <hi>wholly demoliſhed,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as there is ſome rubbiſh, and ſome foundations of houſes ſtill remaining? If this be not <hi>inconſiſtent,</hi> why ſhould it be thought <hi>an inconſiſtency:</hi> To ſay, that though men be fallen off from GOD, yet he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains ſome fragments, and Relicts of the Image of GOD? As in very deed he doth, for the Image of GOD is the <hi>conformity</hi> of the creature to the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour, and the Soul of man is <hi>conformable</hi> to GOD in its nature, as it is a Spiritual and Immortal Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. Likewiſe, man hath not loſt all his <hi>domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi> over the creatures. And it is to be obſerved, that though there be <hi>light</hi> in the conſciences of men that are corrupt, yet this <hi>light</hi> is not the <hi>cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption</hi> of the conſcience; but it is derived from Chriſt and cometh from him, as a <hi>bountiful Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour:</hi> and in this reſpect the light of knowledge, reaſon, and underſtanding, that is in man ſince the fall, may be called the light of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>for he is that true light that thus enlighneth every man, that cometh into the world.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:151253:21"/>
               <head>V. HEAD. Concerning the Scriptures.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. I. Shewing how the Quakers vilify the Scriptures.</head>
                  <p>Look to page 24.25. And we may eaſily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive <hi>the Quakers diſ-esteeme of the Scriptures,</hi> though in ſpeaking to people, they would beare them in hand to the contrary. For,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. They grant that they meet not to read the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> but to waite <hi>on the Lord,</hi> and they meet to worſhip GOD, whoſe worſhip is to be performed <hi>in Spirit and in Truth,</hi> and not in <hi>External Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi> Now do not theſe mens endeavours tend to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> in that they make an oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, between reading the Scriptures, and waiting on GOD, and Spiritual worſhipping of him; as if the Lord could not be waited on, in the uſe of read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Word. Was not the <hi>Eunuch</hi> in the duty of waiting, when ſitting in his chariot he read the <hi>Prophet Iſaias?</hi> This work was ſo well pleaſing to GOD, that the Lord encouraged him in it, help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him to underſtand what before he knew not, <hi>Act.</hi> 8.28. Did not the Saints under the <hi>Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> worſhip GOD in Spirit and in Truth? Surely
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:151253:22"/>
the Lord required of them, <hi>ſincere, Spirit worſhip,</hi> which they performed, (lifting up their Souls to GOD) and did not ſatisfy themſelves with the bare outſide and carcaſe of duty, <hi>Lament.</hi> 3.41. And yet they were not enemies <hi>to external Reading of the Scriptures, Act,</hi> 15.21. <hi>Moſes of old time, hath in every City them that Preacht him, being Read in the Synagogue every Sabbath-day.</hi> And although Reading the Scriptures was a duty done under the <hi>Law,</hi> it doth not ceaſe to be a duty under the <hi>Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel,</hi> becauſe it is no where repealed, but on the contrary, as it was commanded in the <hi>Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> ſo it is confirmed in the <hi>New,</hi> this being a ſpecial means of having the Word of GOD <hi>to dwel richly in us, Coloſſ.</hi> 3.16.</p>
                  <p>It is moſt agreeable to the Scriptures, for a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter to take the <hi>Bible</hi> and read a part of it, opening and applying it, ſee <hi>Nehem.</hi> 8.5.8. <hi>And Ezra o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened the book in the ſight of all the people, ſo they read in the book of the Law of GOD diſtinctly, and gave the ſenſe, and cauſed them to underſtand the reading.</hi> Chriſt himſelf took a <hi>text</hi> and applyed it, <hi>Luke</hi> 4.18.21. And albeit Chriſt did this in the ſynagogue, <hi>Quid inde?</hi> What then? did he not likewiſe Preach in the ſynagogue? And yet Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing continues to be the <hi>Miniſters</hi> duty, 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.2.</p>
                  <p>As for that Scripture, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.29.30.31. it conduceth nothing to keep up the ſucceſſive talk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Quakers. For the <hi>Propheſying</hi> here mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned was the act of Prophets, and it is reſtrained to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:151253:22"/>
them, <hi>all the Prophets who propheſie.</hi> Now the Gentle-man will have much ado, to prove all his brethren, who at their meetings take upon them to Preach, or rather (to uſe <hi>his</hi> owne terme) prate one after another <hi>to be Prophets:</hi> eſpecially, to prove their <hi>women preachers</hi> to be in the number of them, for their preaching is expreſly prohibited, <hi>verſes</hi> 34.35. <hi>Let your women keep ſilence in the Church, for it is not permitted, unto them to ſpeake, — it is a ſhame for women to ſpeake in the Church.</hi> Neither doth the afore-cited Scripture make any thing againſt our way; for Miniſters amongſt us, ſometimes ſpeak <hi>two or three,</hi> and the ſpirits of the Prophets are ſubject to the Prophets. The Quakers themſelves have not many ſpeakers; for at times they ſit dumbe, as if ſilence could promote their mutual edification: Was this the Churches way? Or the cuſtome of the Apoſtles, and primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Chriſtians? Certainly this hemlock (or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention) hath ſprung up ſince their late apoſtacy from the Truth.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, They will not have the Scriptures cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led their <hi>Maſters letter,</hi> no (forſooth) their <hi>Maſters letter</hi> is written in <hi>their hearts,</hi> and there they are to find it, neither is their Maſter ſeperated from them, as thoſe who uſe to write letters to ſervants to ſet them on work. But is not Chriſt as much ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate from Quakers, as from the <hi>ſeven Churches of Aſia?</hi> Or was he not as near thoſe Famous Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, as them? And yet they had letters ſent to
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:151253:23"/>
them from their great LORD and Maſter, to direct them in their duty, <hi>Revel.</hi> 1.11. <hi>I am Alpha, and Omega, and what thou ſeeſt write in a book, and ſend it unto the ſeven Churches which are in Aſia.</hi> Now will ye obſerve how much <hi>theſe perſons</hi> bend their ſtrength to evacuate the authority of the Scriptures; For they ſay, GOD requires us to do all our work by <hi>immediat counſel and direction,</hi> as if by the <hi>out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward command</hi> contained in the Scriptures, GOD did not require any work of them: yea they will not allow the <hi>Scripture precepts</hi> the name of <hi>Commands;</hi> but call them the <hi>outward testimony, and ſignification of the Command,</hi> which (as they ſay) they regaird in its place, that is onely when they have an inward <hi>command,</hi> and ſo while this <hi>inward command</hi> is wanting, <hi>through their neligence in waiting,</hi> all that time, the Scripture loſeth its authority, and is of no uſe to them. Is this to regard the Scriptures? Doth it not tend to forward and confirme negligent Atheiſts, in their contemptuous ſlighting, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dervaluing of the Scriptures? Oh! that all ſuch would read and tremble at the reading of <hi>Ioh.</hi> 12.48. <hi>he that receiveth not my words, hath one that judgeth him, the word that I have ſpoken, the ſame ſhal judge him at the laſt day.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thirdly, They preferre their <hi>ſilent waiting,</hi> to the reading of the Scriptures, as if we muſt firſt come <hi>to this,</hi> ere we can know the Scriptures aright. Now they ſhould prove (which is not ſo much as touched upon) that <hi>their way of waiting</hi> is a meane
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:151253:23"/>
appointed by GOD for right underſtanding of the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> or profitable ſpeaking concerning them. Waiting in their notion is <hi>Apocriphal,</hi> not warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by any Scripture. Some of them have defined it to be a <hi>ſilent poſture of the heart without thinking good or evil.</hi> It ſeemeth to me, no better then miſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t time, to be employed in ſeeking ſuch a <hi>poſture of heart:</hi> the heart is ſuch a ſtirring &amp; working thing, that if it be not upon good, it will be buſie enough in evil, as may be found in our daily experience. Accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Scripture, <hi>faith, patience,</hi> and <hi>hope,</hi> muſt be exerciſed in waiting, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40.1. <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.26. and can we be in the exerciſe of theſe <hi>graces</hi> without thinking good or evil? What an odd conceit is this?</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, Leſt they ſhould ſeeme to be too great enemies to the Scriptures, <hi>they confeſs it to be their deſire to try Doctrines by the Scriptures. Anſ.</hi> If this be their deſire indeed, how is it then, that one of the Quakers ſeeing a Religious woman (in this Town) with a Bible in her hand, told her, ſhe might as well read a Latine book as <hi>that Book?</hi> And why is it, that they do not deſire their hearers to bring their Bibles, that ſo they may the better diſcerne whether the <hi>doctrines</hi> taught at <hi>their meetings,</hi> be anſwerable to the <hi>Scriptures?</hi> But happily they think not this convenient, leſt <hi>their juglings</hi> ſhould be found out; And I muſt tell the Gentle-man (that though he charge us with <hi>jugling</hi>) that the Quakers have been ſuſpected from their firſt riſe, as <hi>notable juglers,</hi> which <hi>R. Farmer, in his Myſtery of ungodlyneſs</hi>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:151253:24"/>
ſheweth by this inſtance, <hi>ſaith he,</hi> it is uſual for Quakers to ſay, they owne the Scriptures, yea, we confirme and eſtabliſh the Scriptures, and witneſs the Scriptures; Now <hi>ſaith he,</hi> an honeſt-man (that means plainly) would think they believed the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to be the <hi>written Word of GOD,</hi> and <hi>the rule</hi> of a Chriſtian to walk by, in things to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved and practiſed, But <hi>ſaith he, theſe perſons</hi> play the deceivers (not uſing words in that ſenſe, they are uſually underſtood) they meane otherwiſe, <hi>they ſay</hi> in expreſs words elſe where, <hi>the Scriptures are not the Saints rule of knowing God and living to him.</hi> And indeed theſe are the words of one <hi>C. Atkinſon</hi> a Quaker, (ſee his book, called <hi>the ſword of the Lord furbiſhed, in anſwere to the Miniſters first principle</hi>) and a little after he inſinuats, that to affirme the <hi>Scriptures to be the rule, is to put darkneſs for light, and light for darkneſs.</hi> Now let all unbyaſſed perſons, judge whether theſe men put the <hi>Scriptures</hi> in their true place.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. II. Proving the Scriptures to be the Word of GOD.</head>
                  <p>He addeth page 26. <hi>That every declaration of a mans mind, is not his word, for ſigns may be a declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his mind. Anſ.</hi> Though a dumb man may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:151253:24"/>
his mind <hi>by ſigns,;</hi> yet this maketh nothing againſt the Scriptures, being the <hi>word of God,</hi> which are ſuch a <hi>declaration of Gods mind,</hi> as he uttered and ſpake. If any thing can be accounted the <hi>proper word</hi> of one, that muſt be it, which he utters and ſpeaks: Now the <hi>Truths, the Commands, and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts,</hi> contained in the Scriptures, were uttered and ſpoken by God, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.1. <hi>And God ſpake all theſe words, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He ſaith, people uſually diſtinguiſh between a mans word and his write. Anſ.</hi> True: For they call the one <hi>verbum dictum,</hi> a word ſpoken, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>verbum ſcriptum,</hi> a word written; but can it be inferred from this, that the <hi>Scriptures</hi> are not the Word of GOD, which he hath committed to writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, for the good of his Church and People.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He ſaith, the Word of GOD is like unto himſelf, ſpiritual, yea, ſpirit, and life, and therefore cannot be read with the external ſenſes. Anſ.</hi> The Word of GOD is twofold, 1. There is the <hi>coeſſential, coeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal word,</hi> namely, JESUS CHRIST, who is one with the Father, this Word properly cannot be read, though we may, and do read of it. 2. There is the <hi>Spiritual Word, the temporal expreſſed Word, or the Word written in time,</hi> now the external ſenſes may be employed in reading <hi>this Word.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He ſaith, that theſe ſcriptures (Hoſ.</hi> 1.1. <hi>Joel.</hi> 1.1. <hi>Eſay.</hi> 38.4.) <hi>are underſtood of that word from which the ſcriptures were given forth. Anſ.</hi> It is not denyed, that the Lord ſpake by the Prophets, and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:151253:25"/>
was the authour of giving forth the <hi>ſcriptures,</hi> but yet that word of the Lord which came to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, is not mean'd of the <hi>Word made fleſh,</hi> (as Quakers would have it) but of the <hi>mind and meſſage of the Lord</hi> contained in Scripture <hi>Ieremiah</hi> 14.1. <hi>the word of the Lord that came to Ieremiah:</hi> Now what word was this, ſurely, none elſe but the <hi>meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage</hi> which the Prophet was to deliver from GOD, to the perſons therein concerned, having reference to that dearth which ſhould make <hi>Judah</hi> mourne and languiſh, verſe 2. The ſame may be ſaid of the other ſcriptures.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He addeth, What the Scripture ſaith and GOD ſaith, may be ſaid, that they are one, becauſe of their agreement. Anſ.</hi> This is to advance <hi>humane writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings,</hi> and to equal them with the <hi>ſcriptures,</hi> when their ſayings agree with what God ſaith.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He ſaith, every one that reads and heares the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures read, heareth not God immediatly. Anſwer.</hi> GOD himſelf ſpeaketh in the Scriptures to them that have eares to hear him, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.6. And though all that read and hear the Scriptures Read, hear not GOD immediatly, as the Prophtts who had truths revealed to them by <hi>immediat inſpiration;</hi> yet when we read the Scriptures GOD ſpeaks to us medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atly, by his written Word: and believers ſo hear <hi>his voice,</hi> that at the reading and hearing of the Scriptures, they are forced to ſay <hi>the voice of GOD,</hi> and not the voice of man.</p>
                  <p>Page 27. <hi>He ſaith, (in anſwering</hi> 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.13.)
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:151253:25"/>
                     <hi>that the word which they heard of the Apoſtles, was the living word. Anſw.</hi> The word which they heard of <hi>Paul,</hi> and received as the word of GOD, was the <hi>Scripture or written word,</hi> which ſpeaketh of the <hi>eſſential and living word,</hi> or it was the doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine he preacht concerning Chtiſt, grounded on, and warranted by the Scriptures, compare 1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.13. with <hi>Act.</hi> 26.22.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He ſaith, that the Phariſees in ſtriking at the firſt Command, did conſequently ſtrike at the living word which gave it forth. Anſ.</hi> The Phariſees without doubt, were enemies to Chriſt, and ſtruck at him many wayes; but yet the word, which they ſought to make void, <hi>Mark</hi> 7. is plainly held forth, to be that written precept, <hi>honour thy father and thy mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> compare verſe 13. with verſe 10.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He concludeth the matter, ſaying, that the reaſon why they may not call the ſcriptures the word of God, is, that people may be directed to that inward living word. Anſ.</hi> If they believe the Scriptures to be true, they may and ought to call them the <hi>word of GOD,</hi> for the Scriptures call themſelves the <hi>word of GOD, Epheſ.</hi> 6.17. <hi>the ſword of the ſpirit which is the word of GOD,</hi> this ſword of the ſpirit, is not a carnal, but a ſpiritual weapon, even the <hi>holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,</hi> (which are mighty through GOD, for repel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the temper, and cutting aſſunder temptations) this was the <hi>ſword</hi> which Chriſt made uſe of, in his conflict with Satan, <hi>its written, and againe it is written, Matth.</hi> 4. <hi>Luke</hi> 4.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:151253:26"/>By calling the Scriptures the <hi>word of God,</hi> (which is a name due to them) this will make their teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony concerning Chriſt to be more regarded, and therefore the more effectual means to our cloſing with the <hi>living word.</hi> It ſeemeth Quakers have ſtrange thoughts of the Scriptures, as if they were ſet up as <hi>an Idol, inſtead of that from whence they came.</hi> If we profeſs love to the Scriptures, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to obey them, this is not to <hi>Idolize them,</hi> and we are far from putting the Scriptures in Chriſts ſtead; Did they ever hear any of us call the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <hi>the eternal Son of God, that Saviour who dyed and ſuffered,</hi> thereby paying a ranſome for ſinners Redemption? Do we not ſay, that though the Scriptures be the <hi>word of God,</hi> yet there is a vaſt dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between them and Chriſt, he being the <hi>eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial, eternal word,</hi> and the Scriptures onely the <hi>word written in time?</hi> Why then ſhould it be inſinuate, that we call Chriſt the Scripture, and put the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in his ſtead, is not this unworthy dealing? We diſtinguiſh between <hi>Christ, the word,</hi> and the <hi>word of Chriſt,</hi> and though the Scripture be not that <hi>word</hi> which is Chriſt, yet it is the word of <hi>that word, Coloſ.</hi> 3.16. Let the word of Chriſt dwell in you richly.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. II. Clearing the Scriptures to be the Rule.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He addeth, that it reſts to be proved, that the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:151253:26"/>
Law and Testimony mentioned, Eſay.</hi> 8.20. <hi>was not the inward law. Anſ.</hi> The proof of this will not be difficult, for here the Prophet oppoſes what is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten (as being no light) if it agree not to <hi>the law and teſtimony.</hi> Let people pretend what they will, to a <hi>law and word within:</hi> yet if they accord not with the <hi>Scripture law, or ſcripture word,</hi> there is no light of truth in them. It is undenyable that the <hi>outward law</hi> gets the name of <hi>teſtimony,</hi> this name was given unto the law written in the two Tables, in regard whereof, the Ark was called the <hi>Ark of the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi> becauſe thoſe Tables were laid up in the Ark, <hi>Exod.</hi> 25.16. 1. <hi>King.</hi> 8.9.</p>
                  <p>My intent in bringing that ſcripture <hi>Ioh.</hi> 7.49. was onely to prove the acceptation of the word <hi>law,</hi> for the <hi>outward law</hi> left upon record in the Scriptures though the Quaker maliciouſly gloſſes on it, as if in ſpeaking for the <hi>law,</hi> we were crucifying Chriſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh, therein comparng us to the <hi>Phariſees:</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the compariſon will fit the Quakers a great deal better then us, their knowne raſh cenſuring abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly declares their conformity to Phariſees; for they can freely pronounce men <hi>damned and curſed,</hi> who will not take their gate of it, and this was the way of the Phariſees, <hi>this people</hi> (ſaid they) <hi>who know not the law are curſed.</hi> Neither is it probable that Chriſt checkt the <hi>Lawyer, Luk.</hi> 10.26. in ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>how readest thou?</hi> But rather would have men in matters of Religion to conſult the <hi>ſcriptures,</hi> and therefore in convincing ignorant and erroneous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:151253:27"/>
of their ignorance and errours; He alleadged the <hi>Scriptures</hi> againſt them, <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.31.32. When a queſtion aroſe about devorcement, Chriſt had preſent recourſe to the Scripture, <hi>Matth.</hi> 19.4. <hi>have ye not read, that he that made them at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, made them male and female?</hi> So when the Phariſees accuſed Chriſts Diſciples for breach of the Sabbath, Chriſt ſaid unto them, <hi>have ye not read, what David did, when he was an hungred, and they that were with him. Matth.</hi> 12.3. Chriſt then would have the ſcriptures <hi>the rule</hi> to walk by, and matters of Religion to be tryed by them: for he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers us to the <hi>ſcriptures</hi> for direction, and its his will that we reſort to them (in controverſies and doubts) for reſolution.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He ſaith, page</hi> 28. <hi>That we ſeeme to lay much ſtreſſe upon this, that it cannot be made out to a Jew or Turk, that Jeſus the Son of Mary, is in very deed the Chriſt without the Scripture. Anſw.</hi> We lay ſo much ſtreſs on it, that we think Quakers can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver prove this <hi>fundamental truth</hi> referring them to the <hi>light within,</hi> for they pretend following of <hi>their light</hi> in oppoſing Chriſt, as much as Quakers do at this day in oppoſing the <hi>precious ordinances and truths of Chriſt:</hi> And if <hi>Pauls</hi> courſe was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable, ſo muſt ours, if againſt the Jews we ſhould alledge <hi>ſcripture</hi> in demonſtrating Chriſt to be the <hi>Meſſiah;</hi> for the Jews profeſs a belief of the <hi>ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,</hi> of the <hi>Old Testament.</hi> Though the <hi>inward teſtimony of the ſpirit</hi> be of great uſe to perſwade and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:151253:27"/>
aſſure us of the <hi>divine authority of the ſcripture,</hi> yet it is falſe to affirme that this can be proved no other way, but by the <hi>ſpirits inward teſtimony:</hi> there are other arguments whereby the <hi>authority</hi> of the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture may be convincingly and ſolidly proved a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Pagans,</hi> and all <hi>Anti-ſcripturiſts</hi> whatſoever. Let me crave leave to put Quakers in minde of one argument, which is excellently im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved, by that judicious ſervant of GOD, <hi>Mr. Baxter,</hi> in his book of the <hi>Saints reſt,</hi> page 239. Where he thus reaſoneth, if the Scriptures be nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the invention of Devils, nor of men, then they can be from none but GOD, (he takes it for gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that good Angels could not be guilty of <hi>forging the ſcriptures</hi>) now he proves at length (it would be needleſs to ſet down here the full proof of this ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, becauſe the book is common, and in the hands of many) that the <hi>Scripture</hi> is not the inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Devils, that no meer men were the inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Scripture,</hi> it was neither deviſed by good men, nor by bad men, then ſure by no man, and conſequently muſt of neceſſity proceed from GOD.</p>
                  <p>When the Ancient Fathers had to do with <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans</hi> (who were ſtrangers to the <hi>inward testimony</hi> of the ſpirit) they made uſe of <hi>other arguments,</hi> in proving the Scriptures Divinity: ſuch as the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venlineſs of the matter, the Majeſtie of the ſtyle, the efficacy of the Doctrine, the verity of the predictions, and by theſe and ſuch like arguments, they confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the learnedſt Pagans. And JOHN CALVIN,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:151253:28"/>
                     <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 7. <hi>of his Instit:</hi> plainly ſuppoſeth that there are other arguments (beſids the teſtimony of the ſpirit) to prove the <hi>divine authority</hi> of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, ſaith he, <hi>verum quidem eſt, ſi argumentis a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere libeat, multa poſſe in medium preferri quae facile evincant, ſiquis eſt in Coelo DEUS, Legem, &amp; Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetias, &amp; Evangelium ab eo manaſſe</hi> i. e. True in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it is, that if we pleaſed to deale by arguments, many things might be produced, that may eaſily prove, that if there be a GOD in Heaven, that the Law, the Prophets, and the Goſpel came from him. Now ſeeing the Quakers have cited CALVIN, I would adviſe them to look to the 9. chapter, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in be fully ſheweth, that fanatical men, who <hi>(forſaking ſcripture)</hi> betake themſelves unto <hi>reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation,</hi> do overturne all principles of godlineſs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He ſaith, that Ioh.</hi> 5.39. <hi>may be tranſlated, ye ſearch the ſcriptures, as Paſor tranſlateth the words. Anſ.</hi> The ſame <hi>Paſor,</hi> ſpeaking of that ſcripture, the kingdom of <hi>God</hi> is within you, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, he ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth the words <hi>in medio veſtro, in ſinu gentis veſtrae,</hi> that is, in the midſt of you, in the boſome of your nation; and yet the Quakers will not admit of this tranſlation. It is confeſſed that <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, is taken by ſome (even PROTESTANT Writters) in the <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicative mood,</hi> though by that which followes, it appears to be <hi>imperative</hi> rather then <hi>indicative;</hi> for the great controverſie at that time was, whether <hi>Chriſt was the Son of GOD,</hi> and the <hi>true Meſſiah,</hi> now Chriſt remits them to the ſcriptures (which the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:151253:28"/>
Jews <hi>deſervedly</hi> had in high eſteeme) as bearing witneſſe unto him, <hi>ſearch the ſcriptures and they are they which teſtify of me;</hi> As who would ſay, peruſe them frequently, ſearch them diligentlie, digging for <hi>theſe heavenly treaſures,</hi> as men do for gold, who break every clod, that they may find the golden oare. Neither doth Chriſt check them, when he ſaith, <hi>in them ye think to have eternal life,</hi> this was a true thought, as to the ſcriptures pointing out the <hi>way</hi> to Eternal life, 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.10.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Seeing the Quaker (page</hi> 29.) <hi>granteth that the ſcriptures are profitable, for doctrine, correction, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof, inſtruction in righteouſneſs,</hi> why then, doth he not acknowledge them to be a <hi>perfect rule</hi> of faith and manners; VVhat more can be requiſite to prove their perfection, then their teaching <hi>truth,</hi> confuting <hi>errour,</hi> reproving <hi>ſin,</hi> and diſcovering <hi>du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</hi> There is enough ſaid, and delivered in the Scripture, to direct us in things to be believed and practiſed, and if the Scriptures do not actually profit us for this end, the blaime is to be laid at the door of our ignorance and perverſneſſe. Now the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are thus profitabe that the <hi>man of God</hi> may be perfect. i. e. That the <hi>Miniſter of Jeſus Chriſt</hi> may be compleate, and every way fitted for the work of his Calling, for though any man led by the ſpirit of GOD, may (in a general ſenſe) be called the <hi>man of God;</hi> yet the Lord honours his <hi>Miniſters</hi> with this tittle, and <hi>peculiarly</hi> attributs it to them, 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.27. and 9.6. 1. <hi>King.</hi> 17.18.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:151253:29"/>
                  <head>SECT. III. Shewing that the Spirit within is not the Rule.</head>
                  <p>In ſtead of anſwering my argument, proving that the Spirit within is not the rule, <hi>he ſaith, did theſe Jews receive Chriſt who had the ſcriptures? Did they not reject him, and why? Becauſe they hearkned not to the inward voice and testimony of the Father concerning him, and this was the teſtimony which he ſaid, was greater then that of John. Anſ.</hi> Look into the place where Chriſt ſpeaks of this teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and it will be found that it is no <hi>inward voice of the Father,</hi> there ſpoken of. See <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.36. <hi>I have a greater witneſs then that of John for the works which the Father hath given me to finiſh, the ſame works that I do, bear witneſs of me:</hi> That is his works in doing miracles, theſe were a more convincing witneſs of Chriſts being the <hi>promiſed Meſſiah,</hi> then that of <hi>John:</hi> And therefore, when <hi>Iohns</hi> Diſciples askt, ſaying, <hi>art thou he that ſhal come, or do we look for another?</hi> Jeſus anſwered, go and ſhew <hi>John theſe things which ye do hear and ſee, the blind re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive their ſight, &amp;c.</hi> As for that teſtimony which the Father gave concerning Chriſt, verſe 37. it was not <hi>an inward voice and testimony,</hi> but an <hi>outward audible voice</hi> from Heaven, <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.17. compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:151253:29"/>
with 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.17.18. And Chriſt reproveth the unbelieving Jews, in that they were ignorant of the Father, though they gloried ſo much of him, as being the people whoſe Progenitors had heard the <hi>voice of GOD, Deut.</hi> 4.12. Now Chriſt ſheweth that all this was nothing to them; for they were ſtrangers to ſuch manifeſtations of GOD, and they looked not like that people whoſe Anceſtors had heard ſo much of GOD, <hi>ye have neither heard his voice, nor ſeen his ſhape.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He ſaith, there is not any word</hi> 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.1. <hi>of try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſpirits by the ſcriptures. Anſwer.</hi> It is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient if there be warrand in other places (though no expreſs mention of it in this) for trying the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits by the ſcripture. Now ſeeing every ſpirit (is not to be believed) that is, every doctrine propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded as received by inſpiration from Gods ſpirit, falſe teachers will be as ready as any to boaſt of the ſpirit: and therefore we muſt try from what ſpirit their doctrine cometh. And what ſurer and ſafer way can there be of trying, then that for which the <hi>Beraeans</hi> are commended, even in trying the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles themſelves? They ſearched the <hi>Scriptures</hi> whether theſe things were ſo, <hi>Act.</hi> 17.11. and Chriſt appealed to the <hi>Scriptures, Ioh.</hi> 5.39.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He ſaith, cannot the ſpirits be tryed by the Spirit of God? How tryed</hi> Peter <hi>the ſpirit of</hi> Ananias <hi>and</hi> Saphirah? <hi>And is not the tryal and diſcerning of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits the priviledge of the Saints now? Anſ.</hi> We are ſpeaking about the trying of Doctrines, now <hi>Ananias</hi>
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:151253:30"/>
and <hi>Saphirah,</hi> their failing was not in a matter of <hi>Doctrine,</hi> but of <hi>Fact,</hi> by lying in keeping back pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> of the price of the poſſeſſion, which <hi>Peter</hi> knew <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarily:</hi> as appears by the miraculous effect, that attended his reproving of this ſin, which was their ſuddaine death, and preſent <hi>giving up of the Ghoſt, Act.</hi> 5.5.</p>
                  <p>As for <hi>diſcerning of ſpirits</hi> (if thereby he either intend the knowledge of the ſecret conceptions and inward thoughts of mens ſpirits, or a certaine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible knowledge, who be truely ſpiritual, and who not.) It is not the priviledge of the Saints now, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was it ever a priviledge common to all the Saints, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.10. <hi>to another is given the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of miracles, to anothter diſcerning of ſpirits.</hi> Though the Saints have that anointing in them which <hi>teacheth them all things;</hi> yet as hereby <hi>external teaching</hi> is not excluded (for <hi>Iohn</hi> himſelf was now teaching in writting this very Epiſtle to them) ſo is not trying of the ſpirits by an <hi>external rule,</hi> the <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointings, teaching,</hi> may well conſiſt with bringing Doctrines to the Touch-ſtone of the Word, doth not the anointing (or the ſpirit) direct us to the <hi>law and testimony?</hi> And if they ſpeak not according to this word, it is becauſe there is no <hi>light</hi> in them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He ſaith, were there any more ſtrongly delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded then the Phariſees, yet how much did they lay claime to the ſcriptures, how came they to be deluded, who were ſo skilled in the ſcriptures according to the letter of them? Anſ.</hi> That the Phariſees were delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:151253:30"/>
the <hi>Scripture</hi> is not to be blamed for this, the fault was in their blindneſs, hence they are ſo often called <hi>blind guids, Matth.</hi> 23.16.24.26. It is granted that deluded ſouls, ſuch as are unlearned and unſtable, may and do <hi>wrest the ſcriptures unto their own deſtruction,</hi> 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.16. But yet there is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough ſaid in the Scriptures, by which <hi>deluſions</hi> might be diſcovered, and <hi>controverſies</hi> ended: If men would be humble and ſtudious in the uſe of helps and means, bringing not <hi>diſcutiendi acumen,</hi> a diſputing head, but <hi>diſcendi pietatem,</hi> a pious heart, deſirous to be inſtructed.</p>
                  <p>And for further clearing of our mind in this, it is to be conſidered, that albeit we look upon the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, as <hi>a rule</hi> for finding out truth, and deciding controverſies, yet that we may be right diſcerners, we judge a work of the ſpirit neceſſary, for remov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our natural depravedneſs, perverſneſs, and ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, ſo that though the ſcripture be ſufficient for diſcovering deluſions, and ending differences <hi>in genere objecti,</hi> yet the ſpirit is neceſſary <hi>in genere cauſae effectivae.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He addeth page</hi> 30. <hi>Though the ſame deluding ſpirit, who deceived first may deceive over againe, that makes nothing againſt the inſufficiency of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, to diſcover the deluſion. Anſwer.</hi> We blaime not the ſpirit for mens falling into deluſion at firſt, or for their continuance in deluſions; Who can charge the ſpirit with inſufficiency, as if he could not diſcover the tricks and deceits of Satan? Yet
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:151253:31"/>
perſons who reject the Scripture, refuſſing it to be <hi>the rule,</hi> pretending onely to an <hi>inward rule,</hi> they provoke the ſpirit to give them up to deluſions, and open a gap for a deluding ſpirit to enter in. May not the Hiſtory of <hi>I. Galpen,</hi> once a Quaker (be an admonition and warning to all that Sect) who by caſting off <hi>external teaching,</hi> and hearkning to a <hi>voice within,</hi> was put upon miſchievous and deteſtable practiſes. Sometimes he was led to the Fidlers houſe, and being told it was ſuch a mans houſe, he anſwered, be it whoſe houſe it will, Chriſt led me hither, and hither I muſt go: Then was his hand forced to knock at the dore, and <hi>a voice</hi> bad him ſay, behold Chriſt ſtands at the dore and knocks: Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>while, he was carried upon his hands and knees out of the dores into the ſtreet, and when his wife would have ſtopt him, <hi>he ſaid,</hi> he muſt not be ſtopt, he muſt forſake wife, children, and all to follow Chriſt. Sometimes, he was forced to take up a knife, and to put it to his throat, and the <hi>voice</hi> ſaid open a hole there, and I will give eternal life. But in the end the Lord was pleaſed to give <hi>him repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance:</hi> whereupon he publiſhed a narration of thoſe things, to diſcover the danger of theſe wayes, and to be for <hi>caution</hi> of others, to take heed how they go out of Gods wayes, and forſake his ordinances: leſt falling into the errour of the wicked, they decline from their former ſtedfaſtneſſe, and leſt not receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the love of the truth, that they might be ſaved, God give them over to ſtrong deluſions to believe a
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:151253:31"/>
lie. See this Hiſtory ſet down largly by <hi>Mr. Samuel Clark,</hi> in <hi>his book</hi> called the <hi>Mirrour for Saints and ſinners.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. IV. The Quakers way is ineffectual to convince an Oppoſer.</head>
                  <p>Quakers in their way cannot convince a Gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayer, for what they call truth, others differing from them, call deluſion and errour, and how can they produce any evidence (that they are not deluded) for the conviction of an unbeliever, who knoweth not the teſtimony of the ſpirit in <hi>them?</hi> And him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf hath not the ſpirit, being in the number of thoſe who are without GOD, and without the Spirit. Suppoſe one ſay, that he hath a <hi>teſtimony of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> to aſſure him of his gracious ſtate, I would ask whether the <hi>teſtimony of the ſpirit</hi> be any otherwiſe then according to the Word of GOD? It is like, Quakers will confeſſe that every <hi>teſtimony</hi> ſpeaking peace (being contrary to the word) that teſtimony is not <hi>the voice of the ſpirit of the Lord;</hi> but the <hi>voice of the ſpirit of deluſion.</hi> Now I would ask (if tryal by the word be neglected) how is it poſſible to know whether this <hi>teſtimony</hi> ſpeake according to the word, or whether it ſpeake contrary to the word? If Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers ſay, that they are aſſured by the ſame ſpirit
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:151253:32"/>
that gives <hi>the teſtimony</hi> that it is according to the word, and other evidence they need not look after: the voice of the ſpirit that ſpeaks in them, is that beyond which there needs no enquiry. Then I aſke again, how can Quakers convince deluded perſons, who pretend to the <hi>teſtimony of the ſpirit,</hi> in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to their gracious ſtate? For they perſwade themſelves, that it is the <hi>voice of the ſpirit</hi> that ſpeaks peace to them; and other evidence they will not look after, <hi>the teſtimony of the ſpirit,</hi> is that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond which there muſt be no enquity. Now will not Quakers according to <hi>their principles,</hi> be ſo far from convincing ſuch of their miſtake, that they will rather confirme them in their deceit?</p>
                  <p>Now according to us <hi>ſcripture is the rule</hi> (which lyes patent &amp; open to both parties. And therfore a Papiſt of great note, is faine to acknowledge that <hi>Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris nihil eſt certius, nihil eſt notius.</hi> i. e. nothing is more certaine and more evident then the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.) And this is profitable <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, that is, for conviction, and (as was ſaid) though the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures do not actually convince the <hi>ſtubborn</hi> and <hi>ſtiff-heretick;</hi> yet there is ſo much in them as may ſatisfy an inquiſitive adverſary, who is willing to know right from wrong, and truth from errour. <hi>Appollos</hi> migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily convinced the Jews by the Scriptures.</p>
                  <p>It is inconſequential to argue, that the Scripture or written word, <hi>is not the rule to us,</hi> (to whom GOD hath ſet down his mind in write) becauſe it was not <hi>a rule</hi> to them who lived when the Scripture
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:151253:32"/>
or written word was not.</p>
                  <p>As for the Prophets, the event of what they foretold, was that whereby they were to be tryed, <hi>Deut.</hi> 18.22. <hi>When a Prophet ſpeaketh in the Name ef the LORD, if the thing follow not, that is, the thing which the LORD hath not ſpoken, but the Prophet hath ſpoken preſumptuouſly, thou ſhalt not be affraid of him. Ierem.</hi> 28.9. <hi>The Prophet which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſieth of peace, when the word of the LORD ſhal come to paſſe, then ſhal the Prophet be known that the Lord hath ſent him.</hi> But becauſe GOD for the try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all of his people, may ſometimes ſuffer ſuch things to fall out, as <hi>falſe-prophets</hi> fortell, <hi>Deut.</hi> 13.2. Therefore when men pretend themſelves to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets ſent of GOD, their doctrine muſt be brought <hi>to the rule and touch-ſtone of GODS written word,</hi> and thereby examined, <hi>Eſay</hi> 8.20.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He ſaith, page</hi> 31. <hi>that we disjoyne the word and the ſpirit, becauſe many preach and read the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and talk of them without the joyn'd concurrence of the ſpirit, which they ought not to do. Anſwer.</hi> He hath not offered to prove that the Scriptures ſhould not be read or ſpoken of, <hi>without the concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of the ſpirit,</hi> unleſs that be his proof (we ſay, they ought not to do) but upon what ground do ye ſay ſo? 1. The command for reading and ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Scriptures, hath not this condition annex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to it, that we ſhould read and ſpeak of the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, onely when we have a concurrence of the ſpirit, and never but then, where is there ſuch a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:151253:33"/>
mentioned? 2. What ſhal be the carriage of wicked perſons, who are ſtrangers to the drawings and motion of the ſpirit, muſt the Bible be to them as an <hi>Almanack out of date?</hi> Shal it be to them, as a book uſeleſs to look into? 3. When the Saints want the concurrence of the ſpirit, may they not read and talk of the Scriptures, as a mean of good to their ſouls? Hovv many cold hearts have been rubbed and chaffed into ſpiritual heat, by read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and talking of the Scriptures; In ſo doing the Lord hath met vvith them, and made their hearts to burne within them: Now though the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures may be read and ſpoken of, without the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence of the ſpirit. Yet to affirme this, is not to diſjoyne the Scriptures and the ſpirit, ſeparating the one from the other; for ſtill the Scriptures re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine to be the endytment of the ſpirit, being ſpoken and breathed forth by the ſpirit, <hi>Act.</hi> 28.25. <hi>Well ſpake the Holy Ghoſt by Iſaias the prophet unto our fathers, Act.</hi> 1.16. <hi>this ſcripture muſt needs have been fulfilled, which the holy Ghoſt ſpake by the mouth of David.</hi> Marke the Scriptures which <hi>Dav d</hi> and others of the Prophets penned, they are the breathings forth of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt himſelf.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Why doth the Quaker complaine ſo much, for my improving <hi>Eſay</hi> 59.21. as if it made ſo much againſt me; whereas it is directly to that purpoſe, which it was alledged for; namely, that GODS Spirit and word go together, and doth not the Lord here promiſe, that the Spirit and Word ſhould
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:151253:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>
continue with his Church and People, to direct and inſtruct them in all neceſſaries, throughout all ages ſuceſſivly, even unto the end of the world?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He aſketh, cannot dead things kill, if men feed upon them? Anſw.</hi> There is no doubt of it, yet the Scripture or that part of Scripture which is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the <hi>law,</hi> is ſaid to be killing in ſuch a way, as dead things are not: And therefore this killing Letter is ſpoken of as being <hi>the miniſtration of death, and the miniſtration of condemnation;</hi> For the Law threatens death againſt the ſinner, and curſeth every one that abideth not in all things that are written therein, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.7.9. Now are the dead things which the Quaker reckons up, thus killing? It ſhal not be denyed, but feeding upon <hi>ſand, gravel, ſtones, &amp;c.</hi> will prove deadly and deſtructive to the body, even as the drinking in of the lifeleſs poyſonous opinions of Quakers will prove hurtful and deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to the ſoul.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. V. Quakers have learned their Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage about the Scriptures from Papiſts.</head>
                  <p>Now any may perceive a Popiſh deſigne in all the Quakers reaſonings againſt the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> for both Papiſts and they joyne in ſtuding to diſgrace them.
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:151253:34"/>
Herein they very much reſemble one another. Ye may hear how Quakers liſp after the Papiſts, and concurre with them in ſpeaking the language of <hi>Aſhdod.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Do not Papiſts call the Scriptures,</cell>
                           <cell>Do not Quakers ſay of them,</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1. A noſe of wax, or a rule of lead which may be bowed every way as men pleaſe?</cell>
                           <cell>If the deluſion be ſtrong in the heart, will it not twine the Scriptures without to cauſe the <hi>ſcriptures</hi> to ſeem for it</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>2. Papiſts call the Scriptures inky Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, paper and parch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</cell>
                           <cell>Quakers ſpeake of the Scriptures as a dead letter;</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>3. Papiſts blaime the Scriptures, (the read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them by the Laity) as that which cauſeth controverſies, multiplyeth both He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies and Sects?</cell>
                           <cell>Quakers ſay, ye that ſet up the Scriptures as a rule, what Sects, what jangling, and conteſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is among you;</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>4. Papiſts preferre the Church before the Scripture?</cell>
                           <cell>Quakers prefer the light within, hence they ſay, that it is by the inward diſpenſation (that the outward diſpenſation of the Goſpel is ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceable) without which it hath no ſervice at all.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <pb n="51" facs="tcp:151253:34"/>
                        <row>
                           <cell>5. Papiſts contemne and vilify the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures?</cell>
                           <cell>Quakers will not have the Scriptures to be ſo much as a copy to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but the Spirit is both their teacher and their copy, and if they walk according to this, by looking upon it, and eyeing it, they ſhal be good ſcholars and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficients, they need not go forth for a copy.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>6. Papiſts ſay the church was judge before the Scriptures were written.</cell>
                           <cell>Quakers ſay, there was a rule before the Scriptures were writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten?</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>7. Papiſts deny the Scriptures to be the principal &amp; compleat rule of faith</cell>
                           <cell>And Quakers do the ſame.</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>So true is that of <hi>Tertullian,</hi> CHRIST is alwayes crucified between two theives.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He denyeth, That that more ſure word of prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie,</hi> 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19. <hi>is the ſcripture. Anſwer.</hi> Had it not been meet, not onely to have denyed this, but likewiſe confuted what was ſaid, proving it to be ſo; Is not the Apoſtle more to be believed (then any
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:151253:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Quaker) who expounds that more ſure word of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie calling it, verſe 20, <hi>not the word in the heart,</hi> but <hi>the propheſie rf Scripture,</hi> or <hi>Scripture propheſie,</hi> which is ſaid to more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſure then a voice fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heaven; not as if there could be any uncertainty of the Lords voice ſpeaking from Heaven: this is ſure e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough in it ſelf, but yet Scripture propheſie is more ſure <hi>quoad nos,</hi> as to us, becauſe a tranſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ient voice is more eaſily miſtaken, or forgotten, then a ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing record.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>VI. HEAD. Concerning Iuſtification.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. I. Wherein is cleared the Quakers agreement with Papiſts in the Doctrine of Iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</head>
                  <p>Page 32. He raiſeth a great ſtorme againſt me, <hi>as diſplaying the banner of diſingenuity, venting filthy imaginations, diſcovering vanity and malice, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending my ſelf in a fooliſh and vaine excurſion. Anſ.</hi> I wiſh the Gentle-man would reflect how much his pen &amp; ſpirit hath been dipt in the <hi>gall of Aſps,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>member
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:151253:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>
that <hi>cauſa firma eſt ſemper querula.</hi> I have not leaſure to anſwere his bitter revilings and rail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and therefore paſſing them: I ſhal endeavour to trace him, according to the method he hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, in giving (as he pretends) an honeſt, and plaine, and true account of their belief in the matter of Juſtification.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He ſaith, page</hi> 33. <hi>That we are justified by Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Christ, both as he appeared and was manifest in the fleſh at Ieruſalem, and alſo as he is made manifeſt and revealed in us, and thus Chriſt and his righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs without, are not divided from his righteouſneſs within, but we do receive him wholly, and undivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Lord our righteouſneſs in the ſight of God, and which ought not, nor cannot be divided. Anſ.</hi> Here he inſinuats that our opinion is, <hi>to divide the the righteouſneſs of Chirſt without, from his righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs within,</hi> which is the calumny of Papiſts againſt us; as if we held that becauſe Chriſts righteouſneſs is imputed to men, there needed no other righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. When as we mantaine <hi>that inherent righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs and imputed</hi> are inſeparably annexed: ſo that every one that is juſtified hath <hi>holineſs and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs wrought in him.</hi> We may not confound Juſtification and Sanctification (ſeeing the Scripture diſtinguiſheth them) and yet we muſt not divide them. Now that the Quakers <hi>fraud and cheatry</hi> (which I ſupect he is guilty of) in this thing, may be diſcovered; it will be neceſſary to enquire how the word juſtifie (in the preſent affaire, namely
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:151253:36"/>
as it imports the ſinners Juſtification before God) is uſed in ſcripture: and in this PROTESTANTS and Papiſts are at variance. <hi>Papiſts ſay, that it ſignifies to make inherently juſt and righteous</hi> (as ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefaction ſignifies to make inherently hot) on the other hand PROTESTANTS affirme that it ſignifies not the making of a man juſt, by infuſed inherent righteouſneſs; <hi>but to abſolve, account, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce a man righteous, Prov.</hi> 17.15. <hi>he that juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies the wicked, and he that condemneth the juſt, even they both are abomination to the Lord.</hi> Marke, to juſtify is not to make <hi>inherently juſt and holy</hi> (for this would not be abominable, but acceptable to <hi>God</hi>) but it is to <hi>abſolve and pronounce a man righteous,</hi> as to condemne, is to declare a man guilty, and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly ſentence him to puniſhment.</p>
                  <p>Now in that <hi>he ſaith, that they are juſtified by Chriſt revealed in them, by which he underſtands grace and holineſs wrought in them by Christ,</hi> (for he afterwards explains it to be that which in ſcripture is called Chriſt formed within.) Here <hi>he</hi> falls in with the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh ſenſe of Juſtification, by righteouſneſs infuſed. And his more full agreement with Papiſts, will appear even in that, wherein page 34. 35. <hi>he ſaith, that they greatly differ from them.</hi> To make good this, I ſhal do two things. 1. Set down the words of <hi>G. Keith,</hi> in his paper to me, (which <hi>Mr. Barclay</hi> acknowledges to be in ſubſtance the ſame with that which he hath written) <hi>Saith he, I perceive that by the righteouſneſs of Jeſus Christ imputed, by which
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:151253:36"/>
thou queries, if we be justified thou underſtandeſt not his work of righteouſneſs, he worketh in his Saints, but his obedience and ſufferings even unto death in the fleſh (not excluding but including his ſouls ſufferings) at Jeruſalem.</hi> To which I thus Reply, that we are even iuſtified by the righteouſneſs of his obedience and ſufferings, in that Veſſel or Man-hood not <hi>formally but cauſally;</hi> foraſmuch, as by his obedience and ſufferings therein, he was the <hi>procuring cauſe</hi> of that grace and power of his revealed in us, which produceth a work of righteouſneſs wrought in us: by which we are <hi>formally</hi> (as the School-men ſpeake) righteous, and this inward righteouſneſſe wrought by him in us, is truely and properly his Righteouſneſſe, and that on a twofold account. 1. For that by his obedience and ſufferings, he procured an enterance to mens hearts, to become a Prince and a Saviour in them. Secondly, In that he is not onely the remote procuring cauſe in the manner aforeſaid, but the immediat worker of it in us, by his immediate Arme and Power, ſo that he is well called the LORD <hi>our righteouſneſs.</hi> Now that there is no inconſiſtency between theſe two, to be juſtified by the obedience of Jeſus Chriſt in the fleſh at Jeruſalem, <hi>as the remote procuring cauſe,</hi> and to be juſtified by the work of Righteouſneſs wrought by him in us, as the <hi>formal cauſe</hi> is manifeſt, being cauſes of different kinds, vvhich do not repugne one to another, but ſweetly concurre to the produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing their effect. Thus far <hi>G. Keith.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="56" facs="tcp:151253:37"/>Second thing to be done, is to ſhew wherein PROTESTANTS differ from <hi>Papiſts</hi> in the matter of Juſtification: which will be notably ſeen by the anſwer both of <hi>PROTESTANTS</hi> and <hi>Papiſts,</hi> to this important and weighty queſtion, viz. what is that very thing, which cauſeth a poor believing ſinner ſtand pardoned and ſo juſt before GOD, and for which he is pronounced righteous, or abſolved from the accuſation and condemnation of the law, and accepted unto eternal life. Now the <hi>Papiſts</hi> in anſwering this queſtion, have <hi>recourſe to infuſed, inherent righteouſneſs,</hi> aſſe ting this to be the thing, whereby they are juſtified in the ſight of GOD. But <hi>PROTESTANTS</hi> though they look upon a <hi>principle of Grace</hi> within, as an excellent gift of GOD; yet they cannot leane to that for Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but think their onely refuge to be the <hi>imputed righteouſneſs of CHRIST,</hi> (namely, the ſatisfaction and merit of his Death, Paſſion, and Obedience in fulfilling the law) judging this to be the <hi>very thing</hi> by which Believers may appeare before GOD, and in the confidence whereof they may live and die: And for which they are accounted righteous, abſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from death, and accepted unto eternal life. Now let us hear the Quakers anſwere to the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned queſtion, and it will be found, that as <hi>Papiſts</hi> make the formal cauſe of Juſtification to be an inherent righteouſneſs wrought in us, and inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red into us by the Spirit of GOD, ſo the Quakers do the ſame; for <hi>G. Keiths</hi> expreſſe vvords are; <hi>that
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:151253:37"/>
we are juſtified by a work of righteouſneſs wrought by Chriſt in us as the formal cauſe:</hi> And therefore when in <hi>their Printed book,</hi> they ſay, <hi>that they rely on Chriſt himſelf revealed in them, indwelling in them, as the ground and foundation of their Juſtification.</hi> What can their meaning be? (though they blind the eyes of the ſimple, by uſing words inoffenſive in themſelvs) but as <hi>G. Keith</hi> explaineth it, to wit, that Chriſt by his obedience and ſuffering, was the procuring cauſe of that grace and power of his revealed in us, which produceth a work of righteouſneſs wrought in us by which we are <hi>formally righteous.</hi> Now is not this a manifeſt coincidency with Papiſts? For even they make the obedience and ſufferings of Chriſt, the <hi>procuring cauſe</hi> of that grace and righteouſneſs wrought in them, which they own as the <hi>formal cauſe</hi> of their firſt Juſtification. So that both Papiſts and Quakers deny the imputed righteouſneſs of Chriſt, to be the very thing by which a Believer ſtands pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned &amp; ſo juſt before <hi>God</hi> &amp; for which he is pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced righteous, or abſolved from the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demnation of the law, and accepted unto eternal life: which is look'd upon as carrying with it ſuch danger, that ſome PROTESTANTS are of opinion, that here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> doth raſe <hi>the very founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> And upon <hi>this ground, Mr. Samuel Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond</hi> undertakes to demonſtrate the <hi>impoſſibility of Salvation,</hi> in and by the principles of Quakers, in his book, called, <hi>The Quakers houſe built upon the ſand.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:151253:38"/>
                  <head>SECT. II. That Works are not Meritorious of Iuſtification.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He addeth, that he may not deny Justification by works, but plead for it, according to the true ſenſe and mind of the ſpirit. Anſw.</hi> Let him hold there and we ſhall go along with him, for we readily yeeld that by works, a man is declared and manifeſted to be a juſtified perſon, ſo that good works <hi>justify our juſtification:</hi> being notable evidences thereof, and ſigns of that faith whereby we are juſtified; for we are not juſtified by a barren faith, but by a faith which is fruitful in <hi>good works,</hi> and this is that which the Apoſtle drives at <hi>Iam.</hi> 2. But juſtification by works, ſuch as the Quakers plead for, is not according to the true ſenſe and mind of the ſpirit. Is it the mind of the ſpirit, that good works are the <hi>meritorious cauſe of Juſtification?</hi> Which <hi>Sam. Fiſher</hi> (one of the Quakers ring-leaders) plainly aſſerts, <hi>exercit.</hi> 1. <hi>page</hi> 84. and <hi>page</hi> 88. <hi>he ſaith, there are good works which in different reſpects are called (truely enough) both Chriſts and ours, viz. ours, as done in and by our perſons; Chriſts, as done only by his Power in us: and by theſe (call them as ye will, Chriſts or ours) is the juſtification of all, that ever were, or ſhal be juſtified, both deſerved and effected.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="59" facs="tcp:151253:38"/>
                     <hi>Object. We underſtand it not any other way then thus, that all their merit or worth is from Chriſt. Anſ.</hi> Where doth the ſcriptures ſay, that works wrought in us have <hi>merit</hi> in them (from Chriſt) to deſerve juſtification? This is a Doctrine of your owne forging and not of Chriſts teaching. Though good works ſhall not want a reward, yet they do not <hi>merit.</hi> It is falſe to ſay, that reward and merit inferre one another. PROTESTANTS uſe to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh between a <hi>reward</hi> of <hi>merit,</hi> and a <hi>reward</hi> of <hi>grace:</hi> which diſtinction is grounded on ſcripture, compare the <hi>original words</hi> in <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.46. with <hi>Luk.</hi> 6.32. and in that you affirme the reward to be of <hi>grace,</hi> then it is not merited by works; the Apoſtle oppoſeth theſe two, making them incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patible, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.6. <hi>And if by grace, then it is no more of works, otherwiſe grace is no more grace, but if it be of works, then it is no more grace, otherwiſe work is no more work.</hi> We acknowledge that God of his rich mercy and goodneſs, hath promiſed to reward good works, and being faithful he will not deny himſelf, 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.13. But a reward given by promiſe, doth not import merit and deſert, the reward proceedeth from the bountie of the Giver, and not from the merit of the receiver.</p>
                  <p>Now the Quakers wiſdome is much to be obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, in that they refuſe to owne the <hi>groſſeſt ſort</hi> of Papiſts (for then their draught would be found out, and their tendency ſufficiently known) but they (under the ſpecious name of new lights) can creep
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:151253:39"/>
towards the <hi>moderate ſort</hi> of them: who ſay, that works are not meritorious, but as they proceed from <hi>grace,</hi> and <hi>by vertue of Gods promiſe:</hi> when as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, if works be of, and flow from the <hi>free grace of God,</hi> this inferrs that they are not meritorious; for that which doth merit, muſt not be done by the ſtrength of another; eſpecially <hi>his,</hi> at whoſe hands we look to merit.</p>
                  <p>It is evident that the Gentle-man is of a higher ſtraine, then to be onely for a reward or merit (as he phraſeth it) <hi>of free grace,</hi> and upon the account of <hi>the promiſe:</hi> Elſe how ſhal he be able to reconcile himſelf to his brother <hi>Sam. Fiſher,</hi> who (<hi>exerc.</hi> 1. <hi>page</hi> 90.) maketh uſe of this Popiſh argument, namely, <hi>evil works are the meritorious cauſe of our condemnation, therfore good works are the meritorious cauſe of our juſtification,</hi> (inſinuating that there is a meritorious dignity in good works, even as there is a meritorious indignity and ſinfulneſs in evil works) this argument hath been often anſwered by a denyal of the conſequence, becauſe our evil works are <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly evil,</hi> but our good works are but <hi>imperfectly good.</hi> And giving but not granting, that our works were perfectly good, yet all the requiſits to make a work meritorious would not agree to them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He addeth, that the works that Papiſts ſeek to be juſtified by, are ſuch as they believe, none can be juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by. Anſ.</hi> Though they do not go along with Papiſts in ſome of their practiſes, yet they owne their principle, as hath been abundantly cleared,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:151253:39"/>
and therefore their correſpondence with <hi>Rome</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing manifeſt, we muſt conclude, that in ſtead of coming out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> they are rather running to it.</p>
                  <p>His next work, page 36. <hi>Is to make people believe, that we are near a kin to Papiſts;</hi> But none who know what Popery is, are like to give him credit, yet if any be of ſuch an eaſie faith, as to take upon truſt what <hi>he</hi> ſaith, then no wonder if the blind leading the blind, both fall into the ditch.</p>
                  <p>We ſhal conſider wherein he chargeth us as guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Popery,</hi> which <hi>he</hi> brancheth forth into ſeveral particulars. 1. <hi>Becauſe we deny, that we are juſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified by Christ dwelling in us. Anſ.</hi> We affirme that we are juſtified by the righteouſneſs of Chriſt, and when this righteouſneſs <hi>is believingly applyed and laid hold on,</hi> then Chriſt dwels in us, is this Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery? Or can any that know the difference between Papiſts and us, think that we agree with them in the matter of our Juſtification? 2. <hi>He ſaith, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to us the way to attaine to a ſtate of Juſtification, is not by believing in the light, wherewith Chriſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightens every man that cometh into the world. Anſ.</hi> That being a created work of light, it is not the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of faith, we are no where warranted to believe in a creature, but threatned with a <hi>curſe</hi> if we do it. 3. <hi>He ſaith, that we deny, that men are to know their juſtification, or that they are in a juſtified eſtate, by the immediate teſtimony of the ſpirit, and ſo do Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, Anſ.</hi> It is by us lookt upon as an errour in
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:151253:40"/>
Papiſts, that they are againſt the certaine knowledge and aſſurance of Juſtification, and do ſo much cry up doubtings; but though <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſhould oppoſe the knowledge of juſtification by an immediat teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of the ſpirit, this will not prove it to be Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: Every thing that Papiſts mantaine, is not Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, for it is known, they hold ſome truths in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon with the Orthodox: Popery is their <hi>ſuper ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded inventions</hi> and <hi>corrupt additions</hi> to the truth, amongſt which is <hi>their</hi> and <hi>your</hi> doctrine of juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation by inherent righteouſneſs.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. III. We are not juſtified by good and Gracious Works wrought in us.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He ſaith, that Rom.</hi> 3.28. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.16. <hi>The works of the law are excluded, but not the works of Chriſt in us. Anſ.</hi> Either the <hi>works of the law</hi> which in theſe ſcriptures are excluded from juſtification, muſt be evil and ſinful works, or elſe good and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious works: they are not evil and ſinful, for here the Apoſtle confutes ſuch among the <hi>Romans</hi> and <hi>Galatians,</hi> as had corrupted the doctrine of juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation; but it would be irrational to think, that their opinion was that ſinful works did juſtify: could they imagine that to be the cauſe of juſtification,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:151253:40"/>
which deſerveth and bringeth on condemnation? And therefore the Apoſtle excludeth (from juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) good and gracious works, and conſequently the <hi>works of Chriſt in us,</hi> as not being the merito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious cauſe of juſtification.</p>
                  <p>Further, we ſhal find that works <hi>ſimply</hi> and <hi>in general,</hi> are excluded from juſtification: and this is notably proved in the caſe of <hi>Abraham,</hi> who though a gracious and godly man, yet was not juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by works, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.2.3.4.5. <hi>For if Abraham were justified by works, he hath whereof to glory, but what ſaith the ſcripture, Abraham believed GOD, and it was counted to him for righteouſneſs, now to him that worketh is the reward not reckoned of grace, but of debt, but to him that worketh not, but believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in him who juſtifieth the ungodly, his faith is counted for righteouſneſs.</hi> Likewiſe works without that limitation <hi>(of the law)</hi> are excluded, <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.5. which ſcripture was cited by me, in oppoſition to juſtification by works, as the <hi>meritorious cauſe</hi> thereof, (verſe 7. <hi>that being justified by his grace, we ſhould be made heires according to the hope of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal life,) and indeed works in us, and done by us, neither merit juſtification nor ſalvation,</hi> though they be the qualification of the perſons that are juſtified and ſhal be ſaved, (for <hi>all ſuch</hi> are regenerate and renewed by the Holy Ghoſt.) It is a known ſaying, good works are the way to the Kingdome, and not the cauſe of reigning: and we onely deny them to be meritorious cauſes of bleſſedneſs, in this reſpect
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:151253:41"/>
the Apoſtle excludes works generally. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Gentle-man might have kept in his inſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, triumphing words, why ſhould he be at ſo much paines to make to himſelf <hi>a man of ſtraw,</hi> and then take pleaſure to undreſs him? There is no hazard to exclude the merit of works in juſtification, and yet to affirme them neceſſarily requiſite in the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject juſtified.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He telleth us page</hi> 38. <hi>That they juſtly caſt off the accuſation of Popery, having expreſs teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of ſcripture, that we are juſtified by workes, Jam.</hi> 2.24. <hi>Anſwer. Papiſts</hi> alledge the ſame ſcripture for juſtification by vvorks, and therefore one anſvvere ſhal ſerve <hi>you both:</hi> vve muſt diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh betvveen juſtification before GOD, and juſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification before men: if vve ſpeake of GOD, and being juſtified in his ſight, and before his Tribunal, then vvorks cannot ſerve the turne, <hi>Job.</hi> 9.2.3. <hi>But how ſhould man be juſt with GOD, if he will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend with him, he cannot anſwere him one of a thouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>and.</hi> Yet vvorks are uſeful in reſpect of men, to declare and clear our Juſtification as to them: thus <hi>Abraham was juſtified by works, Jam.</hi> 2.21. that is, declared to be juſt; hereby he was approved as juſt and righteous in his own conſcience, and before the World.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He ſaith, that good works are not ours, in that ſignification, as where it is ſaid, Hebrews</hi> 4 10. <hi>he that hath entered to his rest, hath ceaſed from his own works. Anſwer.</hi> None of us do affirme that
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:151253:41"/>
that good and gracious works are <hi>ours</hi> in that way that ſinful works are; and therefore <hi>his</hi> anſwere is but a ſhift: he cannot deny good works of Chriſt in us to be called <hi>ours,</hi> for though we be enabled to them by Chriſt, (and ſo efficiently his) yet they are <hi>ſubjectivly</hi> our own, <hi>our own faith, and our own repentance</hi> (it is not Chriſt but we, who repent and believe.) Hence it is evident that if juſtification be by good works of <hi>Chriſt in us</hi> (then our good works juſtify us) for theſe are <hi>ours</hi> in reſpect of ſubject and inherency.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He addeth, that faith may be excluded from juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, if it were granted to be imperfect. Anſwer.</hi> This is his groundleſs aſſertion, for the matter and ſubſtance of our juſtification is not <hi>faith;</hi> but the perfect righteouſneſs of Chriſt apprehended by faith: and upon the account of this <hi>object of faith,</hi> to wit, <hi>Chriſts perfect righteouſneſs:</hi> Which faith applyeth, therefore faith is ſaid to be <hi>accounted for righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Rom.</hi> 4.5.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He ſaith, that little faith is perfect in the meaſure of it, and though the Diſciples had doubting, yet the faith was not doubting. Anſwer.</hi> According to this he might as well ſay, that light in the Aire (at the very firſt breaking in, and dawning of the day) <hi>is perfect light;</hi> for though the Aire then be part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly light and partly dark, yet the light is not dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: yea, he might call gold (attended and ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with a great deale of droſs) <hi>perfect gold,</hi> becauſe the gold is not droſs. <hi>And page</hi> 39. <hi>he reaſoneth
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:151253:42"/>
no better, alledging that though we know but in part, yet our knowledge is not imperfect, we may know a thing in part, and that which we know of it we may know perfectly. Anſ.</hi> It is needful to enquire, what is meant by <hi>imperfection,</hi> is not that <hi>imperfection,</hi> when there is not that degree of grace in us, which ought to be? Now when our faith is but little, and our knowledge in part, have we all that faith and knowledge that we ought to have? Or rather have we not cauſe to complaine, that we come ſhort of the command? Who can ſay they know GOD, believe in him, and love him, in the <hi>highest degree</hi> that they are bound to do, if not, then theſe grace<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> muſt be imperfect?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Object. It is ſaid of Abraham, that his faith was perfected by works, Jam.</hi> 2.22. <hi>Anſwer.</hi> This comes to no more, but that his faith was made known and diſcovered by his works; like that expreſſion, where GODS ſtrength is ſaid ro be <hi>perfected in our weakneſs,</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.9.</p>
                  <p>In anſwering that place <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7.20. <hi>he brings ſcriptures to prove, that there are righteous men who do good.</hi> But this was not the thing denyed, he ſhould have proved that righteous men on earth do good ſo purely, that there is not the <hi>leaſt fault or blemiſh</hi> cleaving thereunto. As for that ſcripture 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.9. <hi>he that is born of GOD ſinneth not</hi> (it doth not prove an abſolute freedom from ſin; for this is contrary to the experiences of the Regenerat, and Saints in all Ages, who have bitterly bewailed,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:151253:42"/>
and ruefully mourned under the ſenſe of their ſins) the words in the Greek are, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, that is <hi>he maketh not ſin, ſin is not his trade.</hi> Now a man makes a trade of ſin, when in ſinning he is in his Element, where he would be: there is no work ſo pleaſing to him, as the work of ſin. But this is not the diſpoſition of a Regenerate Perſon.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He addeth that the Prophet Iſaiah</hi> 64.6. <hi>ſaith not all our righteouſneſs which is of thy working in us, who are Saints is as filthy rags. Anſw.</hi> Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth the Prophet ſay (as the Quaker brings him in ſpeaking) <hi>all our righteouſneſs, which we, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the beſt of the Saints can performe, of and from themſelves are as filthy rags.</hi> The Prophet ſpeaketh in general (and plurally) of righteouſneſſeſs, and that in the perſon of the <hi>whole Church;</hi> and not relating onely to the wicked and ungodly, therefore he uſeth the word <hi>all, and our righteouſneſs.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To affirme the Saints righteouſneſs to be <hi>filthy rags,</hi> is no juſt ground to make us aſhamed, for we do not reflect on the holy Spirit of GOD (as if filthineſs did proceed from him) he is good in giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us the <hi>leaſt degree of grace:</hi> not being bound to give us any (his work of grace and holineſs in us, is a ſpecial ornament to the ſoul, making it in beauty to reſemble GOD) but in reſpect of us, <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection</hi> cleaveth to this grace, in that it is not all the grace which the Law of GOD requireth of us: being commanded <hi>to love GOD, with all our hearts ſouls, and minds, Matth.</hi> 22.37. The beſt action
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:151253:43"/>
and works done and performed by us (as inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments) have ſomething of the <hi>taint of ſin</hi> adhering to them; where is the ſoul that is carried out in prayer, and other ſpiritual duties, with that love and delight, with that purity and fervency of ſpirit, which the ſpiritualneſs of the law doth call for? Now it is the <hi>ſin</hi> which cleaveth to the Saints good works, which is to be throwne away, this indeed is not an ornament but a deformity, for which we ſhould be humbled and aſhamed in the ſight of God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He ſaith, page</hi> 40. 41. <hi>that the Saints are ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate coworkers with Chriſt, but yet it followeth not that his works in them, and by them are defiled, and though it be ſaid, who can bring a clean thing out of an unclean; this hinders not, but that the Lord can, and doth make clean, thoſe who have been unclean, and ſo out of them who are made clean, can bring forth clean things. Anſwere.</hi> 1. We grant that there are thouſands in Heaven whom the Lord hath made perfectly clean, and their actings have not the <hi>leaſt impurity</hi> in them, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.23. <hi>Revel.</hi> 21.27. 2. We grant that there be many on Earth who are ſanctified and cleanſed: yet their cleanſing and ſanctification is but <hi>in part,</hi> they are not throughly cleanſed and perfectly ſanctified; there is yet an unclean part in them, they have in them fleſh as well as ſpirit; and however this unclean part, <hi>viz. the fleſh,</hi> ſhould be chained and kept down; Yet GODS People to their ſmart and grief, find the ſtirrings and ryſings of it, and the reſiſtance and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:151253:43"/>
it makes; whereby they are hindred from doing good perfectly, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.17. <hi>the fleſh lasteth against the ſpirit, and the ſpirit against the fleſh, and theſe are contrary the one to the other, ſo that ye cannot do, the things that ye would. Rom.</hi> 7.19. <hi>the good that I would, I do not, but the evil which I would not, that I do.</hi> Now men being but <hi>in part</hi> holy, and in <hi>part carnal;</hi> therefore the works which proceed from them have ſome filth and taint of ſin cleaving to them: there is ſin in the beſt men to undo them, if GOD ſhould deale with them in ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 130.3. <hi>If thou Lord ſhouldſt marke iniquity, O Lord who ſhal ſtand,</hi> 1. <hi>King.</hi> 8.46. <hi>for there is no man that ſinneth not:</hi> And yet we deny not, but by degrees the <hi>clean part</hi> encreaſeth, and the <hi>unclean</hi> is diminiſhed; yea and at laſt all the uncleanneſs ſhal be wrought out: there is a happy time coming, when the children of GOD, ſhal not have <hi>ſpot or wrinkle, or any ſuch thing;</hi> but this pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge is reſerved for them till they come to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, <hi>for there is not a just man upon earth that doth good and ſinneth not, Eccl.</hi> 7.20. Intimating that the juſt mans doing good is attended with ſin: ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs cleaveth to his good actions, as was formerly cleared by that ſimilitude (which the Quaker hath not in the leſt weakened) of clean water paſſing through an unclean pipe, and thereby receiving a tincture of <hi>uncleanneſs.</hi> The Gentleman that ſuppoſeth himſelf ſo well skilled in the outward creation, ſhould have inſtructed me, what that outward water
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:151253:44"/>
is, which is not capable of defilment: And having firſt done this, he might then (the more freely) have come to his ſupercilious application.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. IV. Iuſtification is not by inherent Righteouſneſs, but by the imputed Righteouſneſs of IESUS CHRIST.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He addeth that juſtification is taken for the mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a man righteous, and then it is all one with ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification. Anſwer.</hi> Is not this to confound what the ſcripture diſtinguiſheth? Now juſtification and ſanctification in ſcripture are alwayes ſpoken of, as diſtinct benefits, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.11. <hi>But ye are ſanctified, but ye are juſtified, Rom.</hi> 8.30. <hi>whom he called (namely to a conformity to the Image of his Son) them he alſo juſtified.</hi> And it is to be obſerved, that we need not conteſt with <hi>Quakers or Papiſts,</hi> whether the word juſtifie, ſignify to make righteous or no? Onely we ſay that the righteouſneſs which doth make a man juſt, or juſtifyeth him, is not <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent</hi> in him. And to aſſert juſtification, to be the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:151253:44"/>
making of a man righteous, <hi>by infuſed, inherent righteouſneſs</hi> (or righteouſneſs wrought in him) is to confound what GOD diſtinguiſheth, and to alter the ſcripture ſenſe of the word <hi>justify.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He addeth, page</hi> 42. <hi>that admitting the Apostle Phil.</hi> 3.9. <hi>ſpeaketh not of his righteouſneſs whileſt he was a Phariſee, yet he was ſtil to deny the work and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſs which was to proceed from his own will and ſpirit. Anſwere.</hi> The Apoſtle in the preceeding verſes, diſclaimed righteouſneſs proceeding from his own will and ſpirit: but verſes 8.9. he ryſeth higher, and goeth a ſtep further, even to the <hi>preſent time,</hi> (I account all things) intending the <hi>preſent graces</hi> and <hi>priviledges</hi> which he enjoyed, and diſclaiming them in the matter of Juſtification; <hi>Paul</hi> durſt not lean to any work of grace in him (the beſt mans graces being imperfect) as that which can endure GODS ſight, his exact and ſevere tryal: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is that word, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.4. <hi>I know nothing by my ſelf, yet am I not hereby juſtifyed:</hi> Notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his holy courſe of life, and obedience performed to the law, yet he ſaw a neceſſity to look after a more perfect righteouſneſs then this: ſuch as God himſelf cannot refuſe as imperfect and inſufficient, namely, the <hi>righteouſneſs which is of GOD by faith.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Then in the following verſe, there are the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent fruits and advantages, which redound to them, who renouncing confidence in themſelves, lay hold on Chriſt for righteouſneſs. Such as 1. Increaſe of Knowledge. 2. Mortification of the Old-man.
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:151253:45"/>
3. Reſurrection to newneſs of Life. To make theſe things the righteouſneſſe whereby we are juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied (as the Quaker doth) is to confound Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication with Sanctification, for here the parts of Sanc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tification (namely, Mortification, and Vivification) are expreſly mentioned.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He ſaith, My last argument from</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21. <hi>is moſt abſurd and impious, for accordingly it would follow, that as Chriſt was made ſin for us, who of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf knew no ſin, no not in the lest, ſo we may be made righteous before GOD, though we have no holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, no faith, no good thing wrought in us. Anſw.</hi> He indeed impudently and abſurdly wreſts my ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, the ſtrength of which lyeth in this: that as our ſins are <hi>inherent</hi> in us, and <hi>imputed</hi> to Chriſt, ſo his righteouſneſs is <hi>inherent</hi> in him, and <hi>imputed</hi> to us: Or as Chriſt was made ſin for us, by the <hi>imputation of our ſins to him, Iſa.</hi> 53.6. ſo we are made righteous before GOD, by the <hi>imputation of his righteouſneſs to us, he hath made him to be ſin for us who knew no ſin, that we might be made the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of GOD in him,</hi> upon which words, one thus excellently gloſſeth, he <hi>ſin,</hi> and we <hi>righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> and not <hi>ours;</hi> but the righteouſneſs of GOD, and not in <hi>us,</hi> but <hi>in him:</hi> Even as he <hi>ſin,</hi> not his own, but <hi>ours,</hi> nor in <hi>himſelf,</hi> but in <hi>us,</hi> ſo therefore are we the <hi>righteouſneſs</hi> of GOD in him, as he is <hi>ſin</hi> in us.</p>
                  <p>The Quakers inference is impious, and abſurd to imagine, that GOD (conſidering his purity and
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:151253:45"/>
juſtice) ſhould accept one as righteous in his fight, and yet his perſon remaine abhored of GOD, as an unholy ſinner; for the righteouſneſs of Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Sanctification are twin bleſſings, which go together in regard of GODS actual application of them: And therefore it is a miſtake aryſing (to ſpeak faireſt) from ignorance, to inſinuate that we are againſt inward righteouſneſs and holyneſs; ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we profeſs that without this <hi>no man ſhal ſee the Lord.</hi> And though we plead for the imputation of Chriſts tighteouſneſs as to Juſtification; yet we do nor hold, that there needs no other righteouſneſs at all: We aſſert <hi>Justification</hi> and <hi>Sanctification</hi> to be inſeparable companions, and that whoſoever is juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, hath <hi>inherent godlineſs and righteouſneſs.</hi> And therefore it is falſe to ſay, that we ſtrengthen the profane and wicked in their preſumption; for we declare to them that while they continue wicked they are without hope, and can lay no juſt claim to Chriſts righteouſneſs: and that they muſt be new creatures, of they can never come to the <hi>New Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He asketh page</hi> 43. <hi>Whether the Apoſtles did ſin in writting the Scriptures? Anſwer.</hi> There are two things that ſhal be ſaid to ſatisfy this demand. 1. That this was <hi>a ſingular extraordinary caſe,</hi> and no doubt but GOD (he that made an immaculate Conception, in the womb of her that was a ſinner) can preſerve extraordinarily ſome <hi>ſingular action</hi> from impurity, ſuch as the penning of the ſcriptures
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:151253:46"/>
was. But what is this to us, who can prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to no ſuch thing? 2. Though the matter contained and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered in the Scriptures, remaines inviolable and without the leaſt defilment; yet what hazard is it to affirme, that the Apoſtles in penning the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures were nor inflamed with love and zeal: Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the utmoſt extent of the Law, though be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing tall Cedars, their love and zeale was far above the love and zeale of others.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>VII. HEAD. Concerning the Quakers ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs magnifying of their Sect.</head>
               <p>I meane to be thrifty of my paper in anſwering the Quakers ſelf-advancing and exalting words. <hi>He ſaith, page</hi> 44. <hi>The flock of Christ is like to him, and can it be an unſutable thing, for one who ſuppoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth himſelf to be of Chriſts flock, to ſay, the flock with whom he is, it likeſt to Chriſt? Anſwer.</hi> What though the flock of Chriſt be likeſt to him? Should the Quakers therefore ſet up themſelves above all the people of GOD on Earth? Are none of Chriſts flock but they? Oh! It is intolerable pride to vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifie all the Saints and Servants of GOD in the
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:151253:46"/>
world, and to ſhut them out from being of Chriſts flock; for if this be their priviledge, then Quakers are not the <hi>moſt Christ like people,</hi> others may call themſelves <hi>ſo</hi> as well as they.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He ſaith, that Chriſtianity ſtands not in flying the ſociety of men, but the matter is for people, to have their occaſions and buſineſs in the world uſing it, as if they were not uſing it. Anſwer.</hi> This indeed is the great work and buſineſs; but can it be inferred from hence, that the true power and life of holineſs is more truely known to Quakers, and eminently held forth by them, then by any people elſe that have come forth ſince the Apoſtles dayes? It were good that that parable were remembred, <hi>Luke</hi> 18.9. <hi>And he ſpake this parable unto certaine which truſted in themſelves, that they were righteous and deſpyſed others.</hi> And truely what ever thoughts the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man hath of the PROTESTANT CHURCHES, (which in diſdaine he calleth our Flocks) there are many in them who live in the world very much dead to the world: and their communication and habitual courſe of life, holdeth forth their converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to be in Heaven; ſome of them have profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed it were ill for them, <hi>if they lived not every day, as if it ſhould prove their dying day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We are far from commending the way of <hi>Monks</hi> and <hi>Hermits;</hi> but <hi>their example</hi> was brought, to give chek to ignorant well meaning people: who are apt to be too much taken with an outward ſhew of mortification.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:151253:47"/>
                  <hi>He ſaith, page</hi> 45. <hi>ſuch as have had ſo much of the fear of God upon their hearts, that they durst not adventure upon ſin, would they not love to be perfect? Anſwer.</hi> Yes ſurely, perfection is their aime, and the white that they ſhoot at, and therefore they long to be in Heaven, where they ſhal ſin no more for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; but they know that the Saints while on Earth ſhall be clogged with ſin: and that the queſtion is not, whether GOD can by the ſingular aſſiſtance of his grace, keep any in this bodily life totally pure from ſin? But whether GOD hath not declared and revealed his mind to the contrary: and whether he ſeeth it not fit to have his people while in this world) exerciſed with relicts of ſin, to be as pricks and thorns in their ſides, and to keep them humble, leſt they ſhould be exalted above meaſure. And though the Saints do fear and dread to adventure upon ſin; yet through the ſtrength of remaining cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, and violence of temptation, they may (to their hearts ſorrow and grief) be drawn to it, which will be evident by reading over the <hi>ſeventh chapter to the Romans.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He asketh page</hi> 46. <hi>Whether ſuch as have lived in the ſenſe of Gods favour, would have pleaded for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance in ſin, and doth not continuance in ſin take away and ecclipſe the ſenſe of Gods favour. An.</hi> There are <hi>conſcience waſting ſins</hi> and falling or continuing in them, will greatly ecclipſe the ſenſe of divine favour; but there are ſins of daily incurſion which people may be guilty of, and yet enjoy the favour of GOD.
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:151253:47"/>
The godly dare not plead for allowing themſelves in the leſt ſin, approving of any ſin will marr our peace, and let in a ſenſible damp upon the ſoul.</p>
               <p>The perſons mentioned by me (in the Dialogue) as having ſuch notable enioyme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion with GOD, were far from <hi>Quakeriſme,</hi> they would have look'd upon <hi>your</hi> opinions as monſtrous, and to be abominated with the greateſt deteſtation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>VIII. HEAD. Proving the Quakers to be guilty of Equivocating.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>He ſaith page</hi> 47. <hi>That it is a falſe challenge and a calumny to charge them as denying Baptiſm and the Lords Supper, for they do owne theſe things in the ſubſtance and reality, and in the true acceptation. Anſwer.</hi> They are utterly againſt Baptiſm with <hi>water,</hi> and the Lords Supper as inſtituted by Chriſt <hi>in giving and receiving Bread and Wine.</hi> Now in this ſenſe Baptiſme and the Lords Supper are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly underſtood, and do not Quakers diſſemble and equivocate, when they ſpeak one thing and meane another? When they ſpeak plaine words that other men uſe, ſaying, they are for Baptiſme and the Lords Supper: but it is with a <hi>reſerved ſenſe,</hi> and not in that ſenſe wherein the words are uſualy taken; what is this but to ſpeak lies in hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſy? As the Apoſtle charges upon the Seducers
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:151253:48"/>
and falſe teachers in his time, 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.2.</p>
               <p>It is a ſlander to ſay that we place the <hi>ſhadow</hi> for the <hi>ſubſtance,</hi> the <hi>huske</hi> for the <hi>kernel.</hi> Do we not make a difference between the outward ſigns, and the things ſignified? Preſſing people no to reſt ſatisfied with the one without the other: and to ſeek not onely the <hi>bread of the Lord,</hi> but that <hi>bread which is the Lord.</hi> We know and believe that out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward priviledges will not ſerve the turne, there muſt be reality and truth of grace in the heart, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe GOD <hi>will puniſh the circumciſed with the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circumciſed, Ierem.</hi> 9.25.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>IX. HEAD. Wherein the Quakers Objections (againſt our ſinging of Pſalms) are anſwered.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 48. <hi>He confeſſes that ſinging of Pſalms was uſed by the Saints, that it is a part of GODS worſhip, when performed by his ſpirit, and ſtill may warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably be performed, and it is not unuſual among Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, yea Davids words may alſo be uſed as they ſute the condition of the party. Anſw.</hi> It is good that <hi>he</hi> grants (and yet it is no more then he ſhould) the lawfulneſs of ſinging <hi>Davids Pſalms,</hi> yet truly I ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:151253:48"/>
his words have not ſo honeſt a meaning, as they have a look, for if Quakers be for ſinging Pſalms; How cometh it to paſs that the exerciſe of this duty is not keept up among them at their meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings? Though they have been meeting in this place for about eight or nine years; yet none (for ought I can underſtand) have been witneſſeſs to their practiſe in this thing. But happily the ſinging that the Gentle-man pleads for, is of the ſame nature with that of ſome of <hi>his friends,</hi> who leading the horſe of <hi>I. Nayler,</hi> in his enterance to <hi>Briſtol:</hi> and ſinging (with one bare before him) <hi>holy, holy, the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly one of Iſrael;</hi> which they applyed to the ſaid <hi>Nayler,</hi> and <hi>he</hi> for <hi>his part,</hi> profeſſed that he might not refuſe any thing, that is moved of the Lord, and that he thought the Father did command them to do it. A woman Quaker ſaid, that ſhe witneſſed <hi>the holy of holies was riſen which moved her ſo to do.</hi> See <hi>Naylers Tryal, pag.</hi> 4.5.</p>
               <p>However, my arguments for ſinging of Pſalms remaine untouched, yet he moveth two objections againſt our way of ſinging.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> 1. <hi>Though ſinging of Pſams in the true ſenſe of them be allowable, yet as uſed by us is abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable, becauſe the perſons uſing it, are a mixed multitude. Anſwer.</hi> He hath not proved it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful to joyne in ſinging with a mixed multitude, hath GOD any where forbidden their ſinging? We find in Scripture that <hi>all the creatures</hi> are called u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon to ſing praiſes to GOD, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 148.11.12.13
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:151253:49"/>
                  <hi>Kings of the earth, and all people, both young men and maidens, old men and children, let them praiſe the Lord. Pſalm.</hi> 96.1. <hi>O ſing unto the Lord a new ſong, ſing unto the Lord all the earth.</hi> As for that Scripture 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.15. it doth not onely ſpeak of <hi>ſinging with the underſtanding,</hi> but alſo <hi>praying with the underſtanding.</hi> And if hereby he would inferre that the mixed multitude ſhould forbear ſinging, <hi>he</hi> may as well urge them to forbear praying: yea according to his way of reaſoning, I know no ſpiritual duty that they ſhould be employed in, becauſe they are dead in their ſins, and it is the living that ſerve God ſpiritually, and not the dead.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Object. All lying is abomination, but many times it falls out, that by ſinging of Pſalms the people come to lie in the preſence of God. Anſw.</hi> This ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection ſaith nothing when we ſing Pſalms that ſute our condition (then we are not guilty of lying) and the truth is, there is ſuch plenty and variety of <hi>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual matter</hi> in <hi>Davids Pſalms, matter</hi> of ſuch ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral and comprehenſive concernment; that they readily offer matter to us, to preſent our own caſe to GOD. But ſuppoſe that the Pſalme do not ſute with our condition, yet we do not lie in ſinging it, why ſhould the ſinging of theſe words <hi>(my heart is not haughty, and I water my couch with teares)</hi> be accounted a lie, more then the reading of them? May we not ſing theſe words as expreſſing the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of former Saints? And withal ſecretly wiſhing that the frame of our hearts were like unto theirs,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:151253:49"/>
is this to lie in the preſence of GOD?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>X. HEAD. Concerning Baptiſm.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. I. There is no Subſtantial difference between IOHNS Baptiſm, and CHRISTS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Page</hi> 49. <hi>He acknowledges that</hi> Iohns <hi>Baptiſm (was with water) and that his Baptiſm and Chriſts Baptiſm agreed in the Authour, but he ſaith as to the matter they are not one, for</hi> Iohn <hi>himſelf diſtinguiſheth them, Mark.</hi> 1.8. <hi>Anſwer.</hi> In this place <hi>Iohn</hi> maketh no difference between the <hi>matter of his Baptiſm</hi> and <hi>Chriſts Baptiſm,</hi> he onely ſheweth a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>his office and work,</hi> and <hi>the office and work of Chriſt;</hi> all that <hi>Iohn</hi> could do was to adminiſter the <hi>outward Element,</hi> but Chriſt could give the <hi>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> by means of the <hi>outward Baptiſm:</hi> ſo that <hi>Iohn</hi> here depreſſeth <hi>himſelf</hi> &amp; advanceth <hi>Chriſt,</hi> it being <hi>Christ alone</hi> who beſtoweth what the outward Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm ſignifieth. <hi>I indeed have baptized you with water
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:151253:50"/>
but he ſhal baptize you with the Holy Ghost.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He ſaith, they agree not in the end, for the end of</hi> Iohns <hi>Baptiſm was but to point and ſhew forth the other, as the end of the ſhadow is to point to the ſubstance. Anſ.</hi> The Scripture ſpeaking of <hi>Iohns</hi> Baptiſm, calleth it <hi>the Baptiſm of repentance for the remiſſion of ſins, Mark.</hi> 1.4. intimating that its end was to <hi>ſignify</hi> and <hi>ſeale</hi> remiſſion of ſin: which likewiſe is the end of Chriſts Baptiſm, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.38. Now <hi>Iohns</hi> Baptiſm and Chriſts agreeing not onely in the <hi>Authour,</hi> but alſo in the <hi>matter</hi> and <hi>end,</hi> this proveth thar there is no ſubſtantial difference between them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Object. They differ in ſubſtance, for it is written Act.</hi> 19, 2.3.4.5. <hi>that there were of the Baptiſm of</hi> Iohn <hi>who had not ſo much as heard of the Holy Ghoſt. Anſwer.</hi> The meaning is not, that they heard not of the <hi>perſon</hi> of the Holy Ghoſt, being Diſciples and Believers, they could not be totally ignorant of this, doubtleſs they were acquainted with the Scriptures, and from thence they could not but know, that there was a Holy Ghoſt; But the thing they were ignorant of, was the <hi>viſible, miraculous,</hi> and <hi>extraordinary gifts of the Holy Ghost:</hi> which then flouriſhed in the Church, and yet were not common to all that were Baptized, <hi>Act.</hi> 8.15.16. <hi>they prayed for them that they might receive the Holy Ghoſt, for as yet he was fallen upon none of them, one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they were baptized in the Name of the LORD JESUS.</hi> The Apoſtle did not anew baptize thoſe perſons that had been baptized with the Baptiſm of
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:151253:50"/>
                     <hi>Iohn:</hi> onely he gave a right explanation of <hi>Iohns</hi> Baptiſm, and then laid hands on them, upon which followed the gifts of the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>viz, ſpeaking with tongues and propheſying</hi> verſe 6.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. II. Shewing that Baptiſm with Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is an Ordinance of CHRIST and to be continued in the Church.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He addeth, That where Christ commands his Diſciples to baptize, Matth.</hi> 28. <hi>there is no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to baptize with water. Anſw.</hi> The ſubſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent practiſe of the Apoſtles may ſatisfy ſober per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, that Chriſts command had reference to bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing <hi>with water;</hi> Can there be a better comment upon the command then Apoſtolical practiſe? And it is obſervable that when <hi>Philip</hi> had preacht <hi>Chriſt</hi> to the <hi>Eunuch,</hi> and it would ſeeme had informed him of the <hi>ordinance of Baptiſm</hi> (however it is ſure, the knowledge of <hi>it</hi> he had) immediatly upon the ſight of <hi>water</hi> he deſired to be baptized, <hi>Act.</hi> 8.37. <hi>ſee here is water what doth hinder me to be baptized.</hi> And that command of Chriſts (<hi>Matth.</hi> 28.) to his Apoſtles, as it doth not expreſly ſpeake of Baptiſm
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:151253:51"/>
with <hi>water;</hi> ſo neither of Baptiſm with the <hi>ſpirit,</hi> and therefore if the Quaker exclude the one, he may likewiſe exclude the other.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Object. It is ſaid baptize into the Name of the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, and this is Baptiſm with the ſpirit- Anſw.</hi> This is affirmed, but without proof. The Name of GOD hath <hi>various acceptations,</hi> and how doth he make good, that it is taken here in <hi>his</hi> ſenſe, and not any other way? If by baptizing into the Name of GOD, he meane <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generating of men, making them just and holy like GOD:</hi> Then I ſay, this was commanded before, when our Lord ſaid, <hi>go teach (or diſciple) all nations,</hi> doth not this imply an endeavour to make them <hi>holy and righteous?</hi> And therefore if Baptizing them into the Name of GOD, import the ſame thing: this would inferre a needleſs tautology in the command of Chriſt, which the GOD of wiſdom will not owne, in ſo ſhort a ſumme of words.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He addeth page</hi> 50. <hi>That</hi> Peters <hi>words in bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing</hi> Cornelius <hi>after he had received the ſpirit im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply no command. Anſ.</hi> Is it not <hi>(totidem verbis)</hi> in plaine terms ſaid, <hi>he commanded them to be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized in the Name of the LORD, Act,</hi> 10.48. and the Scripture phraſe of doing a thing in the <hi>Name of the LORD,</hi> is as much as doing it at his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and by authority and warrand from him, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.20. <hi>Where two or three are gathered to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in my Name</hi> (that is, in obedience to my command) <hi>there am I in the midst of them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="85" facs="tcp:151253:51"/>
                     <hi>Object. That the Apoſtles received no commiſſion to baptize with water, is clear from that of</hi> Paul, <hi>where he ſaith, I thank GOD I baptized none of you, but</hi> Criſpus <hi>and</hi> Gaius, <hi>and the houſhold of</hi> Stepha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus <hi>for I was not ſent to baptize, but to preach the Gospel.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. <hi>Anſwer.</hi> If the Apoſtle had no commiſſion to baptize with <hi>water,</hi> how was it then, that he thus baptized ſome? He would not have done this of his own head and ſelf-will, <hi>Paul</hi> ſhould have ſinned in baptizing any at all without commiſſion: and therefore we gather that he was ſent indeed to <hi>Baptize,</hi> but his principal miſſion was to <hi>Preach;</hi> and this is not an adding to Scripture but the true meaning of it, which will be further cleare by comparing it with <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 6.6. <hi>for I deſired mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and not ſacrifice.</hi> Now it is certaine that ſacrifice was a thing that GOD required, but mercy was the principal thing, it was not ſo much <hi>ſacrifice</hi> as <hi>mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> that GOD called for. Even ſo Chriſt ſent <hi>Paul</hi> not ſo much to <hi>Baptize</hi> as to <hi>Preach;</hi> he ſent him principally to Preach as being a more principal work. The Quakers inſtance about worſhipping of Images, is altogether impertinent, the Religious worſhipping of them (more or leſs) is abſolutly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden. But <hi>Paul</hi> had not ſuch an abſolute prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as to baptizing with water, otherwiſe he had not adventured upon the baptizing of any.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He ſaith, That Scripture Matth.</hi> 28.19. <hi>relat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to the Baptiſm of the Spirit, and not to Baptiſm with Water. Arſw.</hi> Becauſe this is the maine
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:151253:52"/>
Scripture, that the continuance of VVater Baptiſm is grounded upon, it will be needful to clear that by Baptiſm here, is intended (not the Baptiſm of the ſpirit) but Baptiſm with water. For making out of which, two things are to be remarked, 1. That the Baptiſm here mentioned is held forth to be the action of the <hi>Apoſtles:</hi> hence Chriſt ſaid to them, <hi>go and teach all Nations Baptizing them.</hi> Now to baptize with the Spirit, is ſpoken of as the peculiar action of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> to aſcribe to men a power of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing with the <hi>Spirit,</hi> is to attribute to them, what is peculiar to <hi>Christ, Matth.</hi> 3.11. <hi>he that cometh after me is mightyer then I, he ſhal baptize with the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> 2. The <hi>Baptiſm of the ſpirit,</hi> is a ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying, renewing, operation of the ſpirit in and u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the heart. Now if this <hi>Baptiſm</hi> were here in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, then the <hi>duty commanded</hi> ſhould be confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with the promiſe, for the promiſe is, <hi>I will be with you,</hi> that is, <hi>by the aſſistance, preſence, and powerful operation of my ſpirit,</hi> accompanying your labours, making them effectual upon the hearts of people: ſo that underſtanding the words of the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm of the ſpirit, there ſhould be a confounding of the <hi>duty commanded,</hi> with the <hi>mercy</hi> and <hi>bleſſing promiſed:</hi> therfore the Baptiſm which Chriſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded is Baptiſm with <hi>Water</hi> (as is verified by the Apoſtles practiſe) which is to continue as the Preaching of the word, unto the end of the world.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Page</hi> 51. He undertaketh to elude the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures cited by me, as holding forth the excellent
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:151253:52"/>
end; and uſes of Baptiſm, the firſt was <hi>Act.</hi> 2.28. To this, <hi>he ſaith, that here is no mention of outward water. Anſ.</hi> Neither is there mention of outward water, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.16.17. and yet be grants that baptizing there hath reference to <hi>water.</hi> 2. <hi>He ſaith that repentance and remiſſion of ſins may be, and are found without water Baptiſm. Anſ.</hi> Therefore, Baptiſm with water is not abſolutly neceſſary to ſalvation, which we readily yeeld. 3. <hi>He ſaith, where Baptiſm with water is, both theſe are frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wanting. Anſw. Ergo,</hi> the Papiſts are in an er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, who affirme that Baptiſm doth <hi>ex opere ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rato,</hi> conferre grace.</p>
                  <p>Second Scripture is 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.21. To this <hi>he ſaith, that the words following clear the meaning, not to be water Baptiſm, not the putting away of the filth of the fleſh. Anſw.</hi> Theſe words do indeed manifeſt that <hi>Baptiſm</hi> of it ſelf, is not available unto ſalvation, and ſo the <hi>Popiſh opus operatum,</hi> is ſtruck at: as if by the meer receiving of Baptiſm, grace were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed. The like may be ſaid, to what <hi>he</hi> alledges in anſwering the other Scriptures, <hi>viz. Act.</hi> 22.6. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.26. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.7. in all which <hi>he</hi> proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth upon a wrong ſuppoſition, as if we thought that Baptiſm of it ſelf (or by any force of the outward e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lement of water) were effectual to cleanſe the ſoul, and to work grace and regeneration: Now this is far from our thoughts, who make the efficacy of it, to be onely the <hi>power and operation of the Holy Ghost,</hi> accompanying the ordinance in the right uſe of it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="88" facs="tcp:151253:53"/>
                     <hi>He addeth, that Baptiſm with water is but a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure, which was to give place to that one Baptiſm Epeſ.</hi> 4.5. <hi>Anſwer.</hi> This one Baptiſm was the Baptiſm which Chriſt commanded, and it hath been cleared, that this Baptiſm was Baptiſm with water: ſo that that <hi>one</hi> Baptiſm, cannot be called the <hi>ſubſtance,</hi> and Baptiſm with <hi>water</hi> the <hi>ſhadow</hi> ſeeing they are the ſame thing: and therefore it remaineth that baptiſm with <hi>water is an ordinance of Chriſt,</hi> and (the Lord concurring with it) a profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table meane to further our Salvation. And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as <hi>he</hi> reflects upon our baptizing of Infants, and the manner <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f it: it muſt be adverted, that the quarrel betwixt Quakers and us, is not whether Baptiſm belong to Infants, or whether it ſhould be by ſprinkling or dipping: but they are againſt all Baptiſm with water (even of adult perſons) not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing this, ſo much as the name of an ordinance of JESUS CHRIST.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>XI. HEAD. Concerning the LORDS Supper.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>He granteth page</hi> 52. <hi>that Chriſt was the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour of the Lords Supper, and that the Diſciples were enjoyned the obſervance of it, but he ſaith, this provss
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:151253:53"/>
not that it was to be of perpetual continuance. Anſw.</hi> Hereby is proved all that was intended, namely, that the ordinance of the Supper, hath Chriſt for the <hi>Instituter</hi> of it: and therefore it is called the <hi>Lords Table,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.21. and the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.20. Why then doth the Quaker vilify this Ordinance, by ſpeaking of it with that addition <hi>(the Lords Supper ſo called)</hi> cannot he find in his heart to give it that name, which the Scripture giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He ſaith, That by breaking bread Act.</hi> 2.42. <hi>is meant their ordinary eating. Anſwer.</hi> The eating there, is not ordinary, but Sacramental eating, which uſually is expreſſed by this phraſe of <hi>breaking bread,</hi> (a part being taken for the whole) <hi>Act.</hi> 20.7. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16.</p>
               <p>Neither doth <hi>Act.</hi> 2.46. make it evident, that their breaking of bread was their ordinary eating. This text ſpeaketh not of <hi>dayly eating</hi> (but of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing daily in the Temple) And though they did eat from houſe to houſe; yet the <hi>Syriak</hi> expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth it expreſly of the <hi>Eucharist:</hi> and it is thought that the Faithful abode ſometimes in one houſe, and ſometimes in another for fear of perſecution. It ſeemeth the Gentle-man knoweth not well the way of PROTESTANT CHURCHES, who thinketh that their Sacramental eating is but <hi>once or twice</hi> in a year, they plead that it ſhould be often: and the practiſe of ſome is anſwerable, in that they commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate once in a fortnight, and others once every
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:151253:54"/>
moneth. And albeit we do not go to this ordinance to make a full meale for our bodies (liberal feeding of them at ſuch a time would make the better part to be neglected) yet as much is made uſe of, as ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth to repreſent the <hi>Spiritual nouriſhment</hi> of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers by Jeſus Chriſt, and more is not requiſite.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He addeth page</hi> 53. <hi>That the eating mentioned Act.</hi> 2.46. <hi>is conjoyned with this, that they ſold their poſſeſſions, and if we make the Apoſtles example and practiſe our rule, why do we not ſell our poſseſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions as they did? Anſwer.</hi> We hold not our ſelves bound to follow the Saints and Apoſtles in every thing, all their practiſes are not to be imitated by us: And therefore we diſtinguiſh their practiſes, ſome of them were <hi>accidental or occaſional,</hi> being occaſioned by the ſpecial neceſſity of times and ſeaſons; theſe are not alwayes binding (but onely when caſes and ſeaſons are alike) and of this nature, was their ſelling of their poſſeſſions. Then ſome of their actions were upon ſuch grounds as are of <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual</hi> and common <hi>concernment,</hi> to one Church as well a another, to one Age as well as another, and theſe actions are ſtill obligatory: thus we ought to follow them in breaking bread, or in the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the Supper; becauſe this concerns the Churches of Chriſt in this Age as well as in their Age: ſeeing the Lord left it as a ſtanding and laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing monument of his love, to continue untill his coming againe <hi>in the clouds,</hi> as ſhal be made good in due time.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:151253:54"/>
                  <hi>He asketh, Why we do not abſtaine from eating blood, and things ſtrangled, as they did? Anſwer.</hi> The command in reference to theſe things was but temporary, and there is a plaine repeale of it: in that Chriſtian liberty is extended to whatſoever is ſold in the ſhambles, <hi>of that</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>eate making no question for conſcience ſake,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.25.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He asketh againe, Why we do not waſh one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers feet, which they were as ſolemnly commanded to do, as to take and eate? Ioh.</hi> 13.14. <hi>Anſwer.</hi> How is it then, that we do not read in all the Scriptures, that ever the Diſciples practiſed this thing? They continued in breaking bread, but where is there mention of their waſhing the feet of one another? The great deſigne of this command, was to teach the Apoſtles <hi>humility</hi> and <hi>love,</hi> and mutually to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcend for <hi>one anothers good,</hi> even to the meaneſt and loweſt ſervices: our Lord and Maſters patern of humility, ſhould make fellow ſervants aſhamed of <hi>their ſtatlineſs and pride.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He denyeth that the Apoſtle</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. <hi>recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended the practiſe of this ordinance by way of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand. Anſwer.</hi> What clearer command can there be then that verſe 28. <hi>let a man examine himſelf, and ſo let him eate of that bread, and drink of that cup.</hi> Mark, the Apoſtle doth not onely hold forth, that they <hi>were</hi> or <hi>might</hi> be in the uſe of this ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance; but that they ought and ſhould be in the uſe of it, plainly enjoyning this by way of precept: &amp;
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:151253:55"/>
withal diſcovering the neceſſity of previous exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, before their partaking of this ſo ſolemne an ordinance. It is further to be obſerved that the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians</hi> were to be often in the uſe of this ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, <hi>as oft as ye eate this bread and drink this cup.</hi> Now theſe ordinances which were aboliſhed by the coming of Chriſt (and yet for a ſeaſon were practiſed) they were nor <hi>often</hi> uſed by the Apoſtles and primitive Chriſtians: Let me clear this, by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancing in circumciſion (which is the <hi>inſtance</hi> very much talked of by Quakers) we read indeed that <hi>Paul</hi> circumciſed <hi>Timothy,</hi> (but whom other did he circumciſe?) He refuſed to circumciſe <hi>Titus, Gal.</hi> 2.3. and the reaſon of <hi>Timothies</hi> circumciſion, was to prevent the <hi>ſcandal of weak brethren, Act.</hi> 16.3. Now where doth the Apoſtle when he warrands Chriſtians to be often in the uſe of this ordinance of the Supper, give this as a reaſon? Namely, that it was for the ſake of the <hi>weak,</hi> who could nor ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainly be weaned from it, (let the Quaker ſhew this from Scripture if he can) The Apoſtle had a higher riſe, he ſaw <hi>divine authority</hi> ſtampt upon this Ordinance, <hi>that</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>which I received of the Lord, have I delivered unto you.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.23.</p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. I. The Ordinance of the SVPPER is
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:151253:55"/>
not aboliſhed, but to be continued till the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of CHRIST.</head>
                  <p>Page 54. <hi>He</hi> letteth of his great gun, (ſmal ſhot will not ſerve his turne) thinking to give <hi>this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance</hi> deadly wound; But really, <hi>he</hi> maketh a noyſe without doing the leaſt ſpoyle. Let us examine the Scripture which <hi>he</hi> brings for the aboliſhing and ending of the LORDS SUPPER, it is 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.15.16.17. <hi>I ſpeake as unto wiſe men, judge ye what I ſay, the bread which we break, is it not the commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the Body of Chriſt.</hi> Then <hi>ſaith he,</hi> the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle proceeds to ſhew what that bread was, <hi>for we being many are one bread, and one body, for we are partakers of that one bread. Anſwer.</hi> There is not a word here concerning the aboliſhing of the the Lords Supper. This Scripture affords a notable argument to promote union and onneſs among the profeſſing people of GOD: The drift of it being to ſhew, that as many graines of Wheat make up one loaf, ſo many members make up one Body of Chriſt; and partaking of that <hi>one bread,</hi> thereby they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs union in love towards one another.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He asketh, What is that one Bread, is it the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, or the inward? Anſ.</hi> It is both the <hi>outward</hi>
                     <pb n="94" facs="tcp:151253:56"/>
and the <hi>inward,</hi> and yet it is but one Bread, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the Sacramental union, which if between the ſigne, and the thing ſignified: and by vertue of this union, the <hi>ſigne</hi> ſometimes gets the name of the <hi>thing ſignified;</hi> as when Chriſt took the bread, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>this is my Body.</hi> Now by this anſwer, our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent onely is to ſhew how truely the bread may be called <hi>one bread</hi> (and that this ordinance <hi>is to be continued,</hi> we ſhal prove another way) and therefore it is a pitiful evaſion for <hi>him</hi> to ſay, <hi>that we might as well plead for the continuance of all the ſacrifices and offerings, &amp;c.</hi> Any one may ſee <hi>a non ſequitur</hi> in his reaſoning.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He addeth, page</hi> 55. <hi>That the Apoſtles and primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Chriſtians who had a large meaſure of the ſpirit, did uſe this ordinance, but it was not by neceſſity of command. Anſwer.</hi> It cannot be denyed but once there was a command to be in the uſe of this ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, Chriſt ſaid, <hi>do this in rememberance of me.</hi> Now there is no repeale of this <hi>command,</hi> neither in expreſs terms, nor by due conſequence from ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: unleſs he can make (a formal or virtual ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal hereof) to appear, we have reaſon to think that the primitive Chriſtians ſet about this ordinance, by vertue of a <hi>command,</hi> and that ſtill we are oblig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to do the ſame.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He addeth, That we have no ground to ſay, that Chriſt enjoyns the obſervance of this ordinance, till his outward coming ſo many hundred years after. Anſwer.</hi> The Scripture is plaine that the duration
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:151253:56"/>
and continuance of this ordinance muſt be, <hi>till Christ come,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.26. Now this coming of Chriſt is not to be underſtood of an internal com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>in a ſpiritual inward way</hi> of appearance in the hearts of his people; We deny not, but Chriſt promiſed thus to come to them, and hath made his promiſe good, by a plentiful infuſion <hi>of the graces of his ſpirit</hi> into their hearts; after this manner he came to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> who were called <hi>to be Saints,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.2. <hi>and had the Spirit of GOD dwelling in them.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.16. <hi>and were waſhed, juſtified, ſanctified in the name of the Lord Jeſus.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.6. <hi>and enriched in all knowledge,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.5. But notwithſtanding this <hi>inward coming</hi> they continued in the practiſe of this ordinance; and that (as hath been cleared) <hi>neceſſitate praecepti,</hi> in regard of a command; and therefore that coming (untill which this ordinance muſt be continued) what other can it be, but even <hi>Chriſts coming to judgement?</hi> Spoken of by the Angel at his alcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>when he ſhal come in like maner as he was ſeen go to Heaven, Act.</hi> 1.11. Now ſurely, Quakers muſt needs be great enemies to their own ſouls, who oppoſe this ordinance which the primitive Saints (who had the ſubſtance more then any of them) conſcientiouſly practiſed, and the Lord ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly commanded: and plainly intimats his mind, that it ſhould be perpetuated for the good and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of his Church, until his <hi>ſecond coming</hi> to judge the World.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="96" facs="tcp:151253:57"/>It is meeter to paſs by the Gentle-mans empty words, which fill up page 56. then to make a repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition of, or any reply unto them. Onely it is to be conſidered that the difference between Quakers and us, is not about the qualification of perſons, who ſhould be admitted to the Lords Supper; but <hi>they</hi> raſe the very ordinance it ſelf.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>HEAD. XII. Concerning the MINISTRY.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. I. Quakers are againſt a Mediate Call to the MINISTRIE: And an immediate Call <hi>they</hi> have not.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He addeth page</hi> 57. <hi>That it cannot be aſſerted in oppoſition to Quakers (who grant the ſame) that the Miniſtry of the word is an ordinance of Chriſt. Anſ.</hi> In the Dialogue I pointed at a Miniſtry <hi>mediatly called,</hi> and are Quakers for a mediate call to the Miniſtry? At when men are ſet a part and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained to that Office, by faſting, prayer, and
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:151253:57"/>
laying on of hands: It this be their mind, why do they ſpeak againſt thoſe who are <hi>thus</hi> ordained? As not being the Miniſters of Chriſt, but having their Miniſtry from men.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He asketh, Why I cite Epheſ.</hi> 4.11. <hi>Anſwer.</hi> To ſhew that Chriſt appointed Miniſters to be in his Church, and here is touched the principal and publick Officers given to his Church: whereof the three firſt were <hi>extraordinary,</hi> and but <hi>temporary,</hi> and the three laſt <hi>ordinary</hi> and <hi>perpetual:</hi> For ſhould <hi>theſe ceaſe</hi> as the former? Then Chriſt (might come under that imputation, of not being faithful to his promiſe) who gave <hi>them</hi> to continue <hi>till we all come in the unity of the faith unto a perfect man.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He addeth, That it is owned by them that the Miniſtry is not common, yet that hinders not but that any of them may ſpeake when the ſaints are met toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, according to</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.31. <hi>Anſwer.</hi> I would aske how he can make out, that the <hi>propheſying</hi> mentioned in that place is an ordinary Office? And if it be extraordinary, then it can be no foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, for Quakers to build an ordinary practiſe upon. Beſides when it is ſaid, <hi>ye may all propheſie one by one,</hi> it is not to be underſtood of all the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Church indifferently; for ſome are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden expreſly to ſpeak in the Church, verſe 34. And therefore that all muſt be referred to the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets:</hi> all the Prophets may propheſie, and the ſame Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>all are not Prophets,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.29.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="98" facs="tcp:151253:58"/>
                     <hi>He alledgeth, it is not proved that ſome are called to the Miniſtry i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mediatly without the intervention of men and ſome mediatly by men authorized for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. Anſwer.</hi> Were not the Prophets and Apoſtles called immediatly? The Lord ſent them by his own <hi>immediat command, Amos.</hi> 7.15. <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.1.6.7. was nor <hi>Timothy</hi> ſet a part to the work <hi>(me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly)</hi> by the laying on of the hands of the Preſby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery; 1. <hi>Timothy.</hi> 4.14. And it was given him in charge <hi>to lay hands ſuddainly on no man,</hi> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.22. we deny not but ſuch (recorded in Scripture) as had a <hi>mediat outward Call</hi> to the Miniſtry, had alſo an <hi>inward Call</hi> (that is, competent qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, gifts and abilities for the work) but it muſt be obſerved, that the inward call, and imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diat call, are not the ſame thing: In Scripture the one is oppoſed to the other, <hi>Paul</hi> who was immediatly called to be an Apoſtle; oppoſeth himſelf, 1. To <hi>falſe Apoſtles,</hi> who were called by the meer autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of men. 2. He oppoſes himſelf to <hi>ordinary Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters:</hi> who might have an inward call from GOD, and an outward call from men appointed by GOD for this work, ſee <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.1. <hi>Paul an Apostle not of men, neither by man, but by Jeſus Christ.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He addeth, That they who come preaching the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, not in ſpeach onely, but alſo in power and in the Holy Ghost, and in the evidence and demonſtration of the ſpirit, give ſufficient proof that they are called of GOD. Anſwer.</hi> Methinks then, he ſhould have more favourable thoughts of PROTESTANT
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:151253:58"/>
MINISTERS: who have been and are powerful Preachers of the Goſpel, being able to give as evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences of their miſſion from GOD (beſides their competent qualifications, and ordination to the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry) the ſucceſs of and ſome dayly aſſiſtance of the Spirit in their Labours; and yet the Quaker; in the heat and anger of their ſpirits, do not ſpare ſuch. But ſtepping up to the Throne of Judgement, <hi>they</hi> impiouſly cenſure them, as deceivers, hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, and children of the Devil.</p>
                  <p>He maketh much ado, <hi>page</hi> 58. <hi>as if we were fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in with Papiſts, in pleading for miracles;</hi> when as it is known we do not pretend to the doing of miracles; onely if men be ſo bold, as to aſſert an <hi>immediat call</hi> (which the Quakers do) ſuch as the Apoſtles had: we think it meet that they ſhew the ſigns of their Apoſtoleſhip, and the tokens of their immediat call; which hath been alwayes accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed either with the working of miracles, foretelling of things to come, or ſome other extraordinary thing. <hi>Ionah</hi> foretold the deſtruction, <hi>which within fourty dayes was to come upon Nineveh. Iohns</hi> call was attended with extraordinary things at his <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception</hi> and <hi>birth,</hi> and there were <hi>ſingular predictions</hi> concerning him.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Object. So there are ſpecial predictions concerning the Lords pouring forth of his Spirit, upon many in theſe latter dayes to propheſie. Anſwer.</hi> I ſuppoſe the ſpecial prediction which <hi>he</hi> aimes at, is, <hi>Joel</hi> 2.28. now this prediction was accompliſhed in the
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:151253:59"/>
extraordinary pouring forth of the Spirit upon the Apoſtles: when they were filled <hi>with the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> and began to ſpeak <hi>with tongues:</hi> the Apoſtle urg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth this, as the accompliſhment of that promiſe in <hi>Joel.</hi> ſee <hi>Act.</hi> 2.15.16.17. When Quakers can manifeſt that Scripture predictions <hi>(of preparing the way of the Lord)</hi> are applyed to them by Angels and confirmed by the teſtimony of Chriſt, as they were to <hi>Iohn,</hi> we ſhal then look upon them, as cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led as he was, but not till then.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He ſaith that Tit.</hi> 1.5. <hi>Act.</hi> 14.23. <hi>Prove not that thoſe Elders had not the Call of the Spirit of GOD in themſelves. Anſwer.</hi> What ever <hi>inward call</hi> they might have; yet they had not an imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diat call, which is by the <hi>immed at voice and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of GOD,</hi> without the intervention of men: and therefore in that <hi>Moſes</hi> conſecrated <hi>Aaron,</hi> it followeth that his call was not immediat (but rather an extraordinary mediat call) and yet he was called of GOD: being ſet a part in that way which the Lord had preſcribed and appointed.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. II. Proving the continuance of the MINISTRIE.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He addeth that my proof from Epheſ.</hi> 4.12.13.
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:151253:59"/>
                     <hi>is altogether impertinent, becauſe we are against the perfection of the Sa nts in this life. Anſwer.</hi> This is a pregnant and pertinent proof to bold forth the continuance of the Miniſtry, the terme whereof is the day of judgement: For this Miniſtry muſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue till all the Elect come &amp; meet in that compleat unity (not onely of opinion, but alſo of he art and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) which is called the <hi>unity of the faith,</hi> and it is that which the Saints ſhal attaine unto: being come to the ſtate and degree of perfection in the life to come, which ſtate is here called a perfect man.</p>
                  <p>Neither can it be gathered from verſe 14. (that this perfection is on earth) where the Apoſtle onely ſheweth that the Miniſtry of the word is a meane or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained by <hi>God,</hi> to preſerve &amp; keep his People from the poyſon of dangerous errours, and from the ſnares of <hi>ſubtile, crafty ſeducers.</hi> It is true, the Miniſtry is given for <hi>perfecting of the Saints,</hi> and hereby (as a meane) they are brought to <hi>perfection in parts,</hi> and preſſed to ſeek after an <hi>abſolute full perfection</hi> even in degrees. Now in caſting of the Miniſtry that we plead for (namely a Miniſtry according to the order delivered by the Apoſtles and preſcribed in the word.) Quakers manifeſt themſelves to be enemies to the Miniſtry of Chriſt, and injurious to their own ſouls.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:151253:60"/>
               <head>XIII. HEAD. Concerning the SABBATH.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. I. The obſervation of the SABBATH is warranted by the fourth Command.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He addeth page</hi> 59. <hi>That as the fourth Command requireth the obſervation of one day of ſeven, ſo it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly inſtanceth that day, to be the ſeventh. Anſ<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> Though the fourth Command inſtance in the <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth day</hi> (that is for number) yet it ſpeaketh not preciſely of the <hi>ſeventh day</hi> in order from the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. It is ſaid <hi>ſix dayes ſhalt thou labour, but the ſeventh is the Sabbath,</hi> mark, the <hi>ſeventh</hi> is the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, the Lord ſaith not the <hi>ſeventh</hi> from the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. It is likewiſe worthy ſpecial obſervation to conſider the preceptive and the benedictive part of the fourth Command, or the beginning and conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of it. In the beginning it is ſaid, <hi>Remember the Sabbath day to keep it holy.</hi> In the concluſion it is ſaid, <hi>Wherefore the Lord bleſſed the Sabbath day and hallowed it;</hi> obſerve the phraſe, not <hi>ſeventh day,</hi> but <hi>Sabbath day</hi> is bleſſed, ſo that the fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:151253:60"/>
neither begins nor ends with that terme the <hi>ſeventh day,</hi> but with that of the <hi>Sabbath day:</hi> which is an evidence that the deſigne of this Command, is not to bind the Church to a preciſe keeping of the <hi>ſeventh day</hi> from the creation; for there is no expreſs mention of <hi>that day</hi> in all the fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand: the maine intendment therefore of the fourth Command is to preſcribe a <hi>ſeventh day</hi> to be keept holy (after ſix dayes labour) which GOD ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointeth: And this to the People of GOD under the Old Teſtament, was the <hi>ſeventh day</hi> of the week, (it being appointed by GOD in the firſt inſtitution of the <hi>Sabbath, Gen.</hi> 2 3.) but to us it is the <hi>firſt day</hi> of the week; the Sabbath being tranſlated and changed to <hi>this day</hi> by divine authority, as will af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards appear.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Object. The keeping of one day of the week for a Sabbath is not perpetual, but aboliſhed, Coloſſ.</hi> 2.16.17. <hi>let no man judge you in meat or drink, or in reſpect of a holy day, or new Moon, or of the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath dayes. Anſwer.</hi> Here the Apoſtle oppoſeth ceremonial ordinances, but not Goſpel inſtitutions. Indeed the <hi>Old Anabaptists,</hi> and <hi>Familiſts</hi> (with whom Quakers go along) they urged this text againſt all difference of dayes under the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel; though the Apoſtles onely deſigne be to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cry the <hi>ſeveral ſorts of dayes,</hi> which were in uſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Jews, of which he gives an obſervable enu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: proceeding from their <hi>yearlie holy dayes,</hi> to their <hi>monethlie new Moons,</hi> and from them to their
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:151253:61"/>
                     <hi>weeklie Sabbaths:</hi> ſo that granting the weekly Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath to be here taken in, yet it maketh nothing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Christian Sabbath,</hi> but againſt the <hi>old ſeventh day Sabbath.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Object. Rom.</hi> 14.6. <hi>plainlie holdeth forth all dayes to be alike. Anſwer.</hi> What was ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ſerveth to clear this Scripture, it ſpeaketh of <hi>ceremonial daies:</hi> of ſuch dayes as are in the rank with <hi>ceremonial meats,</hi> and therefore oppoſeth not the moral weekly Sabbath.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Object. Gal.</hi> 4.10.11. <hi>Ye obſerve daies and moneths, times, and years, I am affraid of you. Anſ.</hi> There is a twofold obſervation of dayes, <hi>moral</hi> and <hi>ceremonial,</hi> now the Apoſtle ſpeaketh not againſt the former, but the latter: he would not have Jewiſh times (ſuch a their <hi>Sabbatical yeares,</hi> their <hi>annual feaſts;</hi> their <hi>monethlie feasts,</hi> called <hi>new Moons,</hi> their <hi>weeklie ſeventh day,</hi> which is probably thought to be included in that clauſe ye <hi>obſerve dayes</hi>) to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved (which the Jewiſh falſe teachers cryed up) but he was far from crying down the fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, which is no leſs binding then the reſt of the Decalogue: it being delivered in the ſame <hi>majeſtick manner</hi> preſſed with the <hi>ſame ſeveritie,</hi> and written by the <hi>ſame finger of GOD,</hi> and put into the <hi>ſame Ark,</hi> with the reſt. He that ſaid, <hi>Thou ſhalt not commit adulterie; Thou ſhalt not ſteal;</hi> ſaid like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, <hi>Remember the Sabbath day keep it holy:</hi> and therefore if perſons take upon them to ſacrifice this Command to their wild fancies, they need not ſpare
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:151253:61"/>
the other Commands. And in very deed the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of GOD, are little beholden either to Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts or Quakers; for Papiſts reject the ſecond Command, and Quakers give the ſame uſage to the fourth. And this puts me in mind of a Story I have heard concerning <hi>an Honeſt Countrey-man,</hi> who travelling on the rod, there were two who denyed the Sabbath, came up to him, upon a deſigne to try his knowledge; the queſtion they propounded was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the number of the Commands, <hi>the well mean<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing man,</hi> knew the perſons and ſhapt an anſwer ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to their principles, telling them there were eight Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mands: whereupon the <hi>Querists</hi> made ſport, and upbraided <hi>the poor man</hi> with his profeſſion, and his ignorance; but he gravely replyed, that the ſcripture indeed ſpake of ten Commands, <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.13. but they had taken away one Command, and the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts another: ſo that between them, they had brought the Commands from ten to eight.</p>
                  <p>In his anſwer to <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.20. where Chriſt intimats the continuance of a Sabbath. <hi>He ſaith, that Sabbath, is neither here nor elſe where ſaid to be the firſt day of the week. Anſwer.</hi> Though there be no expreſs mention in this place, of the firſt day of the week; yet in that it proves the continuance of a <hi>Sabbath,</hi> it overthrowes the Quakers opinion: who would be levelling all dayes, making them alike. And it is to be remarked, that Chriſt was come into the world, &amp; relateth the ſad things, which were to befal his Diſciples, after he was aſcended to the
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:151253:62"/>
Father; and yet even then a Sabbath was in being</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He addeth page</hi> 60. <hi>That as the outward Jew ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> not be put to fly on his outward Sabbath, ſo the in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ward Jew deſireth much more that he may keep hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Sabbath, which is his ſpiritual reſt in Chriſt, Heb</hi> 4.9. <hi>Anſwer.</hi> The Apoſtle in this chapter ſpeaketh of a reſt, which Believers onely enter into; And ſheweth, 1. That this reſt is not the reſt of the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, verſe 4. 2. That it is not the reſt of the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> verſe 8. <hi>If Jeſus</hi> (that is <hi>Joſhua) had given them reſt, then would he not have ſpoken o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> another reſt.</hi> It followeth then that the reſt which Believers onely ſhall enter into, is the reſt of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, verſe 9. <hi>there remains therefore a rest for the people of GOD.</hi> Now becauſe there is an eternal reſt promiſed to the Believing, obedient people of GOD, ſaith this, any thing why they ſhould not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve one day of ſeven, as a Sabbath unto the Lord, Oh, the conſcientious keeping of the Sabbath is a comfortable evidence of thoſe that ſhal be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to this reſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. II. The firſt day of the Week is ſet a part for the Service of GOD by Divine Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He addeth, If we have the ſame authority for
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:151253:62"/>
keeping the first day of the week, as the Jews had for keeping their day, then let it be produced. Anſwer.</hi> It was produced before, but he would not ſee it: however for the ſake of others we ſhal co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider again that Scripture, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.10. <hi>I was in the Spirit on the Lords day.</hi> Now that by the Lords day is meant the firſt day of the week, will be clear, if we advert that there are peculiar grounds, why this day is ſingular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be called the Lords day, beyond other dayes; Becauſe, 1. on this day our Lord aroſe, and ceaſed from the work of Redemption, <hi>Mark.</hi> 16.1.2. 2. On this day our Lord graciouſly (and frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) appeared unto his Diſciples, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 20.19. 3. On this day our Lord declared himſelf to be the Son of GOD with Power, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.4. 4. On this day our Lord plentifully poured his Spirit upon his Apoſtles, for Penticoſt (or the fifthtieth day from the Paſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver) is computed to have fallen out that year on this day, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.1.2. Thus it is apparent that the firſt day of the week may (beyond other dayes) be peculiarly termed the Lords day. To this may be ſubjoyned the obſervation of famous <hi>Beza,</hi> who ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves out of an ancient Greek Manuſcript, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the firſt day of the week, is expreſly called the Lords day. Now this day being called the Lords, it imports that the Lord is the authour and inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of it, this tittle (as I remember) <hi>the Lords,</hi> is in the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> attributed but to two things: namely, to the Supper (<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>) and the day (<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>) now the Supper is called the
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:151253:63"/>
Lords, becauſe he did inſtitute and appoint it, and ſo the day is called the <hi>Lords,</hi> becauſe Chriſt is the authour and appointer of it: and therefore in keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this day we walk obediently to the fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, which requires on day (to be obſerved as a Sabbath) which the Lord appointeth: we then keep this day, becauſe it is a day inſtituted and appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Lord.</p>
                  <p>Neither muſt thoſe two expreſſions, <hi>the day of the Lord,</hi> and the <hi>Lords day,</hi> be confounded; for all dayes wherein GOD executeth judgement upon ſinners are dayes of the Lord, <hi>Amos</hi> 5.18.20. But the Lords day mentioned <hi>Revel.</hi> 1. is but one, which at that time was known to the Churches to be the firſt day of the week. <hi>Ignatius</hi> (who lived in <hi>Iohns</hi> time) ſpeaking of this day, ſaith, <hi>Omnis Chriſti a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mator, Dominicum celebret diem, Reginam &amp; Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipem dierum omnium:</hi> that is, <hi>let every one that loveth Chriſt keep holy the Lords day, which is the Queen and Empreſs of all dayes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Whereas page</hi> 61. 62. <hi>he inſinuats that every day, even all the dayes of our life, are to be given up unto the Lord and ſpent in his ſervice. Anſwer.</hi> It is true, we ought daily to be employed in the worſhip and ſervice of GOD; But as this will not inferre, that every day is to be keeps as a <hi>ſabbath</hi> (which muſt be wholly conſecrated to the ſervice of GOD) ſo it makes nothing againſt the keeping of a <hi>weekly ſabbath?</hi> for the <hi>Jews</hi> before Chriſt were bound e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day to ſerve GOD; and yet they were tyed to
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:151253:63"/>
the obſervance of a <hi>weekly Sabbath.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thus my former charge is ſtill made good againſt Quakers, that it is for the inventions of men, but the ordinances of Jeſus Chriſt which they diſowne.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>HEAD. XIV. Concerning Original Sin which Quakers deny.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>He affirmeth page</hi> 62. <hi>That the thing which we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend by original ſin, is not expreſſed in ſcripture. Anſ.</hi> Is it not expreſſed in Scripture, that there is <hi>corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> and <hi>ſin</hi> in us from our conception and birth? (And this is that which we intend by original ſin) for this the <hi>Scripture</hi> is plaine, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.6. <hi>that which is born of the fleſh is fleſh,</hi> intimating that men by their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural birth are corrupt and fleſhly. <hi>Job</hi> ſpeaking of mans birth uttereth theſe words, <hi>who can bring a clean thing out of an unclean, Job,</hi> 14.4. <hi>David</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged that <hi>corruption</hi> and <hi>ſin,</hi> wherewith he was defiled from his <hi>conception, Pſalm</hi> 51.5.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He ſaith, the thing that we intend by original ſin, is, that all infants are ſinners before GOD onely for Adams ſin. Anſwer.</hi> It ſeemeth <hi>he</hi> is not well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with our Doctrine about original ſin. It
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:151253:64"/>
is true we aſſert (and with good warrand) that In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants are guilty of <hi>Adams</hi> ſin, <hi>for in Adam all die,</hi> and therefore <hi>in him all have ſinned,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.22. And though <hi>Adams</hi> firſt ſin may be called original ſin; yet we diſtinguiſh of original ſin, it being ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>imputed</hi> or <hi>inherent.</hi> Original ſin <hi>imputed,</hi> is <hi>the diſobedience of Adam,</hi> which is imputed to his poſterity, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.19. <hi>by one mans diſobedience many were made ſinners.</hi> Original ſin <hi>inherent,</hi> is that hereditary inbred corruption, which we brought with us into the world: and this is conveyed and deriv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Infants from <hi>their immediat Parents, in ſin did my mother conceive me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 63. <hi>He denyeth that the guilt of Adams firſt ſin lyes at the door of Infants who never actually ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. Anſwer.</hi> The <hi>Apostle</hi> confutes the <hi>Quaker Rom.</hi> 5.12. Where firſt he ſheweth, that by <hi>one man,</hi> (namely <hi>Adam</hi>) ſin came into the world. Secondly, That <hi>death</hi> entered the world by <hi>ſin.</hi> Thirdly, That death (i. e. lyableneſs to death) paſſed <hi>upon all.</hi> Fourthly, The reaſon why death (which came by the ſin of one man) paſſed upon all; <hi>for that all have ſinned,</hi> ſo that Infants are not exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the guilt of that one mans ſin: which will be further clear, if it be conſidered that the Greek (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) wil bear <hi>in whom,</hi> thus it is varied on the margin of our books; and ſo <hi>Beza</hi> renders it, and they who are well skilled in the Greek, think this the beſt reading. Now it is onely one of three things that can be alledged for the <hi>antecedent</hi> of this
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:151253:64"/>
relative in whom, either <hi>ſin,</hi> or <hi>death,</hi> or that <hi>one man:</hi> but it is not ſin, for <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> (rendred ſin) cannot anſwere the <hi>Greek relative,</hi> becauſe they are of different genders; neither is it death (as the Quakers pretend) for what ſenſe is it to ſay, <hi>in which death all have ſinned?</hi> This is an improper ſpeach. It was long ſince obſerved, that <hi>in peccato moriun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur homines, non in morte peccant, men dye in ſin, they are not ſaid to ſin in death:</hi> and therefore this <hi>in whom,</hi> hath reference to that <hi>one man,</hi> namely, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam;</hi> in him, <hi>all</hi> (without exception of Infants) <hi>have ſinned.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object. It is plaine that ſin is not imputed to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, for the Apoſtle ſaith Rom.</hi> 5.13. <hi>ſin is not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted where there is no Law, now Infants are not capable of a Law. Anſwer.</hi> Infants may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered in reſpect of their <hi>own perſons,</hi> or in reſpect of their <hi>repreſentative:</hi> now though Infants as to their owne <hi>proper perſons</hi> be not capable of a law; for they cannot diſcerne between their right hand and their left, yet their <hi>repreſentative</hi> was capable of a law; Yea, to <hi>Adam</hi> the repreſentative of all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, a law was actually given, and this will ſerve to anſwer the Quakers two other Objections.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Object. Why ſhould Infants be guilty of</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dams <hi>ſin, and not of the ſin of their other forefathers? Anſwer.</hi> The reaſon is, becauſe <hi>Adam</hi> is to be lookt upon, not as <hi>a ſingle individual perſon;</hi> but as <hi>a publick univerſall perſon:</hi> Now that <hi>Adam</hi> was <hi>a publick perſon</hi> repreſenting mankind, is evident
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:151253:65"/>
from the miſerable event of his ſin, which made not onely himſelf obnoxious to death, but likewiſe his Poſterity deſcending from him in an ordinary way, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.12. Yea, ſuch of his Poſterity have come under death, as never actually ſinned in their own perſons, <hi>verſe</hi> 14. <hi>death reigned from Adam to Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, even over them that had not ſinned, after the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude of Adams tranſgreſſion;</hi> that is, over In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants who ſinned not actually as <hi>Adam</hi> did, in their own perſons, yet they were ſubject to death as well as others.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Object. It is ſaid Ezek.</hi> 18.20. <hi>the ſoul that ſinneth it ſhal die, the ſon ſhal not bear the ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of the father. Anſwer.</hi> What if the ſon be a partaker of the <hi>fathers iniquity,</hi> will not GOD then viſit the iniquity of the fathers upon the children? <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.5. Now though Infants partake not of <hi>Adams</hi> ſin by imitation, yet they partake of his ſin, in ſo far as <hi>Adam</hi> was the root of Mankind, and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned as a publick perſon repreſenting them: the <hi>root</hi> dying all the branches dyed in <hi>it,</hi> and with <hi>it,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.22.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He ſaith page</hi> 64. <hi>That Infants are ſubject to diſeaſes, and death, this proves them not to be ſinners. Anſ.</hi> The Scripture gives ground to believe, that if man had not ſinned he ſhould not have dyed; becauſe death is onely threatned in caſe of <hi>mans ſinning, Gen.</hi> 2.17. and upon <hi>his ſinning</hi> GOD told him (not till then) <hi>that he ſhould returne to the dust, Gen.</hi> 3.19. It is true the inanimat creatures ſuffer for the
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:151253:65"/>
ſin of man. But it followeth not, that therefore all of Mankind who ſuffer death are not <hi>ſinners;</hi> eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cialy, ſeeing the Apoſtle plainly affirmes, <hi>that death entered by ſin, and death hath paſſed upon all, for that all have ſinned:</hi> ſo that he concludes all perſons who are lyable to death, to be under the <hi>guilt of ſin,</hi> and conſequently <hi>ſinners.</hi> Chriſt indeed though in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent, was a man of ſorrowes, becauſe our ſins were laid upon him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He pleadeth for the ſalvation of all Infants who die in their infancy, alledging that Scripture Mark.</hi> 10.14. <hi>ſuffer little children to come unto me, for of ſuch is the Kingdom of GOD. Anſwer.</hi> The <hi>Kingdom of GOD</hi> is taken either for the <hi>Kingdom of Grace,</hi> or for the <hi>Kingdom of Glory:</hi> and ſuch Infants as are ſubjects of his <hi>Kingdom of Grace,</hi> upon whom the Lord exerciſeth a gracious government, in regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating and ſanctifying them: all ſuch Infants ſhal be admitted to the Kingdom of Glory. But how will the Quaker prove that all Infants who die in their infancy, have ſuch s gracious operation in and upon them? Now the Scripture is plaine that there is <hi>that</hi> in Infants, which makes them lyable to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.3. <hi>by nature we are children of wrath,</hi> that is from the very firſt receiving of <hi>our natures and beings,</hi> we receive withal a lyableneſs to the wrath of GOD. And that ſome Infants do pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, may be gathered from that which befell <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrha,</hi> none of the inhabitants were ſpared, no not the Infants and Sucklings: and they were
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:151253:66"/>
not onely conſumed with fire and brimſton; but it is expreſly ſaid that they <hi>ſuffer the vengeance of eternal fire, Jude verſe</hi> 7.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He ſaith, page</hi> 65. <hi>That Chriſt is a Saviour not onely to ſave from ſin, but alſo from the conſequences of ſin, not onely from the fruits and branches of it, but from the ſeed. Anſwer.</hi> Chriſt indeed is a perfect Saviour, and will compleatly ſave his people from <hi>every ſin and evil,</hi> but whom he thus ſaveth, it ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth that they had ſin in them to be ſaved from; but if the Quaker ſpeak truth, Infants have not ſin in them to be ſaved from: for <hi>he ſaith, they are not guilty of Adams ſin, and the ſeed doth not make them guilty of ſin before GOD,</hi> becauſe they do not cloſe with <hi>it:</hi> now actual ſin they have not, ſo that Chriſt is not a Saviour to ſave them from their ſin; and conſequently they are ſhut out from being in the number of Chriſts people. I cannot but take notice of the Gentle-mans <hi>impudence,</hi> or elſe <hi>ignorance,</hi> in bringing that Scripture <hi>Matth.</hi> 1.21. as mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo much againſt us, as if we were for a ſalvation in <hi>our ſins:</hi> whenas nothing can more unjuſtly be charged upon us. We aſſert that whom the Lord ſaveth, he workes in them a deteſtation of ſin, and a purpoſe to come off from all their ſins; and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers them (in this life) from ſin in part, compare <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.6 with <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.20.24. and at death he gives them a total riddance of ſin, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.10.</p>
               <p>To ſay <hi>that Infa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts are ſaved fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſin, becauſe they are not ſuffered to fall into it,</hi> (it might be as well ſaid, that
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:151253:66"/>
                  <hi>Chriſt</hi> died to ſave the Elect holy Angels fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſin, becauſe they are not ſuffered to fall into ſin.) This looks like the old evaſion of the <hi>Pelagians, viz.</hi> that Infants need Chriſt, not to ſave them from ſin, but to bring them to the Kingdom of Heaven: againſt <hi>whom Auguſtin</hi> urged that they divided theſe two names of our Saviour, <hi>Jeſus,</hi> and <hi>Christ,</hi> making him a <hi>Chriſt</hi> where he was not a <hi>Jeſus.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>HEAD. XV. Concerning the perſeverance of the Saints, which Quakers are againſt.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>He addeth, That they hold no ſuch matter as fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling away from Regeneration, and that theſe that fell away never attained to regeneration. Anſ.</hi> Here he ſeeks to hide himſelf, but may eaſily be diſcovered: For is not this the doctrine of Quakers, that <hi>Saints</hi> may fall <hi>totally</hi> and <hi>finally</hi> away from true and ſav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing grace? <hi>G. Keith</hi> in his anſwer to my Queries, ſticks not to ſay, that this is clear both from experience, and abundant teſtimonies of Scripture. Now are not Saints regenerat? What is Regeneration but to be brought into ſuch a ſtate, wherein we are made like GOD in righteouſneſs and holineſs? And this being the ſtate of Saints, then it followeth, that if Saints may fall away <hi>totally</hi> and <hi>finally</hi> (which Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:151253:67"/>
grant) then there may be a total and final fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling away from Regeneration.</p>
               <p>It is in vaine to aſſert a total and final falling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from ſaving grace (becauſe it is ſaid, ſome <hi>who believed afterwards fell away,</hi> and ſome make <hi>ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack of the faith,</hi> and ſome <hi>who taſted the good word of GOD, and the powers of the world to come</hi> fell away.) Seeing it is known that we uſe to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh between <hi>ſeeming, counterfeit grace,</hi> and <hi>ſound, ſaving grace,</hi> between the <hi>common gifts of the Spirit,</hi> and the <hi>ſaving graces of the Spirit:</hi> Now it is incumbent for the Gentle-man to prove, that they who believed &amp; made ſhipwrack of their faith, (or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers who finally fell away) had the <hi>ſound</hi> and <hi>ſav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing graces of the ſpirit,</hi> which is the thing that we deny.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He ſaith, That Philipp.</hi> 1.6. <hi>is to be underſtood no otherwiſe, then as the condition is made good on their part, as Heb.</hi> 3.14. <hi>we are made partakers of Chriſt if we hold faſt unto the end. Anſwer.</hi> The condition which the Lord requires on his peoples part, he promiſeth to enable them to make good, <hi>Ierem.</hi> 32.29. <hi>I will give them one heart, that they may fear me for ever.</hi> Here is a promiſe that GODS People ſhal perſevere in <hi>cleaving to him:</hi> and the promiſe of GOD cannot faile, it is more ſure then Heaven and Earth, <hi>Mark.</hi> 13.31.</p>
               <p>Page 66. in anſwering 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5. <hi>He ſaith ſuch as are keept by the power of GOD, it is through faith, but as they abide not in that power through faith
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:151253:67"/>
but wander from it, they fall, and cannot but fall. Anſwer.</hi> A goodly reply <hi>(forſooth)</hi> which is as if he had ſaid, if the Saints fall from faith, they muſt fall and cannot but fall. (<hi>Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrants</hi> grant that a Believer <hi>quatalis,</hi> as a Believer cannot fall away, but <hi>qui talis eſt,</hi> he that is a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever may fall away.) Now the deſigne of that Scripture 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5. is to ſhew that there are two things concurring to prevent the Saints, <hi>total</hi> and <hi>final fall,</hi> namely, <hi>faith</hi> and the <hi>power of GOD:</hi> both work together to keep the Saints unto Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; that Lord who gives faith unto his people helps them to perſevere in it, for he is not onely the <hi>authour but the finiſher of their faith, Heb.</hi> 12.2.</p>
               <p>In anſwering <hi>Ierem.</hi> 32.40. <hi>He ſaith, it ſhould be tranſlated thus, I will put my fear in their hearts, that they may not depart from me. Anſwer.</hi> The words in the <hi>Hebrew</hi> are, <hi>lebilti ſur megnalai,</hi> which will as well carry ſhal not, as may not depart from me. But granting that the words were tranſlated according to his own deſire, yet they are full e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to prove the Saints perſeverance (the Lord putting his fear into them for this end) GODS love will not ſuffer <hi>him</hi> to depart from the <hi>Saints,</hi> and <hi>fear</hi> will not let them depart from GOD: GOD principles their hearts with ſuch a meaſure of <hi>his dread and fear,</hi> as ſtayes them from an <hi>utter de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partur</hi> from him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He</hi> maketh ſhort work with theſe other Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 10.27.28. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 13.1.1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.19
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:151253:68"/>
                  <hi>ſaying, that they ſpeak of thoſe who were to come to a through regeneration. Anſwer.</hi> This is a bare af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation, without any proof. There is no mention in the texts themſelves of a <hi>through regeneration;</hi> and if it be onely <hi>throughly regenerate,</hi> or <hi>perfectly ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified perſons</hi> that ſhal perſevere; then perſeverance is the priviledge onely of <hi>Saints in Heaven,</hi> (whoſe attainment this perfection is) and not of <hi>Saints on earth</hi> who groan under their imperfections.</p>
               <p>Now ſeeing that Saints who have true and ſaving grace are the Regeneat Children of GOD, (when by faith they receive Chriſt, GOD ownes them for <hi>his children,</hi> and they are <hi>truely regenerat, Gal.</hi> 3.26. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.12.13.) On the other hand <hi>graceleſs perſons</hi> are branded as being the children of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 8.44. Is it not then manifeſt that to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the total and final Apoſtaſy of the Saints from grace, will inferre, that they who are the <hi>children of GOD,</hi> by true regeneration this day, may the next day become the <hi>children of the Devil?</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the grace that they have <hi>now,</hi> they may utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly loſe it, erre to <hi>morrow.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He asketh, whether I look upon the Quakers as having fallen away? Anſwer.</hi> His book (contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nor onely his privat ſentiments, but the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon opinions of Quakers) is a ſufficient proof that they have apoſtatized and fallen from the <hi>truth:</hi> and ſuch of them as have felt a gracious operation on their hearts, (but in this houre of <hi>temptation</hi> are under a ſad <hi>ſnare</hi>) I truſt the Lord will convince
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:151253:68"/>
them, and grant them repentance to the acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement of the truth: that by their ryſing againe they may edify and rejoice thoſe Souls whom they have wounded, and ſtumbled by their fall.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>HEAD. XVI. Concerning the hazard and danger of Quakeriſm.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. I. It tends to the neglect of that Worſhip which is due to GOD.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He ſaith page</hi> 67. <hi>That they deny not true wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, but onely our Idolatrous worſhip. Anſwer.</hi> If our Worſhip were <hi>Idolatrous,</hi> they had reaſon to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny it; but it is unreaſonable to call our Worſhip Idolatrous, when they have not a ſhadow of reaſon to prove it to be ſo, unleſs the Gentle-man think that (<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>) the Quakers naked affirmation is a ſufficient reaſon. Now it is manifeſt that Quakers refuſe GOD the worſhip which is due to him in
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:151253:69"/>
the uſe of the creatures, in that they can, and do ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture to uſe theſe, without ſeeking GODS Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing upon them: which hath been (by former Saints) accounted a <hi>profane cuſtome,</hi> utterly unfit to be heard of, among Chriſtians profeſſing the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and fear of GOD! Are we not commanded to eat and drink to the glory of GOD? 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.31. And muſt we not then look up to GOD, and deſire his help to improve the creatures to his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry? Beſids the creatures of themſelves cannot nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh us, if GOD deny his bleſſing, our eating and drinking can do us no good: and therefore we have need to addreſs our ſelves to GOD by prayer; for by <hi>this means</hi> the bleſſing is obtained, and the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures come to be <hi>ſanctified to us,</hi> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.4.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Object. To receive the benefits and gifts of GOD with thanksgiving, and to witneſs it ſanctified to us by the word and prayer is owned by us. Anſwer.</hi> Do Quakers witneſs the creatures ſanctified to them by prayer, when yet they do not pray for the ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed uſe of them? Pray, obſerve the way that Chriſt tooke (his example is worth our imitation) at the receiving of the creatures he lookt up to Heaven for <hi>a bleſſing, Mark.</hi> 6.14. <hi>and gave thanks, Matth.</hi> 15.36. and this appeares to have been his ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry practiſe, he was <hi>knowne of his Diſciples in break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bread:</hi> it being his ordinary manner to <hi>bleſs</hi> the bread (in ſome ſpecial way) which he break, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he was diſcerned and differenced from others <hi>Luk.</hi> 24.30.31.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="121" facs="tcp:151253:69"/>
                     <hi>Object. It is uſual among us, when we ſit down, to waite upon the Lord for ſometime, that we may know our ſelves ſtated in his fear, and as there we ſtand, outward expreſſions may be uttered by us. Anſwer.</hi> When <hi>they</hi> are not thus ſtated in GODS fear, yet they have liberty and freedom to fall to meat: ſo it would ſeeme though they will not pray <hi>without fear,</hi> yet they can eate <hi>without fear,</hi> which is the character of wicked perſons, <hi>Jude, verſe</hi> 12. As for their waiting (its but an engine to overthrow Scripture precepts) ſeeing it hath reference to a <hi>new inward command,</hi> without <hi>which</hi> they do not hold themſelves obliged, to expreſs their deſire in words, but as they are thus required of them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He addeth page</hi> 68. <hi>That to ſay, that a man can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, nor ought not to pray without (an impulſe) the ſpirits drawing, and motion, hath no bad tendency, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all ſuch prayers, as are performed without the help of the ſpirit, are abomination, not true prayers, but hypocritical and deceitful. Anſwer.</hi> We grant theſe things. Firſt, That the <hi>ſpirit</hi> teacheth and helpeth the Saints to pray, ſometimes they are ſo ſtirred and moved to prayer, that they cannot be at quiet; but they muſt to ſome ſecret corner: and there poure out their complaints before the LORD, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.6. Secondly, That the ſeaſon when the <hi>ſpirit</hi> moveth to duty, ſhould be laid hold on, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.8. <hi>when thou ſaidſt ſeek ye my face, my heart ſaid unto thee, thy face I will ſeek.</hi> Thirdly, When the ſpirit moveth the w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ek is ſweeteſt; then
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:151253:70"/>
the Chriſtian is cheerful in the exerciſe of duty. The joy that is in a <hi>little hearty praying,</hi> is beyond all the joyes that the world can afford, <hi>Iſaiah.</hi> 56.7. Fourthly, Perſons cannot pray aright without the <hi>ſpirit,</hi> and therefore the prayers of the wicked are ſaid to be <hi>an abomination unto the Lord. Prov.</hi> 15.8. But it muſt be obſerved, that though prayer with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the <hi>ſpirit</hi> be an <hi>abomination</hi> to GOD; yet o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of prayer is <hi>double abomination:</hi> the reaſon is, becauſe to pray without the ſpirit, is a ſin for the <hi>manner,</hi> but to neglect prayer is a ſin, both as to <hi>mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> and <hi>manner.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He addeth, whoſoever can pray to the Lord in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, let him pray, but that any can pray without the ſpirit, that we deny. Anſwer.</hi> May he not accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to this way of reaſoning, take men off from eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing? If <hi>they</hi> can eate to the <hi>glory of GOD</hi> indeed, then let them eate; but that they can eate to the glory of GOD, without the ſpirit: thats denyed. Likewiſe he may take men off from the works of their calling, for as the praying, ſo the <hi>plowing of the wicked is ſin, Prov.</hi> 21.4.</p>
                  <p>A motion of the ſpirit, is an encouragement to, but it is not our alone warrant for prayer: GOD in his word hath commanded prayer, 1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.17. <hi>pray without ceaſing:</hi> in obedience to this <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand</hi> we ought to ſet to the duty. And if it be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged that we ſhould pray (when we have the <hi>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi>) without ceaſing; but not otherwiſe: it may as well be ſaid, that children ſhould <hi>honour</hi> their
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:151253:70"/>
Parents, and husbands <hi>love</hi> their wives, when they have a <hi>motion</hi> of the ſpirit to it; but in the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of this <hi>motion,</hi> they may omit theſe duties.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He asketh, what ground I have to believe, that ſome Quakers for the ſpace of a whole yeare, have not ſo much as once bowed a knee to call upon GOD in their families? Anſwer.</hi> There is too much ground for the belief of it: their infrequency in family prayer, is too palpable. One of <hi>them</hi> confeſſed (whom I forbear to name) that now he was come to that <hi>pitch,</hi> that he prayed alwayes: and though heretofore he was wont to call his family together, and pray with them; yet he had not done ſo for a twelve moneth paſt. Is this a lovly Religion which takes men off from family prayer? It is a miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſhift, to tell that friends of <hi>truth,</hi> who have any whom they can joyne with: do meet, waite, and pray together. Now grant that perſons in <hi>Quakers families</hi> were enemies to truth, would it not be a work of charity, and demonſtration of love and tenderneſs to their ſouls, to pray with them, and for them? Muſt not <hi>Abraham</hi> keep up Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion in his familie, becauſe an <hi>Iſhmael</hi> was in it? Nor <hi>David</hi> becauſe of the preſence of <hi>Abſolom?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Page</hi> 69. <hi>He looketh upon me, as one wholly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acquainted with the wayes and motions of the ſpirit, for ſuppoſing that an impulſe of the ſpirit, may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed for many yeares. Anſwer.</hi> Is there not ground to ſuppoſe, that men may turne looſe negligent, and defective in waiting, even for ſeveral yeares:
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:151253:71"/>
If ſo, then the <hi>motions</hi> of the ſpirit may be denyed to them, (which he acknowledges are frequent, but to thoſe that waite for them) and therefore all that time that they (who neglect to waite) want the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the ſpirit: they muſt not adventure upon prayer: yea they muſt not pray, though they were at the gates of <hi>death,</hi> and in danger of <hi>preſent drowning.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is true <hi>he</hi> conceives, that at ſuch a ſeaſon the breathings of the <hi>ſpirit</hi> will not be wanting to the <hi>Saints;</hi> but what ſhal the wicked do in this caſe; Muſt they keep ſilent? Shal it not be lawful for them, to follow the advice which the Apoſtle gave to <hi>Simon Magus? Act.</hi> 8.22. <hi>pray GOD if per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps the thoughts of thy heart may be forgiven thee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Quakers <hi>principle</hi> is, that men ſhould not pray without a <hi>motion</hi> of the <hi>ſpirit.</hi> Now ſuppoſe that perſons contract guilt by their not <hi>waiting,</hi> hereby provoking the Lord to withhold the <hi>motions</hi> of his <hi>Spirit</hi> from them: then theſe motions being with-held, their not praying is not ſin: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they need not to be troubled for their omiſſion of prayer. Now doth not this tend to lull people aſleep in ſecurity, and to keep them from charging themſelves with that ſin: which without repentance GOD will charge upon them? for he will call ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to an account for their omiſſions, as well as for their commiſſions.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <pb n="125" facs="tcp:151253:71"/>
                  <head>SECT. II. Quakeriſme tends to render Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification of ſin uſeleſs.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He asketh page</hi> 70. <hi>Whether mortification of ſin be uſeleſs, where the end of it (which is perfection) is attained? Anſwer.</hi> There is a <hi>twofold perfection;</hi> namely, <hi>comparative,</hi> and <hi>abſolute;</hi> the Apoſtle ſpeaketh of both theſe kinds of <hi>perfection, Philipp.</hi> 3. and denyeth to himſelf <hi>an abſolute, compleate per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection,</hi> verſe 12. <hi>not as though I had already at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, either were already perfect.</hi> Yet he out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtripped many others in holineſs, and ſo had a <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parative perfection,</hi> verſe 13. <hi>let us therefore, as many as be perfect, be thus minded.</hi> Now when there is an <hi>abſolute, compleate perfection</hi> (which is the thing the Quaker pleads for) without the leaſt indwelling corruption and ſin: to ſuch there is no uſe for <hi>mortification.</hi> Perſons need not to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up in <hi>killing ſin</hi> (which is the importance of the word <hi>mortifie</hi>) that have not ſin in them to be killed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He</hi> quarrels at my ſaying, the opinion of a ſinleſs perfection in this life wounds the very vitals of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and here the Quaker triumphs (but it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:151253:72"/>
the victory;) Asking, <hi>Whether the vitals of Religion conſist in ſinning or not ſinning? Anſwer.</hi> The <hi>vitals</hi> of Religion conſiſt in the <hi>means</hi> appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by GOD, (and diligent improvment thereof) for ſubduing and bearing down ſin: ſuch as <hi>prayer, repentance, mortification, believing, application of the Blood of Christ,</hi> And though the Quakers grant that <hi>theſe things</hi> are needful for attaining unto perfection yet ſuppoſing a ſinles perfection to be actually attai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned unto (by men in this world) what need is there then to pray for <hi>pardon of ſin, to repent of ſin, apply Chriſts blood</hi> for cleanſing <hi>from ſin?</hi> Seeing there is no ſin to be <hi>pardoned, repented of,</hi> or <hi>cleanſed from.</hi> And therefore (the Gentle-man not denying that ſuch conſequences do flow from <hi>his principle</hi>) he is faine to ſhift, ſaying, <hi>that they who come to perfection witneſs the true uſe of theſe things;</hi> but in the meane time he ſhould remember, that (under a pretence of perfection) <hi>he</hi> takes them off from the practiſe and uſe of the <hi>aforementioned duties and means;</hi> and ſo Chriſtianity in the <hi>vitals</hi> of it is ſtruck at.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He accuſes me of confuſion and contradiction, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe (as he ſaith) I would inferre a ſinleſs man to be a ſinning man. Anſwer.</hi> Is it either confuſion or a contradiction to affirme one of the Quakers con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitedly ſinleſs men (to be ſinful) who pretending to be without ſin; yet diſcover much ſin, by their <hi>pride, paſſion, bitterneſs, cenſuring</hi> and <hi>condemning</hi> others, and <hi>vilifying</hi> them by <hi>opprobrious termes,</hi> and <hi>railing accuſations:</hi> if ſuch ſay, they have no
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:151253:72"/>
ſin, <hi>they are but liars, and the truth is not in them,</hi> 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.8. It is remarkable, to conſider whom the Apoſtle ſpeaketh of, <hi>if we</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>what we?</hi> look to verſe 1. <hi>we that have heard and ſeen and handled the word of life;</hi> verſe third, <hi>we who have fellowſhip with the Father, and with his Son Jeſus Christ, verſe</hi> 7, <hi>we who</hi> (by our Juſtification) <hi>are cleanſed from the guilt of all ſin;</hi> yet it <hi>we</hi> ſay, we have no ſin, we are not <hi>ſincere</hi> but <hi>hypocrites,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving both our ſelves and others.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Object. This Scripture</hi> 1. <hi>Iob.</hi> 1.8. <hi>is conditional, otherwiſe it would contradict what followes, verſe</hi> 9. <hi>and chapter</hi> 2.4. <hi>and chapter</hi> 3.9. <hi>Anſwer.</hi> There is no contradiction; but ſweet agreement between theſe Scriptures: for verſe 9. ſpeaketh of <hi>forgivneſs of ſin,</hi> (which conſiſteth in freedom from the guilt of ſin) and this may be where ſin is nor utterly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſhed. And 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.4. is underſtood of a <hi>ſincere</hi> nor <hi>abſolutlie perfect</hi> keeping of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of GOD. And as for 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.9. it was formerly opened, and may be further cleared by comparing it with chapter 5.16. where the Apoſtle ſpeaketh of a <hi>ſin unto death,</hi> which they that are <hi>born</hi> of <hi>GOD</hi> cannot commit, verſe 18. <hi>we know that whoſoever is born of GOD ſinneth not, but he that is begotten of GOD, keepeth himſelf and the wicked one toucheth him not:</hi> That is, ſo as to draw him to that <hi>unpardonable ſin,</hi> the Child of GOD is ſecured from <hi>this ſin.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:151253:73"/>
               <head>HEAD. XVII. Wherein Truth is cleared of Calumnies.</head>
               <p>Page 72. <hi>He</hi> cometh to examine whether <hi>their</hi> or <hi>our</hi> principles will be moſt acceptable to the wicked. And firſt, <hi>he ſaith, wicked men and hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites love well to hear, that they can never be free from their ſins in this life. Anſwer.</hi> Some wicked men, are ſo well conceited of the <hi>honeſty</hi> and <hi>integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> of their hearts, that it is a hard thing, to get con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victions of ſin faſtened upon them: and as for <hi>mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification</hi> of ſin, which we urge as neceſſary to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; there is nothing more diſtaſtful to the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked then this.</p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>He ſaith, they love well to hear, to be juſtified by Christ without them. Anſwer.</hi> How is it then, that ſo many wicked men, ſcoff at juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation by Chriſts righteouſneſs without them? Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling [in contempt] this imputed righteouſneſs an <hi>imaginary, putative</hi> righteouſneſs. Is it not natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral for perſons to ſeek to be juſtified by ſomething <hi>within</hi> them?</p>
               <p>Thirdly, <hi>He ſaith, they love well to hear, that the words without them are the onely rule. Anſwer.</hi> Doubtleſs there are many wicked perſons, who
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:151253:73"/>
could wiſh there were no <hi>ſuch rule.</hi> Hath it not been the attempt of the wicked to deſtroy the <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures?</hi> In the tenth Perſecution the <hi>books</hi> of the holy Scriptures were ordered to be burnt: and to this day there is a ſecret enmity in the hearts of thouſands of ſinners againſt the <hi>Scriptures.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, <hi>He ſaith, they love well to hear, that they may uſe the cuſtomes and faſhions of this world, and that they may uſe ſports, games, and playes, and weare laces, ribbons, &amp;c. Anſwer.</hi> They hear from none of <hi>us</hi> any thing to encourage them in following ſinful cuſtomes and faſhions: theſe we oppoſe, yea, we think that people ſhould be ſparing even as to lawful games and recreations. As for wearing <hi>ribbons, laces, gold-rings, &amp;c.</hi> we judge it not ſimply <hi>unlawful;</hi> and yet perſons ſin, when in this they exceed their <hi>degree</hi> and <hi>rank:</hi> which is the thing condemned by the Apoſtle, 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.9.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, <hi>He ſaith, they love well to hear, that men must not expect to hear GOD immediatly. Anſ.</hi> Some of them know not what is intended by GODS <hi>immediate ſpeaking,</hi> and others have no liking to hear GOD <hi>mediatly</hi> by the Miniſtry of his Word: this is a burdenſome ſtone, that they would faine be rid of.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, <hi>He ſaith, they love well to hear, that water Baptiſm, and giving of Bread and Wine are the Ordinances of Chriſt; for then they think they are Chriſtians, if they partake of theſe outward things, Anſwer. Our</hi> endeavour is to take them off from
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:151253:74"/>
their <hi>groundleſs thoughts:</hi> telling them that out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward priviledges muſt not be reſted on, and that who ever build their hopes of Heaven meerly upon theſe, they build upon the ſand, a foundation which will faile them in the day of their ſtraite.</p>
               <p>Seventhly, <hi>He ſaith, that none plead more for the obſervation of the Sabbath, then profane light men. Anſwer.</hi> The <hi>contrary</hi> is abundantly known, for none are greater enemies then they to the <hi>true</hi> obſervation of the Sabbath: which muſt be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voted entirely to GOD, and ſpent in the publick and private exerciſes of his worſhip and ſervice. Are not the wicked brought in ſaying, <hi>when ſhal the Sabbath be gone? Amos</hi> 8.5.</p>
               <p>Eightly, <hi>He ſaith, they love well to hear, that they may be members of a Church, though they have no infallible evidence of holineſs. Anſwer.</hi> Have all the members of the Quakers Church infallible evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences of grace and holineſs? I muſt be free to tell you, that <hi>your raw, conceity Proſelyts,</hi> are ſo <hi>ignorant,</hi> and yet ſo <hi>confident,</hi> that ſober men ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect them to be in a fools paradiſe.</p>
               <p>Ninthly, <hi>He ſaith, they love well to hear of our Doctrine of Election and Reprobation. Anſwer.</hi> I have heard diverſe of <hi>them (Pelagians</hi> mocked at predeſtination) wrangle againſt this doctrine, and herein <hi>Quakers</hi> joyne with <hi>them;</hi> but the truth will ſtand firme againſt them both.</p>
               <p>Tenthly, <hi>He ſaith, they love our Doctrine of once in grace and ever in grace. Anſwer.</hi> What
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:151253:74"/>
ground can <hi>graceleſs perſons</hi> have to like this? (<hi>they</hi> being alienated from the life of GOD) the promiſe of perſevering in grace doth not belong to them: and we do not plead for a <hi>wild perſeverance,</hi> the Saints who have had moſt perſwaſions of their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeverance, have been moſt cloſs and circumſpect in their walk with GOD. Thus it is evident that <hi>our principles</hi> do not gratifie the wicked, nor give them the leſt allowance in licentiouſneſs and looſneſs: and if any of us be looſs and licentious (as a lace, there be too many!) it is our principle, that the <hi>wrath of GOD will come upon ſuch children of diſobedience.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>HEAD. XVIII. The Quakers tenents are pleaſing to the Wicked.</head>
               <p>The Quakers religion is exceeding ſuitable to <hi>carnal hearts.</hi> Firſt, <hi>They</hi> love well to hear, that a ſufficient light is in them, that Chriſt (and ſaving grace) is in them. Secondly, <hi>They</hi> love well to hear that <hi>all dayes</hi> are alike, and that men may work and plough on the Sabbath as well as on any other day. Thirdly, <hi>They</hi> love well to hear, that Family Prayer is but a forme. Fourthly, <hi>They</hi> love well to hear that they muſt not pray in ſecret; but when they have an <hi>inward</hi> drawing and motion
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:151253:75"/>
to it. Fifthly, <hi>They</hi> love well to hear <hi>outward teaching</hi> cryed down: and mind the <hi>light within,</hi> here is your teacher and this light is not a <hi>chapter without you,</hi> in a book. Sixthly, <hi>They</hi> love well to hear the holieſt Miniſters ſpoken againſt, as <hi>hirel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings,</hi> and <hi>Baals Prieſts.</hi> Seventhly, <hi>They</hi> love well to hear, the LORDS Ordinances vilified and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached: carnal Bread and Wine, is lovely lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage to them. Eightly, <hi>They</hi> love well to hear, that <hi>Adams</hi> ſin is not theirs, and that the <hi>evil ſeed</hi> doth not make them guilty of ſin before GOD, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till they cloſe with it. Ninthly, <hi>They</hi> love well to hear, that they may ſit down to eate, and drink, and riſe up againe without a word of thankſgiving or prayer to GOD. But I am tyred with raking in this Dung hill. I leave it to unbyaſſed perſons to judge, whether <hi>theſe principles</hi> will not ſure with carnal hearts? Will not the wicked be glade to hear theſe things cryed down, which they themſelves live down, and cannot be brought up to the practiſe of them?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He ſhuts up his book charging me with a notorious lie. Anſ.</hi> Wherein am I guilty of <hi>lying?</hi> The Dialogue ſuppoſed <hi>A Conference between an enemy to, &amp; a Lover of the Truth;</hi> and might I not (without a lie) teſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tify ſo much love to mens Souls, as to expreſs pity toward the ſeduced, wiſhing GOD to (reclaime them, and to) confirme his people in his wayes? What is it that ſome will not carp at? Epecially, the perſons that I have to do with: of whom a pious
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:151253:75" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Miniſter in <hi>England,</hi> giveth this teſtimony, ſaith he, <hi>We have a ſtrange generation of men abroad, whoſe very Religion conſiſts in railing, reviling, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching the Servants of the living GOD, not the beſt men, nor the beſt Miniſters under Heaven can e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape them.</hi> Then he ſets down a letter, wherein the Quakers gave the Miniſters of Chriſt theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing names; <hi>Conjurers, Theeves, Robbers, Anti-Chriſts, Witches, Blind-guides, Devils, Lyars, Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblers, Baals Prieſts, a Vipe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ous and Serpenti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Generation, Bloody Herodians, Blaſphemers, Scarlet coloured Beaſts, Babilons Merchants, Buſie-Bodies, Whited walls, Painted Sepulchres, reavening Wolves, Perſecutors, Tyrants, greedie Dogs, Phariſees!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then <hi>he</hi> gives good advice, Chriſtians (ſaith <hi>he</hi>) when ye hear this language learne to conforme your ſelves to Chriſt, go ye firſt to GOD with the LORDS own plea. <hi>Zach.</hi> 3.2. <hi>Now the LORD rebuke thee O Satan, even the Lord that hath choſen Jeruſalem rebuke thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>See <hi>Ambroſe</hi> his looking unto <hi>Jeſus,</hi> pag. 1006.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
